<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/healthcurr18.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Active Living">
    <strand_text>Active Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="A1">
        <overall_text>A1. participate actively and regularly in a wide variety of physical activities, and demonstrate an understanding of the value of regular physical activity in their daily lives</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A1.1 actively participate in a wide variety of program activities (e.g., tag games, cooperative games, movement exploration with equipment, dance, outdoor activities), according to their capabilities, while applying behaviours that enhance their readiness and ability to take part (e.g., trying new activities, being engaged and maintaining movement throughout the activity, actively cooperating with peers, having the required equipment to take part, accepting and showing respect for others in the group, listening actively, following rules, playing fair) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “You and your classmates will be participating in a lot of different physical activities together this year. Remember, when playing with others, it’s always important to show respect and to follow the rules. What are some examples of showing respect and following rules in your daily life?” 

Students: “We show respect for other people and for things, too. We show respect for other cultures, for our own family and other people’s families, for our friends, and also for the environment. We show respect for other people by working well together at school or greeting people politely when we are introduced.” “We show that we respect the environment by turning off lights when we are not in the room, by not littering, and, whenever we can, by walking, wheeling, or biking instead of using a car.” “We also follow many different kinds of rules at home and in our communities. For example, a rule that we follow to stay safe is to always tell an adult when we are going to play outside, so they will know where we are.”
</specific>
          <specific>A1.2 demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to their personal enjoyment of being active (e.g., having the opportunity to participate fully in all aspects of an activity, having support from their peers, being exposed to a variety of activities, being outdoors) as they participate in a wide variety of individual and small-group activities [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What kinds of physical activities do you like best?”

Student: “I like games in which everyone gets to play and people are not eliminated. If you get eliminated, you do not get the chance to play and get better at the activity.”</specific>
          <specific>A1.3 describe the benefits of participating in physical activity every day (e.g., physical benefits, such as better sleep, more energy, reduced risk of getting sick; social benefits, such as improved interaction with peers, greater empathy, stronger interpersonal skills, improved independence; emotional/mental benefits, such as stress release, greater self-confidence, improved concentration) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Being physically active has many benefits, such as giving us more energy to play with friends. What are some other benefits of being active every day?”

Student: “I have so much fun when my friend and I go skating after school. Being active every day helps me feel alert and prepared for school.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the importance of being physically active, and apply physical fitness concepts and practices that contribute to healthy, active living</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A2.1 Daily physical activity (DPA): participate in sustained moderate to vigorous physical activity, with appropriate warm-up and cool-down activities, to the best of their ability for a minimum of twenty minutes each day (e.g., moving to music at a variety of speeds during warm-up, participating in a variety of dance activities, moving on scooter boards) [PS]
</specific>
          <specific>A2.2 identify new capabilities and other benefits that may result from improved cardiorespiratory fitness (e.g., being able to sustain activity over a greater distance or longer period of time, requiring shorter rest periods, feeling better after activity) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “We have been doing a lot of physical activities that work our hearts over the past two weeks. How will continuing to do this type of activity improve your fitness?”

Students: “Physical activity is good for the heart because the heart is like other muscles and it works better when it gets exercise. Today I snowshoed all the way up the hill and didn’t need to stop and take a break.” “I find it a lot easier to push myself up a ramp in my wheelchair since I’ve been doing exercises to build up my arm strength.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.3 assess their degree of physical exertion during cardiorespiratory fitness activities, using simple self-assessment methods (e.g., talk test, breath sound check, increase in heart rate or breathing rate, change in how one feels during the activity) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “How did you check how you were feeling during today’s activity?” 
Student: “I did the talk test. I knew my heart and lungs were working too hard because I couldn’t breathe and talk with my partner while I was running. I needed to slow down for a while to catch my breath.” </specific>
          <specific>A2.4 develop and act on personal goals related to physical activity (e.g., jumping rope continuously for a specified period of time, doing something active indoors or outdoors with family members on the weekend) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What goal have you set for yourself, and how will this goal help you?”

Student: “My goal is to be able to do all the DPA activities without needing to stop and rest in the middle. When I can do that, I’ll know that I’m getting fitter and healthier.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate responsibility for their own safety and the safety of others as they participate in physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A3.1 demonstrate behaviours and apply procedures that maximize their safety and that of others during physical activity (e.g., self-monitoring, being in control of themselves and aware of their surroundings, cooperating with others, abiding by rules and playing fairly, communicating positively to help others be safe, using equipment appropriately both in class and on the playground) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What do you need to do to be safe when playing wall ball? When using a scooter board?”

Students: “When I’m playing wall ball, I need to be aware of how much space there is around me and also of how hard I throw. If I throw the ball too hard at the wall, it may come back really fast and hit me or someone else.” “When I’m using a scooter board, I need to be careful not to get my fingers caught underneath. I should always sit or kneel and not stand on the board. I need to keep my hair away from the wheels. I need to stay in control when I move and be careful not to bump into other people or things.”
</specific>
          <specific>A3.2 describe how to respond to accidents or injuries incurred while participating in physical activity (e.g., remain calm, stop all activity and hold the equipment, ask an injured person if he or she needs help, tell an adult what happened, avoid crowding the person who is injured) [PS, CT]
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>

    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Movement">
    <strand_text>Movement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
	  <overall id="B1">
        <overall_text>perform movement skills, demonstrating awareness of the basic requirements of the skills and applying movement concepts as appropriate, as they engage in a variety of physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B1.1 perform controlled transitions between static positions, using different body parts and shapes and different levels, with and without equipment (e.g., move smoothly between yoga positions, from a stork balance to a standing-scale balance, from a knee scale on a bench to a standing position on the bench) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Create a balance by making a twisted shape with your body at a low level and another using a wide shape at a medium level. When you are ready, demonstrate a controlled transition between the two balances. What helps you control the transition?”

Student: “To move in control from one balance to another, I keep my eyes focused on one spot, I move slowly, and I hold my muscles tight. I can move more smoothly if I take a breath before I move, then let my breath out slowly as I’m moving. I also need to think about the order of my movements.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.2 demonstrate the ability to jump for distance or height, using two-foot and one-foot take-offs, while remaining in control (e.g., jump high over lines or blocks; jump far past markers, over beanbags, or into a hula hoop that is held horizontally a short distance above the ground) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “To jump far or high and land safely, what do you need to do?”

Student: “I need to start by bending my knees and crouching, so when I take off, I can push hard on the ground and stretch out my body to get farther or higher. To land safely, I need to bend my knees to cushion my landing and keep my feet apart, my head up, and my arms out.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.3 perform a variety of locomotor movements with and without equipment, alone and with others, moving at different levels, using different pathways, and travelling in different directions (e.g., leap for distance in a zigzag pathway; alternate between walking and sprinting in a warm-up activity; travel sideways, alternately reaching high then bending low to touch the ground; move as close to others as possible without touching them, then far from others to find their own space; skip with a partner, matching their steps and arm actions; make patterns with a scarf; make up a movement sequence in response to action words or words of a poem) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “When you are changing direction or moving around an object, how is your movement different from when you are going in a straight line?”

Students: “I slow down a little to make sure I am in control.” “I hold tight to my walker, look to make sure the way is clear to move it, and then turn it in the new direction.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.5 retain objects of different shapes and sizes in different ways, using different body parts and equipment (e.g., carry a beach ball while running and tag others with it in a game; balance a ball on a racket; hold a plastic ball in a scoop while jogging; control a ball with right and left feet while moving around pylons; bounce a ball using dominant and non-dominant hands while seated or kneeling) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What can you do to maintain control as you are moving (dribbling) a ball with your feet?”

Student: “I bend my knees and use the sides of my feet to keep the ball close to my feet as I move it.”

Teacher: “Can you dribble the ball using both your left foot and your right foot? Why is it important to be able to dribble using both feet?”

Student: “It lets me move in different ways quickly and makes it difficult for others to get the ball away from me.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="B2">
        <overall_text>apply movement strategies appropriately, demonstrating an understanding of the components of a variety of physical activities, in order to enhance their ability to participate successfully in those activities.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B2.1 demonstrate an understanding that different physical activities have different components (e.g., movement skills, rules and boundaries, conventions of fair play and etiquette), and apply this understanding as they participate in and explore a variety of individual and small-group activities [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “When you are demonstrating your dance sequence to others, what things do you need to think about to make your demonstration most effective?”

Student: “We should have a ‘front’ for our sequence, so our audience can see well. We should have a starting position that we hold still.” 

Teacher prompt: “What skills are you using at each station in the activity circuit? What guidelines do you need to follow so that the activity goes well?”

Student: “We are practising different throwing, catching, and jumping skills at different stations. At the first jumping station, we are working on jumping to touch the wall as high up as we can. At the second jumping station, we are trying to jump as far as we can from the line. There are a few throwing and catching stations where we are practising throwing and catching by throwing through hoops, throwing at a target, and catching with our hands, with scoops, and when holding small nets, blankets, or towels with a partner. At each station, we take turns and share the equipment. When the music stops, we stop right away and get ready to move to the next station. We record how we are feeling and how we are doing on our tracking sheets.” 

Teacher prompt: “When playing a tag game like cat and mouse, how do you play fairly, showing use of etiquette?”

Student: “I follow the rules. If I am tagged, I switch roles to be a chaser without arguing.”</specific>
          <specific>B2.2 apply a variety of simple tactics to increase their chances of success during physical activities (e.g., assume a ready position in preparation to receive the ball when playing small-sided games such as two-on-two or to be ready for a quick start in a race; practise a balance routine on a line in the gymnasium while waiting for a turn on a balance beam or a bench) [PS, CT]* 

Teacher prompt: “What did you and your partner do well when working together in your activity? What could you work on next time?”

Student: “We worked together well when we were playing the ‘popcorn’ game. In this game, you have to try to bounce the balls off the parachute while other people try to keep throwing the balls back onto the parachute. My partner was beside me and we worked well together because we cooperated to lift the parachute, then ‘snap’ it down quickly together to bounce the balls off. Next time, we could work at paying attention the whole time so we are ready when the balls come our way.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
	 </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Healthy Living">
    <strand_text>Healthy Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
	        <overall id="C1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to healthy development</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C1.1 demonstrate an understanding of how the origins of food (e.g., where the food is grown, how it is made) affect its nutritional value and environmental impact [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What is the difference between processed and unprocessed foods (e.g., processed cheese and a wedge of cheese, toasted oat cereal and large-flake oatmeal, a fruit roll-up and an apple)?”

Student: “Unprocessed foods are foods that are raw or the way they were before they were processed. Processed foods have been changed in some way to help preserve them or make them more convenient to use or easier to sell.”

Teacher: “Processed foods lose some of their nutrients when they are manufactured. How else are processed foods different from fresh foods in terms of nutrients? What is the environmental impact of processed foods?”

Student: “Fresh foods can be healthier to eat. Processed foods have more sugar, salt, trans fats, and other things added to improve the flavour or colour or to help preserve them. The way processed foods are made and the way they have to be shipped can make air pollution and other environmental problems worse. Manufacturing them can also make water pollution worse, and the packaging they come in creates extra garbage.” Substance Use, Addictions, and Related Behaviours</specific>
          <specific>C1.2 demonstrate an understanding of different types of legal and illegal substance abuse (e.g., dependency on nicotine in cigarettes or caffeine in coffee, energy drinks, and colas, or sugar and salt in sports drinks, or alcohol in beer, wine, and spirits) and the impacts of abusing these substances on themselves and others (e.g., dependencies or addictions, financial stresses, legal issues, health issues, environmental issues) 

Teacher prompt: “When a family member is abusing alcohol, there is an impact on him or her, but there is also an impact on others. What impact does it have on others in the family?”

Student: “People who abuse alcohol may not be able to take good care of their families. They may miss important events, spend money on alcohol that is needed for other things, or get involved in arguments. Sometimes emotional or physical abuse happens in families if someone is abusing alcohol.”

Teacher: “Pop and sports drinks are not illegal substances, but consuming too much of them can still lead to problems. What problems might be associated with drinking too much of these kinds of drinks?”

Student: “Drinking too much of these drinks can give you more caffeine, sugar, or salt than is good for your body. Too much caffeine can make you jittery or too excited and may even make you addicted to caffeine. When you are addicted to caffeine, you sometimes get a headache when you do not have the caffeine. Too much sugar can lead to tooth decay. Too much salt makes your blood pressure go up and is not good for the heart. Also, you can get too full drinking these drinks and then not eat enough healthy foods.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to apply health knowledge and living skills to make reasoned decisions and take appropriate actions relating to their personal health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C2.1 demonstrate an understanding of the importance of good oral health to overall health, and assess the effect of different food choices on oral health [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Problems with teeth or gums can be painful, can make it difficult to eat, and can affect our appearance. Oral health problems can also contribute to health problems that affect other parts of the body, like the heart, lungs, and digestive system. We can keep our teeth healthy by brushing and flossing and going to the dentist for regular checkups. Being careful about what we eat can also help. What kinds of foods should you limit? What could you eat instead?”

Student: “I should limit the amount of sugary foods that I eat, especially those like sticky popcorn or candy apples that stick to your teeth. I can eat apples without the candy coating instead, or a piece of cheese, or vegetables such as carrots or radishes.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.2 apply their understanding of good safety practices by developing safety guidelines for a variety of places and situations outside the classroom (e.g., guidelines for water safety; safe routes and practices for going to school; home fire safety and emergency plans; safe camping checklists; guidelines for safe Internet use; personal hygiene guidelines; wildlife safety precautions; guidelines for managing allergies; Halloween safety practices; rules for behaviour around guide dogs, other service animals, and animals in general) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some examples of how you might prepare yourself or your family to respond in an emergency - like a fall into deep water or a house fire?” 

Student: “In an emergency, it helps to have a plan. To prepare for an emergency around water, I could learn basic swimming skills, such as finding the surface, supporting myself at the surface, and swimming a short distance. I could also learn about basic boating safety rules, such as wearing a personal flotation device whenever I’m in a boat and staying with the boat if it overturns. To prepare for a home emergency like a fire, I could help make a family escape plan that we could use in case of fire, with escape routes and meeting places.” 

Teacher prompt: “How do you stay safe when walking to school?”

Student: “I am careful when going by driveways and parking lots. I make eye contact with drivers before crossing the road, so that I know they have seen me. I walk with someone else.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.3 apply decision-making strategies to make healthy choices about behaviours and the use of various substances in ways that could lead to dependencies, identifying factors that should be considered (e.g., short-term use of medications can be helpful for an illness, but misuse of some medications could lead to dependency or harm; moderated television watching or computer use can provide healthy entertainment or new learning or be necessary to complete school work, but too much screen time can reinforce sedentary habits and inactivity, which can lead to social isolation and increased vulnerability to physical ailments; cultural teachings can provide guidance when considering the impact of using substances) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What can you do to make healthier choices about substances or dependent behaviours?”

Student: “I need to think about what is healthy for me and what could be harmful and also what is legal and illegal. I can collect information and check facts about what I hear. I can find out where to get help if needed. I can pay attention to my choices and my behaviour and think about what needs to change. I can discuss things that are a problem with a friend or an adult and start looking for solutions.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to make connections that relate to health and well-being - how their choices and behaviours affect both themselves and others, and how factors in the world around them affect their own and others’ health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C3.1 explain how local fresh foods and foods from different cultures (e.g., berries, curries, chapattis, lychees, kale, lentils, corn, nan, wild game, fish, tourtière) can be used to expand their range of healthy eating choices [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Why is it a good idea to eat local fresh foods when they are available?” Student: “They are more nutritious, taste better, and are better for the environment because they don’t have to be shipped so far.” 

Teacher prompt: “Look at these different versions of Canada’s Food Guide. This one is in English, these have been translated into different languages, and another is for First Nation, Métis, and Inuit users. What is the same about these guides? What is different about the food choices they recommend, and why are they still healthy choices?” 

Student: “All of the guides show four food groups, but the foods in the groups are different. They are still healthy choices because they provide all of the nourishment that people need to stay healthy. The translated versions of the guides all show the same pictures, but the languages are different. All of the guides provide information about healthy choices for different cultures. The First Nation, Métis, and Inuit guide has some different information. The picture on the front shows the food groups as a part of a circle instead of a rainbow. It also shows some pictures of some First Nation, Métis, and Inuit foods, like berries, wild plants, bannock, and wild game, and includes healthy living tips that fit with the lives of First Nation, Métis, and Inuit people.” Personal Safety and Injury Prevention</specific>
          <specific>C3.2 explain how the portrayal of fictional violence in various media (e.g., television dramas, video games, Internet, movies) can create an unrealistic view of the consequences of real violence (e.g., physical trauma, chronic disability, family stress, death) [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Watching violence in movies, in video games, and on television might make you think that violent behaviour is normal or acceptable. How is violence in a cartoon different from real life?”

Student: “In a cartoon, characters aren’t really hurt. If they are badly hurt in one scene, they may suddenly be all right in the next. In real life, a person involved in violence can be seriously hurt, physically and emotionally.”

Teacher: “Why is play fighting not a good idea?”

Student: “Nobody intends to hurt anybody in a play fight, but someone may get hurt accidentally. If the person who gets hurt gets angry, then the play fighting can turn into real fighting.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
	</overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Living Skills">
    <strand_text>Living Skills</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate personal and interpersonal skills and the use of critical and creative thinking processes as they acquire knowledge and skills in connection with the expectations in the Active Living, Movement Competence, and Healthy Living strands for this grade.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 use self-awareness and self-monitoring skills to help them understand their strengths and needs, take responsibility for their actions, recognize sources of stress, and monitor their own progress, as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: monitor their progress towards personal fitness goals, placing a sticker on the Active Living calendar on the fridge in their home each time they participate in a physical activity with a family member; Movement Competence: check whether they feel stable when performing static balances and adjust position if they do not; Healthy Living: identify some of the characteristics that make them unique, and think about things they may have done or said that acknowledged the unique characteristics of others in a positive way or that were disrespectful or hurtful to others)</specific>
          <specific>1.2 use adaptive, management, and coping skills to help them respond to the various challenges they encounter as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: engage in a physical activity when they feel anxious or unhappy, to help make them feel better; Movement Competence: experiment with adopting a positive attitude if they are not feeling confident as they learn a new skill, and describe how doing so affects their skill development; Healthy Living: make sure that they are getting enough sleep and eating healthy food to help them learn and grow) 

Students: “I have a congenital heart disease. I can do most things in physical education. I do my best, but I also understand how much physical activity I am able to do. If I need to adjust, my teacher and I work together to make the activity work better for me.” “I had butterflies about being in the play at the assembly this afternoon, but then I ran a lot in physical education, and I felt a lot less nervous afterwards.”</specific>
          <specific>1.3 communicate effectively, using verbal or non-verbal means, as appropriate, and interpret information accurately as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: remind others about safety rules in a positive and supportive way; Movement Competence: talk with a partner to decide which piece of equipment to use and what distance to stand apart from each other in order to practise throwing and catching successfully; Healthy Living: explain to a friend who loves video games how real violence differs from fictional violence, and try to persuade that friend to choose less violent games) 

Student: “Your bike helmet looks like it is sitting on the back of your head. Do you want help with your straps to make it sit straight?”</specific>
          <specific>1.4 apply relationship and social skills as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living to help them interact positively with others, build healthy relationships, and become effective team members (e.g., Active Living: be willing to be anyone’s partner for physical activities and be accepting of everyone when working in small groups; Movement Competence: interact positively with others when sharing space; Healthy Living: show leadership in identifying and avoiding peer pressure) 

Students: “When I am moving around the gym in different ways, I practise being able to move close to others and in my own space, changing directions quickly.” “I don’t think leaving the new girl out is a good idea. I think we should ask her to sit with us at lunch.”</specific>
          <specific>1.5 use a range of critical and creative thinking skills and processes to assist them in making connections, planning and setting goals, analysing and solving problems, making decisions, resolving conflicts, and evaluating their choices in connection with learning in health and physical education (e.g., Active Living: come up with ideas for ways in which they could be physically active inside their family’s house or apartment; Movement Competence: after performing a movement sequence, reflect on what they could have done differently to make the transitions from one movement to another smoother; Healthy Living: plan what they might bring to a family picnic, focusing on local foods, and give reasons for their choices)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>