<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/healthcurr18.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Active Living">
    <strand_text>Active Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="A1">
        <overall_text>participate actively and regularly in a wide variety of physical activities and identify how regular physical activity can be incorporated into their daily lives</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A1.1 actively participate in a wide variety of program activities (e.g., activity centre and circuit activities, tag games, parachute activities), according to their capabilities, while applying behaviours that enhance their readiness and ability to take part (e.g., joining in willingly, showing respect for others, following directions, taking turns) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “We show respect in many ways. In our classroom, we show respect for people of all cultures and abilities by including everyone in our activities. In our school, we show that we respect the environment by recycling and cleaning up. Showing respect for others is an important part of participating in physical activities. How do you show respect for others when you are being active?”

Student: “I show respect by tagging other people gently when we are playing tag and speaking politely to others.”
</specific>
          <specific>A1.2 demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to their personal enjoyment of being active (e.g., having the opportunity to participate fully in all aspects of an activity, having a comfortable environment for activities, being able to explore different ways of being active, having the opportunity to take part in activities that relate to their cultural background) as they participate in a wide variety of individual and small-group activities [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some things that help you enjoy being physically active?” 

Students: “I like it when everyone has their own ball, so we all get to play and practise a lot.”“I have more fun when I have lots of space to run and move.”“I love playing outside. When it is really hot, I play under the trees so I am in the shade.” “I liked this activity because it reminded me of a game we used to play in my home country.” 

Teacher prompt: “Each person pick up a ball or a beanbag. See how many different ways you can toss and catch your object while travelling around the gymnasium. Which way is your favourite?”
</specific>
          <specific>A1.3 identify a variety of ways to be physically active at school and at home (e.g., at school: playing actively at recess; participating in a variety of physical activities in class, including DPA activities; participating in after-school physical activities; at home: helping with outdoor activities like gardening, raking, or shovelling snow; going for a walk with family members; playing in the park; riding bikes on the community trail) [CT]
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the importance of being physically active and apply physical fitness concepts and practices that contribute to healthy, active living</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A2.1 Daily physical activity (DPA): participate in sustained moderate to vigorous physical activity, with appropriate warm-up and cool-down activities, to the best of their ability for a minimum of twenty minutes each day (e.g., doing an animal walk, a fitness circuit, parachute activities; galloping to music, wheeling their wheelchair around the gym) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “As you are moving like animals, see if you can keep moving the whole time without stopping. How does your jumping look different if you are jumping like a frog instead of hopping like a rabbit? How do your arms look different if you are showing how you would fly like a bird instead of climbing a tree like a squirrel?” 

Teacher prompt: “When you are exploring different ways of moving using hoops, what do you need to think about as you move?”

Student: “When I roll a hoop, I need to watch out for other children around me so I don’t hit anyone. When I jump into a hoop, I need to be careful not to land on the hoop, because I could slip. If I am holding a hoop with my partner, we should be careful not to pull the hoop and bend it.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.2 demonstrate an understanding of how being active helps them to be healthy [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Your heart is always beating and pumping blood to the muscles and the rest of the body. When you move faster, this will make your heart and lungs work harder, which makes them stronger and healthier.”
</specific>
          <specific>A2.3 identify the physical signs of exertion during a variety of physical activities (e.g., heart beats faster, body gets warmer, breathing becomes faster and deeper, perspiration increases) [CT]
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate responsibility for their own safety and the safety of others as they participate in physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A3.1 demonstrate behaviours and apply procedures that maximize their safety and that of others during physical activity (e.g., cooperating; listening carefully; wearing appropriate footwear; keeping a safe distance away from others while doing physical activities, either in class or on the playground; staying within defined boundaries; treating their wheelchair as part of their body) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “How do you know that you have chosen a good spot for doing your cool-down stretches today?”

Student: “I can stretch my arms out and not touch anyone or the wall from where I’m standing/sitting.”
</specific>
          <specific>A3.2 identify environmental factors that pose safety risks during their participation in physical activity (e.g., extreme heat may cause fatigue, too much sun exposure will cause sunburn, extreme cold and wind chill may cause frostbite, objects on the ground may trip someone who cannot see, wet pavement or floors may create a slipping hazard), and describe ways of preparing themselves to enjoy outdoor activities safely [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “If you are dressed properly, you will have more fun when you are being active outside. What do you need to wear in the summer/winter to participate safely in outdoor activities in any weather?”

Student: “In the summer, I should wear a hat and sunscreen when I go outside. In the winter, I need to wear a warm coat, a hat, mittens, and boots. If I wear a scarf, it needs to be tucked in so it does not catch on anything.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Movement">
    <strand_text>Movement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="B1">
        <overall_text>perform movement skills, demonstrating awareness of the basic requirements of the skills and applying movement concepts as appropriate, as they engage in a variety of physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B1.1 perform a variety of static balances, using different body parts at different levels (e.g., low level: crouch with weight balanced on hands and feet; medium level: stand and lean forward with arms outstretched; high level: stretch tall with arms overhead and legs wide apart) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “See if you can make different shapes with your body while you balance your weight on different body parts. Can you balance at a low level? Can you balance while stretching up high? How many different shapes can you make with your body when you are balancing on three body parts?”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.2 demonstrate the ability to move and stop safely and in control, with an awareness of people and equipment around them [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Find your own spot where you cannot touch anyone or anything, even when you stretch out your arms. When the music starts, skip or gallop to the music. When the music stops, stop moving and freeze in place as quickly as you can. Stay on your feet and check your spot. Are you still in your own space where you cannot touch anyone or anything?”</specific>
          <specific>B1.3 perform a variety of locomotor movements, travelling in different directions and using different body parts (e.g., jump over lines; walk carefully backwards along a line while looking over their shoulder; move forward with different body parts touching the ground; move arms in different ways while walking, dancing, or skipping; take giant steps while moving sideways) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Each time the music changes, change the way you are moving. Can you run or wheel your wheelchair in a big circle? Straight lines? Zigzags? Can you travel forward? Sideways? Can you skip? Hop? Run? Crawl? Can you make up a new way of moving?”

Students: “Look how I can pull my body along the floor with my arms to move like a seal.”“I am using my arms to make big circles while I jump over all the lines in the gym.”“I can slide sideways taking big steps.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.4 send objects of different shapes and sizes at different levels and in different ways, using different body parts (e.g., roll a ball along a line, throw a rubber chicken underhand to a chosen spot, kick a ball to a specific area, toss or drop a beanbag into a hula hoop, pass a sponge ball over their head to the next person in a short line who passes it between his or her legs to the next person) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Which body parts (hand, foot, elbow, head) can you use to send the ball forward?”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.5 receive objects of different shapes and sizes at different levels and in different ways, using different body parts (e.g., catch or trap a ball with two hands, catch a beanbag that they toss themselves or that a partner tosses to them, stop a rolling ball with hands or feet) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “When you get ready to catch, put your arms out with your hands up and your fingers spread wide. When you catch or trap an object, pull it in to your body as you grab it to help cushion it.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="B2">
        <overall_text>apply movement strategies appropriately, demonstrating an understanding of the components of a variety of physical activities, in order to enhance their ability to participate successfully in those activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B2.1 demonstrate an understanding that different physical activities have different components (e.g., movement skills, basic rules and boundaries, conventions of fair play and etiquette), and apply this understanding as they participate in and explore a variety of individual and small-group activities [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What do you need to think about when we are playing tag? What about when you and a partner are playing with a hula hoop - what is different?”

Student: “When we are playing tag, I need to keep moving, watch out for the person who is ‘it’, and make sure I don’t run into anybody else. When I am rolling a hoop with a partner, I need to be able to roll the hoop in one direction and catch it when comes back. I only need to be ready to move if my partner doesn’t send the hoop close to me. I need to make sure nobody is in between me and my partner when I roll it to her, so I don’t hit anyone.” 

Teacher prompt: “When you are choosing a ball to practise throwing and catching, what can you do to play fairly and show respect for your classmates? What about when you are playing with the ball?” 

Student: “When I am picking the ball I am going to use, I can wait my turn without pushing. When I am throwing the ball, if it bounces into someone else’s space, I need to wait until the way is clear before I run after the ball so I don’t wreck their game.”</specific>
          <specific>B2.2 apply a variety of simple tactics to increase their chances of success while participating in and exploring physical activities (e.g., extend arms to improve stability when balancing on one foot; change speed, direction, or level to avoid being tagged; move closer to a target to increase the likelihood of success when sending an object) [PS, CT]* 

Teacher prompt: “What did you do to improve your chances of success in the activity we just did?”

Students: “I am a fast runner/I can make my wheelchair move fast. I kept moving the whole time so I wouldn’t get tagged.” “I am deaf and can’t hear the music, but I watched for your hand signal so I knew when to change direction.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Healthy Living">
    <strand_text>Healthy Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="C1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to healthy development</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C1.1 explain why people need food to have healthy bodies (e.g., food provides energy for the healthy growth of teeth, skin, bones, muscles, and other body components) 

Teacher prompt: “Just as some toys need batteries to run, we need healthy foods to be active and to grow. How does eating a healthy breakfast every day help you learn?” 

Student: “It gives me energy to help me stay alert and concentrate.”
</specific>
          <specific>C1.2 demonstrate an understanding of essential knowledge and practices for ensuring their personal safety (e.g., knowing their home phone numbers; knowing how to contact 9-1-1; seeking help from a police officer, teacher, elder, or other trusted adult; knowing routines for safe pickup from school or activities) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Why is it important to know your phone number and your address?” Student: “It is important to know how to contact someone for help in an emergency.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to apply health knowledge and living skills to make reasoned decisions and take appropriate actions relating to their personal health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C2.1 describe how the food groups in Canada’s Food Guide (i.e., vegetables and fruit, grain products, milk and alternatives, meat and alternatives) can be used to make healthy food choices [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Canada’s Food Guide provides information that can help you make healthy food choices. What does the food guide tell you that can help you decide what foods to eat regularly and what foods to limit?” Student: “The guide tells you what kinds of foods to eat and how much. There are four food groups, and we need to eat foods from all four groups.”

Teacher: “Can you tell me which foods we should eat every day, and which ones we should eat less often?”

Student: “We should eat fruits and vegetables every day. We should eat treats that are not in the food guide less often. Sometimes it is okay to have foods that are not in the guide - like candies, cookies, and sweet treats - but there are also lots of foods that are in the food guide - like berries and other fruits - that are great to have as treats.”

</specific>
          <specific>C2.2 know and recognize cues to hunger, thirst, and the feeling of fullness, and explain how they can use these cues to develop healthy eating habits [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What does your body do to let you know you are hungry or thirsty?”

Student: “My stomach grumbles when I’m hungry and my mouth is dry when I’m thirsty.”

Teacher: “What should you do when this happens?”

Student: “I should try to have a snack or a drink when I feel hungry or thirsty.”
</specific>
          <specific>C2.3 demonstrate the ability to recognize caring behaviours (e.g., listening with respect, giving positive reinforcement, being helpful) and exploitive behaviours (e.g., inappropriate touching, verbal or physical abuse, bullying), and describe the feelings associated with each [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Caring behaviours are found in healthy relationships. How might you feel in a healthy relationship?”

Student: “I might feel happy, safe, secure, cared for.”

Teacher: “How might you feel in a relationship that is not healthy?”

Student: “I might feel sad, scared, angry, confused, hurt.”

Teacher: “What are some situations in which you might feel that way?”

Student: “I might feel that way if someone was being mean or leaving me out, if someone was touching me when I didn’t want to be touched, or if I was left at home alone.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.4 apply their knowledge of essential safety practices to take an active role in their own safety at school (e.g., inform teacher of allergies, be aware of food safety issues, play in supervised areas, follow safe routines for travelling to and from school) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some things that students may be allergic to?”

Student: “They may be allergic to nuts and other foods, bee stings, or medicine.”

Teacher: “What can we do to make the classroom as safe as possible?”

Student: “We should not bring anything that might have nuts in it to school. People with allergies who need to use medicine if they have a reaction should carry their medicine [epinephrine autoinjector] with them. We should know who has an allergy and what the signs of an allergic reaction are, and we should get an adult to help if someone is having a reaction.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to make connections that relate to health and well-being - how their choices and behaviours affect both themselves and others, and how factors in the world around them affect their own and others’ health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C3.1 demonstrate an understanding of how to stay safe and avoid injuries to themselves and others in a variety of situations, using knowledge about potential risks at home, in the community, and outdoors (e.g., items or situations that could lead to poisoning, slips, falls, fire, or injury, including injuries from household products, medicines, kitchen tools and equipment, insecure furniture, candles, toys; road, water, and playground hazards; weather and sun hazards) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What do you do to stay safe and avoid injuries at home and when you are outside?”

Student: “I wear a helmet when I ride my bike. I wear sunscreen and a hat in the summer. I never swim alone. I only take medicine if my parents/caregivers give it to me.”

Teacher: “How do you cross the road safely?”

Student: “I cross where there is a traffic light or a crosswalk, or at a corner. I look carefully both ways to make sure no cars are coming before crossing. I make sure that the drivers can see me, and that I am not hidden by bushes or cars.”

Teacher: “What can you do to stay safe in the kitchen?”

Student: “I make sure an adult is with me when I’m doing things in the kitchen. I do not use a knife or other sharp tools on my own, and I don’t touch cleaners and products that are marked with danger symbols.”

Substance Use, Addictions, and Related Behaviours</specific>
          <specific>C3.2 identify habits and behaviours (e.g., excessive screen time or video game usage, smoking) that can be detrimental to health, and explain how people can be encouraged to adopt healthier alternatives [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some behaviours that can be harmful to your health? What are some things you can do that are healthier or that protect your health and the health of other people?”

Student: “Spending too much time watching television or playing computer games keeps us from getting all the physical activity we need. We can play outside after school instead. Smoking is bad for you, and so is breathing smoke that is in the air when other people are smoking. We can ask people not to smoke around us. It is against the law for people to smoke in cars when there are children in the car.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Living Skills">
    <strand_text>Living Skills</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate personal and interpersonal skills and the use of critical and creative thinking processes as
they acquire knowledge and skills in connection with the expectations in the Active Living, Movement
Competence, and Healthy Living strands for this grade.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 use self-awareness and self-monitoring skills to help them understand their strengths and
needs, take responsibility for their actions, recognize sources of stress, and monitor their own
progress, as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and
acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: ask themselves
whether they are doing the best they can while they are participating in DPA activities in the classroom; Movement Competence:describe how they feel when they move in different ways; Healthy
Living: ask themselves whether they used a tissue or did a “sleeve sneeze”to cover their nose and
mouth when sneezing in order to avoid spreading germs)</specific>
          <specific>1.2 use adaptive, management, and coping skills to help them respond to the various challenges
they encounter as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and
acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: apply knowledge of
safety procedures to make themselves feel safer and more confident as they play on the playground;
Movement Competence:try to express themselves positively when they are excited or disappointed
during a game or when they are learning a new skill; Healthy Living: be able to use proper terminology to name their body parts, so they can explain where they may be hurt or sore)</specific>
          <specific>1.3 communicate effectively, using verbal or non-verbal means, as appropriate, and interpret
information accurately as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living:speak
respectfully and pay attention to others when sharing equipment; Movement Competence:use eye
contact, body cues, and words as needed to communicate clearly when sending and receiving objects;
Healthy Living: effectively communicate feelings they might experience in response to caring
behaviours and exploitive behaviours)</specific>
          <specific>1.4 apply relationship and social skills as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living to help them
interact positively with others, build healthy relationships, and become effective group or
team members (e.g., Active Living:take turns when using equipment; Movement Competence:
work cooperatively to share the space and try not to bump into others when moving around the
gymnasium; Healthy Living:listen respectfully to show they care about someone)</specific>
          <specific>1.5 use a range of critical and creative thinking skills and processes to assist them in making 
connections, planning and setting goals, analysing and solving problems, making decisions,
and evaluating their choices in connection with learning in health and physical education
(e.g., Active Living:make connections between being active and staying healthy; Movement Competence:use creative thinking skills to come up with new ways of moving and balancing – for
instance, balancing on four body parts, three body parts, or five body parts; Healthy Living:make
and explain choices that protect them from the sun, such as wearing a hat and applying sunscreen)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>