<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <strand id="Confederation">
    <strand_text>Confederation</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>describe the internal and external political factors, key personalities, significant events, and geographical realities that led to the creation of the Dominion of Canada in 1867, and to the growth of Canada as other provinces and territories joined Confederation;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* identify key social, political, economic, and physical characteristics of the British North American colonies between 1850 and 1860 (e.g., British, French, First Nation, and Black communities);</specific>
          <specific>* identify external and internal factors and events leading to Confederation (e.g., political deadlock, intercolonial trade, reciprocity, Britain's repeal of the Corn Laws, the Fenian raids, the U.S. doctrine of Manifest Destiny, transportation and defence issues);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the roles of key individuals (e.g., Sir George-Étienne Cartier, Sir John A. Macdonald), the main events leading to the signing of the British North America Act (e.g., the Charlottetown, Quebec, and London Conferences; coalition government in the Canadas), and the reasons for the exclusion of certain groups from the political process (e.g., First Nation peoples, women, the Chinese and Japanese).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate information about the needs and challenges that led to the formation and expansion of the Canadian federation;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide research on issues and problems (e.g., Why did Nova Scotia join Confederation in 1867 while Prince Edward Island did not? What qualities made Louis Riel a good leader?);</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of primary and secondary sources to locate relevant information about the regional interests of each colony/ province before and after joining the Dominion of Canada (e.g., primary sources: artefacts, journals, letters, statistics, field trips, period documents and maps; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* describe and analyse conflicting points of view about a historical issue or personality (e.g., British versus Canadian points of view about trade and defence; Queen Victoria, Sir John A. Macdonald, Joseph Howe, Louis Riel);</specific>
          <specific>* construct and use a wide variety of graphs, charts, diagrams, maps, and models to organize and interpret information (e.g., a decision-making chart showing the advantages and disadvantages of joining Confederation for each colony);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse, synthesize, and evaluate historical information (e.g., determine the changes in Canada's boundaries in 1867, 1870, 1871, 1873, 1898, 1905, 1949, and 1999, using a series of maps);</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using media works, political cartoons, oral presentations, written notes and descriptions, drawings, tables, charts, and graphs (e.g., create captions for political cartoons of the time);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., Confederation, conference, political deadlock, reciprocity, intercolonial trade, Corn Laws, Fenians, Manifest Destiny) to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>compare Canada as it was in 1867 to the Canada of today, including political, social, and other issues facing the country in both periods.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* illustrate the growth of Canada, using outline maps or other tools, identifying the physical regions of Canada, the colonies that joined Confederation, and their boundaries and dates of entry (e.g., 1867 - Ontario, Quebec, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia; 1870 - Manitoba, as a province, and Northwest Territories, as a territory; 1871 - British Columbia; 1873 - Prince Edward Island; 1898 - Yukon, as a territory; 1905 - Alberta, Saskatchewan; 1949 - Newfoundland; 1999 - Nunavut, as a territory);</specific>
          <specific>* use sections 91 and 92 of the British North America Act to outline how and why responsibilities are divided between the federal and provincial governments and relate these divisions to some present-day disagreements between the two levels of government (e.g., federal responsibilities for First Nation peoples, health care, the environment, trade, telecommunications).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Western Canada">
    <strand_text>Western Canada</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>outline the main factors contributing to the settlement and development of the Prairie provinces, British Columbia, and Yukon, and describe the effects of development on various groups of people in the region from a variety of perspectives;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* describe the everyday life of various groups (e.g., First Nation peoples, Métis, Europeans) in western Canada in the late nineteenth century;</specific>
          <specific>* explain the factors that led to the settlement of the Canadian west (e.g., federal government policy of opening up the prairies for European settlement, protective tariffs, railroad construction);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse how treaties and the Indian Act of 1876 transformed the lifestyles of First Nation peoples in the Canadian west;</specific>
          <specific>* describe the role of the Canadian Pacific Railway in furthering Canada's expansion, and identify the key individuals (e.g., Donald Smith, William Van Horne) and groups (e.g., Chinese workers) whose efforts led to the railway's completion;</specific>
          <specific>* describe the causes and results of the Red River Rebellion of 1869-70 and the North-West Rebellion of 1885 and explain the role of key individuals and groups (e.g., Louis Riel, Gabriel Dumont, the North-West Mounted Police, Thomas Scott, Big Bear, Poundmaker, General Wolseley, Catherine Schubert);</specific>
          <specific>* explain the effects of post-Confederation immigration, new wheat strains, and the Klondike gold rush on the expansion of western Canada and British Columbia (e.g., the development of prairie towns, the entry of the Yukon Territory into Confederation, the growth of Dawson City).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate information about conflicts and changes that occurred during the development of western Canada;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide research on issues and problems (e.g., Why did Big Bear receive the treatment he did from Canada's legal system?);</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of primary and secondary sources to locate relevant information about the building of the railway, the settling of the land, and social and cultural life in the developing west (e.g., primary sources: photographs of Chinese labourers and prairie sodbusters, the poetry of Robert W. Service; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse, synthesize, and evaluate historical information (e.g., trends in immigration, the impact of Treaties 1 to 8);</specific>
          <specific>* describe and analyse conflicting points of view about a historical event (e.g., the Pacific Scandal, the hanging of Louis Riel, the imprisonment of Big Bear);</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using media works, political cartoons, oral presentations, written notes and reports, drawings, tables, charts, and graphs (e.g., create diary entries depicting Louis Riel as a hero or a traitor);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., treaties, Métis, Rupert's Land, provisional government, prospector, panning for gold, staking a claim) to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>show how the history of the Canadian west has influenced both artistic/imaginative works and Canadian institutions.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* compare the image and duties of the North-West Mounted Police to the image and duties of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police today;</specific>
          <specific>* show how examples of art, poetry, music, and video reflect the history of the Canadian west (e.g., the art of Emily Carr, "The Cremation of Sam McGee" by Robert W. Service, "The Canadian Railroad Trilogy" by Gordon Lightfoot, Paul Yee's writings).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="A Changing Society">
    <strand_text>A Changing Society</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>describe key characteristics of Canada between 1885 and 1914, including social and economic conditions, the roles and contributions of various people and groups, internal and external pressures for change, and the political responses to these pressures;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* describe the factors contributing to change in Canadian society (e.g., immigration, technology, politics, globalization);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the achievements of individuals and groups in Canada who have contributed significantly to the technological development of Canada and the world (e.g., Martha Black, Guglielmo Marconi, Alexander Graham Bell, J.A.D. McCurdy, Samuel McLaughlin, George Ross, Adam Beck) and analyse the impact on society of new technologies (e.g., prospecting, radio, the telephone, the automobile, electricity);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the social and working conditions of Canadians around the beginning of the twentieth century (e.g., in mining, forestry, factory work; on farms; in cities);</specific>
          <specific>* describe how specific individuals and events helped change the position of women and children in Canada (e.g., Nellie McClung, Emily Carr, Lucy Maud Montgomery, Pauline Johnson; the Temperance Movement, laws establishing compulsory education);</specific>
          <specific>* outline the advantages and disadvantages of Clifford Sifton's immigration policy in the Laurier era;</specific>
          <specific>* identify and explain the factors that led to Laurier's electoral defeat in 1911 (e.g., the reciprocity issue, political compromise, French-English tensions);</specific>
          <specific>* identify key events that illustrate Canada's role within the British Empire and explain their significance (e.g., the Boer War, the Naval Question, Canada's participation in Imperial conferences);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the treaties, alliances, events, and people that contributed to the start of the First World War, and explain their relevance to Canada.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate information about the factors that shaped Canada as it was entering the twentieth century;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to facilitate research on particular topics (e.g., Why did Canadians support Laurier's leadership for fifteen years? Who started the First World War?);</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of primary and secondary sources to locate relevant information (e.g., primary sources: immigration posters, photographs of working conditions, journals and diaries; secondary sources: print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse, synthesize, and evaluate historical information (e.g., immigration tables, population growth tables);</specific>
          <specific>* describe and analyse conflicting points of view about a historical issue (e.g., child labour, the Boer War, the causes of the First World War);</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using media works, political cartoons, oral presentations, written notes and reports, drawings, tables, charts, and graphs (e.g., prepare a report on a selected topic and individual);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., advocate, movement, temperance, reciprocity, entrepreneurs, multiculturalism, alliance, entente) to describe their inquiries and observations.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>compare living and working conditions, technological developments, and social roles near the beginning of the twentieth century with similar aspects of life in present-day Canada.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* create an immigration campaign to attract immigrants to Canada around the beginning of the twentieth century and today, using media appropriate to the period (e.g., poster, pamphlet);</specific>
          <specific>* compare the challenges facing farmers and workers at the beginning of the twentieth century to those facing farmers and workers today;</specific>
          <specific>* compare family roles at the beginning of the twentieth century to family roles today (e.g., responsibilities and roles of men, women, and children).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Patterns in Human Geography">
    <strand_text>Patterns in Human Geography</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>identify the main patterns of human settlement and identify the factors that influence population distribution and land use;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* identify the three main patterns of human settlement - linear, scattered, and clustered;</specific>
          <specific>* identify and explain the factors affecting population distribution (e.g., history, natural environment, technological development, immigration trends/patterns);</specific>
          <specific>* compare the characteristics of places with high and low population densities;</specific>
          <specific>* explain how site and situation influence settlement patterns;</specific>
          <specific>* identify and describe the types of land use (e.g., residential, recreational, institutional, commercial, industrial, agricultural; for transportation, communication, utilities; public space);</specific>
          <specific>* summarize the factors that affect patterns of urbanization, industrialization, and transportation.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of geographic representations, resources, tools, and technologies to gather, process, and communicate geographic information about patterns in human geography;
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide and synthesize research on the study of population characteristics and patterns (e.g., What conditions are needed to maintain a high quality of life? What is the relationship between literacy rate and GNP? What action can students take to aid a developing nation?);
</specific>
          <specific>* locate relevant information from a variety of primary and secondary sources (e.g., primary sources: interviews, field studies, surveys; secondary sources: statistics, maps, diagrams, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences using computer slide shows, videos, websites, oral presentations, written notes and reports, illustrations, tables, charts, maps, models, and graphs (e.g., create graphs to compare factors affecting quality of life; create an illustrated brochure outlining positive features of a developing nation; map the ten highest and lowest countries on the Human Development Index; interpret population pyramids to predict population trends in other countries);
</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., site, situation, rural, developed, developing, urbanization, population density, population distribution, gross domestic product [GDP], gross national product [GNP], correlation, birth and death rates, literacy rate, life expectancy) to describe their inquiries and observations.
</specific>
          <specific>* create and use a variety of maps for specific purposes (e.g., to show land use, transportation routes, population distribution, popular tourist destinations);
</specific>
          <specific>* produce and interpret simple scatter graphs to determine the correlation between population characteristics;
</specific>
          <specific>* construct and examine population pyramids to make predictions about future trends in population characteristics.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>compare living and working conditions in countries with different patterns of settlement, and examine how demographic factors could affect their own lives in the future.
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* compare key characteristics (e.g., quality of life, level of industrialization and urbanization) of a number of developed and developing countries;
</specific>
          <specific>* research job trends and predict the skills that will be needed to meet the challenges of Canada's changing demographics.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Economic Systems">
    <strand_text>Economic Systems</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>describe the characteristics of different types of economic systems and the factors that influence them, including economic relationships and levels of industrial development;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* outline the fundamental questions that all economic systems must answer: what goods are produced; how they are produced; for whom they are produced; by whom they are produced; and how they are distributed;
</specific>
          <specific>* describe the characteristics of different types of economic systems (e.g., traditional, command, market) and explain why most countries, including Canada, have a mixed economy that includes features from more than one system;
</specific>
          <specific>* explain how the availability of particular economic resources (e.g., quantity and quality of land, labour, capital, entrepreneurial ability) influences the economic success of a region;
</specific>
          <specific>* identify and give examples of the three major types of industries - primary (resource), secondary (manufacturing), and tertiary (service) - and describe how these industries have developed in Canada.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of geographic representations, resources, tools, and technologies to gather, process, and communicate geographic information about regional, national, and international economic systems;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide and analyse research on economic influences and relationships (e.g., Where would be the best place to start a new logging industry in Canada? How have the types of industries in Canada changed since the nineteenth century? How has technology changed a specific industry?);</specific>
          <specific>* locate relevant information from a variety of primary and secondary sources (e.g., primary sources: statistics, interviews, published field studies, a field trip to a local industry; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);
</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using computer slide shows, videos, websites, oral presentations, written notes and reports, illustrations, tables, charts, maps, models, and graphs (e.g., use a brief dramatization to explain an industry to the class; produce a map showing the locations of natural resources and raw materials needed by an industry);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., economy; traditional, command, market, and mixed economies; supply and demand; production; goods; services; consumer; market; distribution; imports; exports; land; entrepreneurial; capital; primary, secondary, and tertiary industries) to describe their inquiries and observations.
</specific>
          <specific>* use thematic maps to identify economic patterns (e.g., the location of industries in relation to sources of raw materials, markets, and transportation; the proportional flow of trade between countries; sources of labour).
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>compare the economies of different communities, regions, or countries, including the influence of factors such as industries, access to resources, and access to markets.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* compare the economies of some top trading nations and explain the reasons for their success, taking into account factors such as industries, access to resources, and access to markets;
</specific>
          <specific>* investigate and explain the advantages and disadvantages of Canada's involvement in major trade associations/agreements (e.g., North American Free Trade Agreement [NAFTA], World Trade Organization [WTO]);</specific>
          <specific>* investigate and describe how a new or existing industry affects the economy of a region.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Migration">
    <strand_text>Migration</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>identify factors that affect migration and mobility, describe patterns and trends of migration in Canada, and identify the effects of migration on Canadian society;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* identify the push and pull factors that influence people to move (e.g., push: drought, war, lack of freedom, discrimination and persecution; pull: employment opportunities, security, climate);
</specific>
          <specific>* identify barriers to migration (e.g., physical, financial, legal, political, emotional);
</specific>
          <specific>* describe how technology has improved human mobility;
</specific>
          <specific>* explain how the components of culture (e.g., language, social organization, educational systems, beliefs and customs) can be affected by migration;
</specific>
          <specific>* describe the effects that migration has had on the development of Canada (e.g., its multicultural character, rural and urban resettlement, interprovincial movement, the brain drain).
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of geographic representations, resources, tools, and technologies to gather, process, and communicate geographic information about migration and its effects on people and communities;
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide and analyse research on migration and mobility (e.g., What barriers exist today for new immigrants? In which time period would it be harder for people to immigrate to Canada - now or a hundred years ago? Where would be the best place to migrate to in Canada?);
</specific>
          <specific>* locate relevant information from a variety of primary and secondary sources (e.g., primary sources: surveys, statistics, interviews, field studies; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);
</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using computer slide shows, videos, websites, oral presentations, written notes and reports, illustrations, tables, charts, maps, models, and graphs (e.g., write a story/ journal relating the difficulties faced by past or present immigrants; create a slide show to show how technological changes have affected mobility; create a video presentation encouraging immigrants to come and live in Canada);
</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., accessible, barriers, migration, mobility, immigration, emigration, refugees, modes of transportation, push factors, pull factors) to describe their inquiries and observations.
</specific>
          <specific>* use thematic maps to identify patterns in migration (e.g., location of regions that were sources of significant immigration to Canada, proportional flow along migrational routes to Canada).
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>connect the real experiences of Canadians to information about the causes and effects of migration.
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* use a decision-making model to select an ideal place to live, and present this decision to other members of the class;
</specific>
          <specific>* investigate the migrational roots of the members of the class and relate them to Canada's cultural development.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>