<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/sstudies18curr.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Heritage and Citizenship">
    <strand_text>Heritage and Citizenship</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>identify and describe major features of daily life and social organization in medieval European societies from about 500 to 1500 C.E. (Common Era);</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* describe the hierarchical structure of medieval society and the types of people in it (e.g., peasants, officials, scholars, clergy, merchants, artisans, royalty, nobles), and explain how and why different groups cooperated or came into conflict at different times (e.g., to promote trade, to wage war, to introduce the Magna Carta);</specific>
          <specific>* describe aspects of daily life for men, women, and children in medieval societies (e.g., food, housing, clothing, health, religion, recreation, festivals, crafts, justice, roles);</specific>
          <specific>* describe characteristics of castles and aspects of castle life (e.g., design and building methods; community structure - lord, knights, squires, men-at-arms, workers; sports and entertainment; heraldry; justice; conflict and defence);</specific>
          <specific>* outline the reasons for and some of the effects of medieval Europe's expanding contact with other parts of the world (e.g., the Crusades; Muslim influence on arts, architecture, and the sciences; the explorations of Marco Polo, the opening of the Silk Road, and the trade in luxury goods; the Black Death; Italian control of the Mediterranean; development of the printing press);</specific>
          <specific>* describe some of the ways in which religions shaped medieval society (e.g., Catholicism, Judaism, Islam; events and practices: pilgrimages, tithing, confession, festivals; occupations: clergy, caliph, nuns, monks; buildings: cathedrals, mosques, monasteries, temples, synagogues; influences on the arts; the building of libraries);</specific>
          <specific>* describe medieval agricultural methods and innovations (e.g., common pasture, three-field rotation, fertilizers, the padded horse collar, the wheeled plough, mills), and explain why the innovations were important;</specific>
          <specific>* outline important ways in which medieval society changed over time (e.g., growth of towns, specialization of labour, changes in transportation methods, changes to law and justice), and give reasons for the changes.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to investigate the major events and influences of the era and determine how they shaped medieval society;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide research (e.g., What impact did Islamic culture have on European medieval societies? Why did castles have moats? Which medieval trade guilds have comparable apprenticeship programs today? What valuable items did Marco Polo bring back from Asia?);</specific>
          <specific>* use primary and secondary sources to locate information about medieval civilizations (e.g., primary sources: artefacts, field trips; secondary sources: atlases, encyclopedias and other print materials, illustrations, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* use graphic organizers to summarize information (e.g., pyramid showing social hierarchies, circle chart showing system of crop rotation, timeline showing dates of innovations and events, T-chart showing comparison of peasants' and lords' lifestyles);</specific>
          <specific>* draw and label maps or create models to illustrate features of medieval landscapes (e.g., a village, a castle or palace, a mosque with a minaret);</specific>
          <specific>* read and interpret maps relevant to the period (e.g., showing trade routes, locations of castles, layout of a town or city);</specific>
          <specific>* use media works, oral presentations, written notes and descriptions, and drawings to communicate information about life in medieval society (e.g., the roles of men, women, and children; the problems of sanitation and health in towns and cities);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., peasant, page, clergy, squire, caliph, imam, merchant, trade guild, chivalry, manor, monastery, mosque, pilgrimage, Islam, Christianity, Judaism, Magna Carta, Crusades) to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>relate significant elements of medieval societies to comparable aspects of contemporary Canadian communities.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* compare aspects of life in a medieval community and their own community (e.g., with respect to housing, social structure, recreation, land use, geography, climate, food, dress, government);</specific>
          <specific>* make connections between social or environmental concerns of medieval times and similar concerns today (e.g., pollution, the spread of disease, crime, warfare, poverty, religious intolerance);</specific>
          <specific>* use artistic expression to re-create or respond to imaginative works from medieval times (e.g., illustrate a coat of arms; dramatize a story about the Knights of the Round Table; listen and respond to medieval ballads and poems; create a storyboard for a tale from The Thousand and One Nights).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Canada and World Connections">
    <strand_text>Canada and World Connections</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>name and locate the various physical regions, provinces, and territories of Canada and identify the chief natural resources of each;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* explain the concept of a region (i.e, an area that is similar throughout its extent and different from the places around it);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the physical regions of Ontario and describe their characteristics (e.g., Canadian Shield, Great Lakes- St. Lawrence lowlands, Hudson Bay lowlands);</specific>
          <specific>* explain how the St. Lawrence River and the Great Lakes systems shape or influence the human activity of their surrounding area (e.g., with respect to transportation, industry, recreation, commercial fishing);</specific>
          <specific>* identify Ontario's major natural resources and their uses and management (e.g., water, for hydroelectricity and recreation);</specific>
          <specific>* identify and describe types of communities in each physical region of Ontario (e.g., tourist, manufacturing, and agricultural communities in the St. Lawrence lowlands; First Nation communities in the Hudson Bay lowlands; forestry and mining communities in the Canadian Shield region);</specific>
          <specific>* describe a variety of exchanges that occur among the communities and regions of Ontario (e.g., fruit from the Niagara Peninsula, nickel from Sudbury, vehicles from Oshawa, wild rice from Kenora, cranberries from Wahta First Nation) and among the provinces and territories (e.g., potatoes from Prince Edward Island, fish from British Columbia, grain from Saskatchewan, Inuit artwork from Nunavut);</specific>
          <specific>* identify Canada's provinces and territories and its main physical regions (e.g., Canadian Shield, Appalachians, Hudson Bay lowlands, Arctic lowlands, Great Lakes-St. Lawrence lowlands, interior plains, cordilleras);</specific>
          <specific>* describe and compare the environments of the physical regions of Canada (e.g., with respect to landforms and waterways);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the natural resources necessary to create Canadian products, and the provinces and territories from which they originate (e.g., trees/furniture/Ontario);</specific>
          <specific>* relate the physical environment to economic and cultural activities in the various provinces and territories (e.g., mountains/ skiing/British Columbia; the Grand Banks/ fishing/Newfoundland and Labrador; beaches/tourism/Prince Edward Island; temperate climate and fertile soil/orchards/ southern Ontario).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to determine the influence of physical factors on the economies and cultures of Ontario and the other provinces and territories;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide research and clarify information on study topics (e.g., What are the effects of physical features on land use? How are goods transported from one province or territory to another?);</specific>
          <specific>* use primary and secondary sources to locate information about natural resources and their uses (e.g., primary sources: interviews, classroom visitors, class trips; secondary sources: atlases, encyclopedias and other print materials, illustrations, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* use graphic organizers and graphs to sort information, clarify issues, solve problems, and make decisions (e.g., use a pro-and-con chart to identify the effects of clear-cutting on a forest community; use a decision-making chart to consider the alternatives to and consequences of constructing dams on a river system; create a bar graph to show average temperature by province);</specific>
          <specific>* use media works, oral presentations, written notes and descriptions, drawings, tables, and graphs to identify and communicate key information about the regions, provinces, and territories;</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., regions, Canadian Shield, Great Lakes lowlands, St. Lawrence lowlands, Hudson Bay lowlands, interior plains, Arctic lowlands, cordilleras, physical features, boundaries, province, capital, territory, natural resources, grid) to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
          <specific>* locate on a map community boundaries and adjacent communities (e.g., towns, counties) within a region;</specific>
          <specific>* locate on a map of Ontario and label the Great Lakes and other major bodies of water and waterways (e.g., Hudson Bay, James Bay, the Ottawa River);</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of sources (e.g., atlases, relief maps, globes, aerial and satellite photographs) to locate and label the physical regions of Canada on a map;</specific>
          <specific>* use cardinal and intermediate directions, pictorial and non-pictorial symbols (e.g., dots to represent entire cities), scale, and colour to locate and display geographic information on various maps;</specific>
          <specific>* use number and letter grids to locate places on base maps and road maps, and in atlases;</specific>
          <specific>* create and use a variety of thematic maps of Canada's physical features (e.g., landforms, climate, natural resources);</specific>
          <specific>* construct maps of transportation routes between local communities within a region (e.g., rail, road, water, air);</specific>
          <specific>* construct maps of the provinces and territories, showing major roadways, railways, and cities, including capital cities;</specific>
          <specific>* prepare various forms of maps, using symbols and legends, to display places, transportation routes, and political boundaries (e.g., international, national, provincial) in Canada.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>identify, analyse, and describe economic and cultural relationships that link communities and regions within Ontario and across Canada.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* identify relationships, in a variety of fields, that link Ontario and the other provinces and territories (e.g., in art, literature, music, dance, technology, heritage, tourism, sports);</specific>
          <specific>* compare two or more regions (e.g., the Arctic and the Prairies), with respect to their physical environments and exchanges of goods and services;</specific>
          <specific>* identify and describe a cause-and-effect relationship between the environment and the economy in a province or territory (e.g., overfishing on the Grand Banks; changes to landscape resulting from open-pit mining or clear-cut logging);</specific>
          <specific>* describe how technology (e.g., in communications, transportation) affects the lives of people in an isolated community in Canada (e.g., the impact of snowmobiles on hunting in the Arctic; the effects of satellite television and the Internet on schoolchildren; the effect of air transport on the availability of products).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>