<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <strand id="New France">
    <strand_text>New France</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>outline the reasons why settlers came to New France; identify the social, political, religious, and economic factors that shaped the colony; and describe how settlers and fur traders interacted with the First Nation peoples;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* explain why people came to live in New France (e.g., for land, for military reasons, for the fur trade, for religious reasons) and describe the impact of European immigration on First Nation settlements;</specific>
          <specific>* identify key characteristics of economic, political, and social life in New France (e.g., the seigneurial system; the roles of governor, bishop, and intendant);</specific>
          <specific>* identify and explain examples of conflict and cooperation between the French and First Nation peoples (e.g., with respect to the fur trade, religion and culture, military alliances/conflicts), and between the French and English fur traders (e.g., competition between the North West Company and the Hudson's Bay Company);</specific>
          <specific>* outline the background and causes of key events of the period (e.g., the expulsion of the Acadians, the Seven Years' War, the Battle of the Plains of Abraham) and describe their effects.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate information about how settlers in New France met the physical, social, and economic challenges of the new land;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to aid in gathering and clarifying information (e.g., How did the Catholic Church influence the life of First Nation peoples and French settlers in New France?);</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of primary and secondary sources to locate relevant information about how early settlers met the challenges of the new land (e.g., primary sources: artefacts, journals, letters, statistics, field trips, interviews, period documents and maps; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse, synthesize, and evaluate historical information from different points of view (e.g., First Nation peoples' ideas about spirituality and Jesuit ideas about religion);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse and describe conflicting points of view about a historical event (e.g., the expulsion of the Acadians), giving examples of fact and opinion;</specific>
          <specific>* construct and interpret a wide variety of graphs, charts, diagrams, maps, and models to organize and interpret information (e.g., create a diagram illustrating the structure of the government in New France);</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using media works, oral presentations, written notes and reports, drawings, tables, charts, and graphs (e.g., create a chart illustrating the organization of the seigneury);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., seigneurial system, rivalry, expulsion, Acadian) to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>identify and explain similarities and differences in the goals and interests of various groups in New France, including French settlers, First Nation peoples, and both French and English fur traders.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* compare and contrast past and present attitudes to the fur industry (e.g., ideas about trapping, fashion);</specific>
          <specific>* compare the attractions and drawbacks for French Canadians in choosing life on a farm versus life in the church or in the woods (e.g., as an habitant, a Jesuit priest, an Ursuline nun, a coureur de bois, a fille du roi).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="British North America">
    <strand_text>British North America</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>explain the origins of English settlement in British North America after the fall of New France, describe the migration and settlement experiences of the various groups of settlers, and outline the causes, events, and results of the War of 1812;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* explain the historical impact of key events on the settlement of British North America (e.g., the Treaty of Paris, the Quebec Act, the American Revolution);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the different groups of people (e.g., Black Loyalists, slaves, indentured servants, Iroquois allied nations, Maritime Loyalists) who took part in the Loyalists' migration and identify their areas of settlement;</specific>
          <specific>* outline the reasons for the early settlement of English Canada (e.g., as an outcome of the American Revolution);</specific>
          <specific>* explain key characteristics of life in English Canada from a variety of perspectives (e.g., family life, economic and social life, the growth and development of early institutions, transportation, relationships with First Nation peoples and French settlers);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the major causes and personalities of the War of 1812;</specific>
          <specific>* describe the impact of the War of 1812 on the development of Canada (e.g., defence-related construction, as in Fort Henry and the Rideau Canal; the movement of the capital to Bytown [Ottawa]; the emergence of national pride; the building of roads such as Kingston Road and Yonge Street; the shipping industry in the Maritimes);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the achievements and contributions of significant people (e.g., Sir John Graves Simcoe, Lady Elizabeth Simcoe, Joseph Brant/Thayendanegea).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate information about the beginnings and development of the new British colonies;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to facilitate research on specific topics (e.g., Why were the Iroquois peoples allied with the British Crown? How were Indian reserves created in English Canada and French Canada and what were their impacts on First Nation peoples?);</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of primary and secondary sources to locate relevant information about how early settlers met the challenges of the new land (e.g., primary sources: artefacts, journals, letters, statistics, field trips, interviews, period documents and maps; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse, synthesize, and evaluate historical information (e.g., debate the question: Who won the War of 1812?);</specific>
          <specific>* describe and analyse conflicting points of view about a series of historical events (e.g., the Royal Proclamation of 1763, the Quebec Act of 1774, the Declaration of Independence of 1776, the Indian Act of 1876);</specific>
          <specific>* construct and use a wide variety of graphs, charts, diagrams, maps, and models to organize and interpret information (e.g., on a map of North America, trace the migration routes of the Loyalists and identify their areas of settlement);</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using media works, oral presentations, written notes and reports, drawings, tables, charts, and graphs (e.g., conduct a historical demonstration of immigrants coming to the Canadas);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., institutions, revolution, Loyalists, Patriots, Upper Canada, Lower Canada) to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>identify some themes and personalities from the period, and explain their relevance to contemporary Canada.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* illustrate the historical development of their local community (e.g., its origins, key personalities, and the contributions of various cultural groups), using a variety of formats (e.g., a heritage display, posters, a drama skit or role play, a brochure, a Web page);</specific>
          <specific>* prepare and present a biographical sketch of a historical person from the period 1759-1812 (e.g., Laura Secord, Isaac Brock, Tecumseh, Thomas Peters).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Conflict and Change">
    <strand_text>Conflict and Change</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>describe the causes, personalities, and results of the rebellions of 1837-38 in Upper and Lower Canada in relation to themes of conflict and change;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* identify types of conflict (e.g., war, rebellion, strike, protest), and describe strategies for conflict resolution;</specific>
          <specific>* identify key issues and events of the rebellions of 1837-38 in Upper and Lower Canada (e.g., issues related to land, transportation, government; events such as Mackenzie's march down Yonge Street);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the role of key personalities (e.g., Mackenzie, Papineau, Bond Head) involved in the rebellions, and the methods they used to bring about change;</specific>
          <specific>* explain the major social, economic, political, and legal changes that resulted from the rebellions and their impact on the Canadas (e.g., the Durham Report, the union of the Canadas, the Rebellion Losses Bill).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate information about issues and conflicts in Upper and Lower Canada, and about the attempts to resolve them;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide research on issues and problems (e.g., Why is Mackenzie a hero to some Canadians and a traitor to others?);</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of primary and secondary sources to locate relevant information about key personalities involved in the rebellions (e.g., primary sources: artefacts, journals, letters, statistics, field trips, period documents and maps; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* analyse, synthesize, and evaluate historical information (e.g., Papineau's Ninety-two Resolutions);</specific>
          <specific>* describe and analyse conflicting points of view about a series of historical events (e.g., Should rebels be given amnesty? Should women have a role in governing councils?);</specific>
          <specific>* construct and use a wide variety of graphs, charts, diagrams, maps, and models to organize and interpret information (e.g., label the transportation routes and location of skirmishes on a map of Upper and Lower Canada);</specific>
          <specific>* investigate and report on methods of conflict resolution employed in everyday life at home, at school, and in the community;</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences, using media works, oral presentations, written notes and descriptions, drawings, tables, charts, and graphs (e.g., label the original political divisions on a map of Upper and Lower Canada);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., rebellion, moderate, radical, conflict, responsible government, Family Compact, Château Clique, Patriote, Fils de la Liberté, Doric Club) to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>compare methods of conflict resolution in both historical and contemporary situations.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* compare the impact of political unrest and change in the Maritimes and in Upper and Lower Canada in the 1820s and 1830s;</specific>
          <specific>* compare and contrast historical conflict-resolution strategies with those used today to resolve disputes at home, at school, and in the community.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Geographic Inquiry">
    <strand_text>Geographic Inquiry</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>identify and explain the themes of geographic inquiry: location/place, environment, region, interaction, and movement;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* explain the geographic concept of location/ place (e.g., "location" means where a place is and where it is relative to other places; "place" is defined by unique physical and human characteristics);</specific>
          <specific>* explain the geographic concept of environment (e.g., "environment" refers to physical surroundings and conditions, particularly as they affect people's lives);</specific>
          <specific>* explain the geographic concept of region (e.g., a region is a part of the earth's surface that has similar characteristics throughout its extent; the concept of region helps to simplify complex ideas);</specific>
          <specific>* explain the geographic concept of interaction (e.g., the environment provides opportunities and challenges; people change the environment as they use it);</specific>
          <specific>* explain the geographic concept of movement (e.g., "movement" refers to the flow of people, goods, and information and the factors that affect this flow).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of geographic resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate geographic information;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide and synthesize research on an environmental issue (e.g., What is the effect on various groups of the government moratorium on cod fishing? What role does an environmentalist play in the planning of an urban community?);</specific>
          <specific>* locate and use relevant information from a variety of primary and secondary sources (e.g., primary sources: interviews, statistics, aerial photographs, satellite images, live telecasts; secondary sources: maps, diagrams, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);
</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries about different points of view on an issue, using computer slide shows, videos, websites, oral presentations, written notes and reports, drawings, tables, charts, diagrams, maps, models, and graphs (e.g., write and produce an interview presenting a perspective on government restrictions on fishing);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., phenomena, issues, bias, fact, opinion, absolute location, relative location, interaction, region) to describe their inquiries and observations.
</specific>
          <specific>* create and use maps for a variety of purposes (e.g., a thematic map of hurricane regions that illustrates an environmental pattern, a thematic map of deforested areas).
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>analyse current environmental issues or events from the perspective of one or more of the themes of geographic inquiry.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* apply the perspective of one or more themes of geographic inquiry to produce a report (e.g., newspaper, television, radio, website) on an actual or fictional environmental event (e.g., forest fires, illegal dumping, an oil spill, deforestation, an epidemic, drought, the development of a new mine, the depletion of fish stocks);</specific>
          <specific>* choose an environmental issue that illustrates one of the themes of geographic inquiry and explain why various individuals and groups have different opinions on the issue (e.g., theme of interaction: wilderness conservationists versus loggers);</specific>
          <specific>* create a visual presentation (e.g., computer slide show, storyboard, poster, video) to report on how conditions in and around the school illustrate the five themes of geographic inquiry.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Patterns in Physical Geography">
    <strand_text>Patterns in Physical Geography</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>identify patterns in physical geography and explain the factors that produce them;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* identify various types of landforms and explain how they are used to describe regions;</specific>
          <specific>* identify and describe world landform patterns (e.g., fold mountains along the west coast of North and South America, continental drainage basins and river systems);
</specific>
          <specific>* explain how world climate patterns result from the interaction of several factors (i.e., latitude, altitude, global wind systems, air masses, proximity to large bodies of water, ocean currents);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the effects of natural phenomena (e.g., tornadoes, earthquakes, hurricanes) on people and the environment;
</specific>
          <specific>* explain how natural vegetation patterns result from the interaction of several factors, including climate, landforms, soil types, and competition for available nutrients (e.g., landforms: plains/grains; climate: tropics/fruit);</specific>
          <specific>* identify major river systems of the world (e.g., the Amazon, the Nile, the St. Lawrence, the Mississippi, the Yangtze) and describe their drainage patterns as either dendritic or trellis;
</specific>
          <specific>* identify the characteristics of the three types of agriculture - subsistence, commercial, and specialized - and the differing climate, topography, and soil conditions that are favourable to each type;</specific>
          <specific>* describe how the following major factors influence commercial agriculture: location, climate, raw materials, market, labour, transportation.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate geographic information about the earth's physical features and patterns;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide research for a comparative study of physical patterns (e.g., What features characterize different types of river drainage systems around the world? What are the similarities and differences between the Cascade Mountains and the Rocky Mountains? What effect does pollution of the Great Lakes have on the lives of Canadians? What effect does acid precipitation have on the forest industry?);</specific>
          <specific>* locate relevant information using a variety of primary and secondary sources (e.g., primary sources: aerial photographs, satellite images, interviews, field studies; secondary sources: climate maps, illustrations, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);
</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries and analyses for specific purposes and audiences, using computer slide shows, videos, websites, oral presentations, written notes and descriptions, drawings, tables, charts, diagrams, maps, models, and graphs (e.g., create a map showing the relationship between physical features of the country and recreational activities; create a model of different physical patterns; present a computer slide show of how the mountain ranges of the world were created);
</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary, including correct geographic terminology (e.g., classify, climate graph, pattern, latitude, altitude, contour lines), to describe their inquiries and observations.
</specific>
          <specific>* use a variety of thematic and topographic maps to identify patterns in physical geography;
</specific>
          <specific>* construct, interpret, and compare climate graphs;
</specific>
          <specific>* use contour lines to represent elevation on maps (e.g., Mount Olympus, Mount Pelée, Fuji-san);</specific>
          <specific>* draw cross-sectional diagrams from topographic maps (e.g., of landforms, river profiles).
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>explain how patterns of physical geography affect human activity around the world.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* investigate and report on world patterns of landforms, climate, and vegetation that are favourable to specialized types of commercial agriculture (e.g., tree farming, potatoes, cotton, rice, coffee, bananas, tobacco, sugar cane, sheep, beef, dairy farming);
</specific>
          <specific>* investigate the physical features and climate of a variety of popular tourist destinations and use a decision-making model to select an ideal travel destination.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Natural Resources">
    <strand_text>Natural Resources</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>describe how humans acquire, manage, and use natural resources, and identify factors that affect the importance of those resources;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* describe a variety of ways in which people use and manage renewable, non-renewable, and flow resources to meet their needs;</specific>
          <specific>* identify patterns in the distribution and use of natural resources throughout the world;
</specific>
          <specific>* describe ways in which technology has affected our use of natural resources (e.g., with respect to their discovery, management, extraction, processing, and marketing);</specific>
          <specific>* explain the concept of sustainable development and its implications for the health of the environment;
</specific>
          <specific>* describe the economic importance of natural resources to a particular country (e.g., fish along Canada's coasts, diamonds in South Africa, oil in the Middle East).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate geographic information about the distribution, use, and importance of natural resources;
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* formulate questions to guide research into problems and points of view regarding the management and use of natural resources (e.g., How important are Canada's mineral deposits and extraction to the country's economy? What effect would the discovery of a new gold or diamond deposit have on its surrounding area? How can we ensure the sustainability of a resource? How might changes in technology affect natural resource extraction and use?);
</specific>
          <specific>* locate and record relevant information from a variety of primary and secondary sources (e.g., primary sources: eyewitness interviews, field studies; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, diagrams, print materials, videos, CD-ROMs, Internet sites);</specific>
          <specific>* communicate the results of inquiries for specific purposes and audiences using computer slide shows, videos, websites, oral presentations, written notes and descriptions, drawings, tables, charts, diagrams, maps, models, and graphs (e.g., create a poster to promote the proper use of a natural resource; stage a debate on a proposal to extract a resource in an environmentally sensitive area such as the tundra or the ocean floor);
</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary, including correct geographic terminology (e.g., flow resource, non-renewable, renewable, sustainable development), to describe their inquiries and observations.</specific>
          <specific>* produce maps showing locations of Canada's natural resources;
</specific>
          <specific>* use thematic maps to identify patterns of natural resources (e.g., locations of valuable minerals).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>describe positive and negative ways in which human activity can affect resource sustainability and the health of the environment.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* produce a report (e.g., newspaper, television, website) on the factors that affect the future availability of natural resources (e.g., overfishing, clear-cut logging, urban sprawl, accessibility of resource deposits);
</specific>
          <specific>* present and defend a point of view on how a resource should be used.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>