<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/math18curr.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Number Sense and Numeration">
    <strand_text>Number Sense and Numeration</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>represent, compare, and order numbers, including integers;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- represent, compare, and order decimals to hundredths and fractions, using a variety of tools (e.g., number lines, Cuisenaire rods, base ten materials, calculators);</specific>
          <specific>- generate multiples and factors, using a variety of tools and strategies (e.g., identify multiples on a hundreds chart; create rectangles on a geoboard) (Sample problem: List all the rectangles that have an area of 36 cm2 and have whole-number dimensions.);</specific>
          <specific>- identify and compare integers found in real-life contexts (e.g., -10°C is much
colder than +5°C); </specific>
          <specific>- represent and order integers, using a variety of tools (e.g., two-colour counters, virtual manipulatives, number lines);</specific>
          <specific>- select and justify the most appropriate representation of a quantity (i.e., fraction, decimal, percent) for a given context (e.g., “I would use a decimal for recording the length or mass of an object, and a fraction for part of an hour.”);</specific>
          <specific>- represent perfect squares and square roots, using a variety of tools (e.g., geoboards, connecting cubes, grid paper);</specific>
          <specific>- explain the relationship between exponential notation and the measurement
of area and volume (Sample problem: Explain why area is expressed in square
units [units2] and volume is expressed in cubic units [units3].).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of addition and subtraction of fractions and integers, and apply a variety of computational strategies to solve problems involving whole numbers and decimal numbers;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- divide whole numbers by simple fractions and by decimal numbers to hundredths,
using concrete materials (e.g., divide 3 by ½ using fraction strips; divide 4 by 0.8 using base ten materials and estimation);</specific>
          <specific>- divide whole numbers by simple fractions and by decimal numbers to hundredths,
using concrete materials (e.g., divide 3 by ½ using fraction strips; divide 4 by 0.8 using base ten materials and estimation);</specific>
          <specific>- use a variety of mental strategies to solve problems involving the addition and subtraction of fractions and decimals (e.g., use the commutative property: 3 x 2/5 x 1/3 = 3 x 1/3 x 2/5, which gives 1 x 2/5 = 2/5 ; use the distributive roperty: 16.8 ÷ 0.2 
can be thought of as (16 + 0.8) ÷ 0.2 = 16 ÷ 0.2 + 0.8 ÷ 0.2, which gives 80 + 4 = 84);</specific>
          <specific>- solve problems involving the multiplication and division of decimal numbers to thousandths by one-digit whole numbers, using a variety of tools (e.g., concrete materials, drawings, calculators) and strategies (e.g., estimation, algorithms);</specific>
          <specific>- solve multi-step problems arising from real-life contexts and involving whole numbers and decimals, using a variety of tools (e.g., concrete materials,  drawings, calculators) and strategies (e.g., estimation, algorithms);</specific>
          <specific>- use estimation when solving problems involving operations with whole numbers, decimals, and percents, to help judge the reasonableness of a solution (Sample
problem: A book costs $18.49. The salesperson tells you that the total price,
including taxes, is $22.37. How can you tell if the total price is reasonable without using a calculator?);</specific>
          <specific>- evaluate expressions that involve whole numbers and decimals, including expressions that contain brackets, using order of operations;</specific>
          <specific>- add and subtract fractions with simple like and unlike denominators, using a variety of tools (e.g., fraction circles, Cuisenaire rods, drawings, calculators) and algorithms;</specific>
          <specific>- demonstrate, using concrete materials, the relationship between the repeated addition of fractions and the multiplication of that fraction by a whole number (e.g., 1/2 + 1/2 + 1/2 = 3 x 1/2);</specific>
          <specific>- add and subtract integers, using a variety of tools (e.g., two-colour counters, virtual manipulatives, number lines).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of proportional relationships using percent, ratio, and rate.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- determine, through investigation, the relationships among fractions, decimals, percents, and ratios;</specific>
          <specific>- solve problems that involve determining whole number percents, using a variety of tools (e.g., base ten materials, paper and pencil, calculators) (Sample problem: If there are 5 blue marbles in a bag of 20 marbles, what percent of the marbles are not blue?);</specific>
          <specific>- demonstrate an understanding of rate as a comparison, or ratio, of two measurements with different units (e.g., speed is a rate that compares distance to time and that can be expressed as kilometres per hour);</specific>
          <specific>- solve problems involving the calculation of unit rates (Sample problem:You go shopping and notice that 25 kg of Ryan’s Famous Potatoes cost $12.95, and 10 kg of Gillian’s Potatoes cost $5.78. Which is the better deal? Justify your answer.).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Measurement">
    <strand_text>Measurement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>report on research into real-life applications of area measurements;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- research and report on real-life applications of area measurements (e.g., building a skateboard; painting a room).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>determine the relationships among units and measurable attributes, including the area of a trapezoid and the volume of a right prism.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- sketch different polygonal prisms that share the same volume (Sample problem:
The Neuman Company is designing a new container for its marbles. The container
must have a volume of 200 cm3. Sketch three possible containers, and
explain which one you would recommend.);</specific>
          <specific>- solve problems that require conversion between metric units of measure (e.g.,
millimetres and centimetres, grams and kilograms, millilitres and litres) (Sample problem: At Andrew’s Deli, cheese is on sale for $11.50 for one kilogram. How much would it cost to purchase 150 g of cheese?);</specific>
          <specific>- solve problems that require conversion between metric units of area (i.e., square centimetres, square metres) (Sample problem: What is the ratio of the number of square metres to the number of square centimetres for a given area? Use this ratio to convert 6.25 m2 to square centimetres.);</specific>
          <specific>- determine, through investigation using a variety of tools (e.g., concrete materials, dynamic geometry software) and strategies, the relationship for calculating the area of a trapezoid, and generalize to develop the formula [i.e., Area = (sum of lengths of parallel sides x height) ÷ 2] (Sample problem: Determine the relationship between the area of a parallelogram and the area of a trapezoid by composing a parallelogram from congruent trapezoids.);</specific>
          <specific>- solve problems involving the estimation and calculation of the area of a trapezoid;</specific>
          <specific>- estimate and calculate the area of composite two-dimensional shapes by decomposing into shapes with known area relationships (e.g., rectangle, parallelogram, triangle) (Sample problem: Decompose a pentagon into shapes with known area relationships to find the area of the pentagon.);</specific>
          <specific>- determine, through investigation using a variety of tools and strategies e.g.,decomposing right prisms; stacking congruent layers of concrete materials to form a right prism), the relationship between the height, the area of the base, and the volume of right prisms with simple polygonal bases (e.g., parallelograms, trapezoids), and generalize to develop the formula (i.e., Volume = area of base x height) (Sample problem: Decompose right prisms with simple polygonal bases into triangular prisms and rectangular prisms. For each prism, record the area of the base, the height, and the volume on a chart. Identify relationships.);</specific>
          <specific>- determine, through investigation using a variety of tools (e.g., nets, concrete materials, dynamic geometry software, Polydrons), the surface area of right prisms;</specific>
          <specific>- solve problems that involve the surface area and volume of right prisms and that require conversion between metric measures of capacity and volume (i.e., millilitres and cubic centimetres) (Sample problem: An aquarium has a base in the shape of a trapezoid. The aquarium is 75 cm high. The base is 50 cm long at the front, 75 cm long at the back, and 25 cm wide. Find the capacity of the aquarium.).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Geometry and Spatial Sense ">
    <strand_text>Geometry and Spatial Sense </strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>construct related lines, and classify triangles, quadrilaterals, and prisms;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- construct related lines (i.e., parallel; perpendicular; intersecting at 30º, 45º, and 60º), using angle properties and a variety
of tools (e.g., compass and straight edge, protractor, dynamic geometry software) and strategies (e.g., paper folding);</specific>
          <specific>- sort and classify triangles and quadrilaterals by geometric properties related to symmetry, angles, and sides, through investigation using a variety of tools (e.g., geoboard, dynamic geometry software) and strategies (e.g., using charts, using Venn diagrams) (Sample problem: Investigate whether dilatations change the geometric properties of triangles and quadrilaterals.);</specific>
          <specific>- construct angle bisectors and perpendicular bisectors, using a variety of tools (e.g., Mira, dynamic geometry software, compass) and strategies (e.g., paper folding), and represent equal angles and equal lengths using mathematical notation;</specific>
          <specific>- investigate, using concrete materials, the angles between the faces of a prism, and identify right prisms (Sample problem: Identify the perpendicular faces in a set of right prisms.).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>develop an understanding of similarity, and distinguish similarity and congruence;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- identify, through investigation, the minimum side and angle information (i.e.,
side-side-side; side-angle-side; angle-side angle) needed to describe a unique triangle (e.g.,“I can draw many triangles if I’m only told the length of one side, but there’s only one triangle I can draw if you tell me the lengths of all three sides.”);</specific>
          <specific>- determine, through investigation using a variety of tools (e.g., dynamic geometry software, concrete materials, geoboard), relationships among area, perimeter, corresponding side lengths, and corresponding angles of congruent shapes (Sample problem: Do you agree with the conjecture that triangles with the same area must be congruent? Justify your reasoning.);</specific>
          <specific>- demonstrate an understanding that enlarging or reducing two-dimensional shapes
creates similar shapes; </specific>
          <specific>- distinguish between and compare similar shapes and congruent shapes, using a variety of tools (e.g., pattern blocks, grid paper, dynamic geometry software) and strategies (e.g., by showing that dilatations
create similar shapes and that translations, rotations, and reflections generate congruent shapes) (Sample problem: A larger  square can be composed from four congruent square pattern blocks. Identify another pattern block you can use to compose a larger shape that is similar to the shape of the block.).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>describe location in the four quadrants of a coordinate system, dilatate two-dimensional shapes, and apply transformations to create and analyse designs.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- plot points using all four quadrants of the Cartesian coordinate plane;</specific>
          <specific>- identify, perform, and describe dilatations (i.e., enlargements and reductions), through investigation using a variety of tools (e.g., dynamic geometry software, geoboard, pattern blocks, grid paper); - create and analyse designs involving translations, reflections, dilatations, and/or simple rotations of two-dimensional shapes, using a variety of tools (e.g.,concrete materials, Mira, drawings, dynamic geometry software) and strategies(e.g., paper folding) (Sample problem: Identify transformations that may beobserved in architecture or in artwork [e.g., in the art of M.C. Escher].);</specific>
          <specific>- determine, through investigation using a variety of tools (e.g., pattern blocks, Polydrons, grid paper, tiling software, dynamic geometry software, concrete materials), polygons or combinations of polygons that tile a plane, and describe the transformation(s) involved.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Patterning and Algebra">
    <strand_text>Patterning and Algebra</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>represent linear growing patterns (where the terms are whole numbers) using concrete materials, graphs, and algebraic expressions;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- represent linear growing patterns, using a variety of tools (e.g., concrete materials, paper and pencil, calculators, spreadsheets) and strategies (e.g., make a table of values using the term number and the term; plot the coordinates on a graph; write a pattern rule using words);</specific>
          <specific>- make predictions about linear growing patterns, through investigation with concrete materials (Sample problem: Investigate the surface area of towers made from a single column of connecting cubes, and predict the surface area of a tower that is 50 cubes high. Explain your reasoning.);</specific>
          <specific>- develop and represent the general term of a linear growing pattern, using algebraic expressions involving one operation (e.g., the general term for the sequence 4, 5, 6, 7, … can be written algebraically as n + 3, where n represents the term number; the general term for the sequence 5, 10, 15, 20, … can be written algebraically as 5n, where n represents the term number);</specific>
          <specific>- compare pattern rules that generate a pattern by adding or subtracting a constant, or multiplying or dividing by a constant, to get the next term (e.g., for 1, 3, 5, 7, 9, …, the pattern rule is “start at 1 and add 2 to eachterm to get the next term”) with pattern rules that use the term number to describe the general term (e.g., for 1, 3, 5, 7, 9, …, the pattern rule is “double the term number and subtract 1”, which can be written algebraically as 2 x n - 1) (Sample problem: For the pattern 1, 3, 5, 7, 9,…, investigateand compare different ways of finding the 50th term.).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>model real-life linear relationships graphically and algebraically, and solve simple algebraic equations using a variety of strategies, including inspection and guess and check.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- model real-life relationships involving constant rates where the initial condition starts at 0 (e.g., speed, heart rate, billing rate), through investigation using tables of values and graphs (Sample problem: Create a table of values and graph the relationship between distance and time for a car travelling at a constant speed of 40 km/h. At that speed, how far wouldthe car travel in 3.5 h? How many hours would it take to travel 220 km?);</specific>
          <specific>- model real-life relationships involving constant rates (e.g., speed, heart rate, billing rate), using algebraic equations with variables to represent the changing quantities in the relationship (e.g., the equation p = 4t represents the relationship between the total number of people that can be seated (p) and the number of tables (t), given that each table can seat 4 people [4 people per table is the constant rate]);</specific>
          <specific>- translate phrases describing simple mathematical relationships into algebraic expressions (e.g., one more than three times a number can be written algebraically as 1 + 3x or 3x + 1), using concrete materials (e.g., algebra tiles, pattern blocks, counters);</specific>
          <specific>- evaluate algebraic expressions by substituting natural numbers for the variables;</specific>
          <specific>- make connections between evaluating algebraic expressions and determining theterm in a pattern using the general term (e.g., for 3, 5, 7, 9, …, the general term is the algebraic expression 2n + 1; evaluating this expression when n = 12 tells you that the 12th term is 2(12) + 1, which equals 25);</specific>
          <specific>- solve linear equations of the form ax = c or c = ax and ax + b = c or variations such as b + ax = c and c = bx + a (where a, b, and c are natural numbers) by modelling with concrete materials, by inspection, or by guess and check, with and without the aid of a calculator (e.g., I solved x + 7 =15 by using guess and check. First I tried 6 for x. Since I knew that 6 plus 7 equals 13 and 13, is less than 15, then I knew that x must be greater than 6.”).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Data Management and Probability">
    <strand_text>Data Management and Probability</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>collect and organize categorical, discrete, or continuous primary data and secondary data and display the data using charts and graphs, including relative frequency tables and circle graphs;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- collect data by conducting a survey or an experiment to do with themselves, their environment, issues in their school or community, or content from another subject and record observations or measurements;</specific>
          <specific>- collect and organize categorical, discrete, or continuous primary data and secondary data (e.g., electronic data from websites such as E-Stat or Census At Schools) and display the data in charts, tables, and graphs (including relative frequency tables and circle graphs) that have appropriate titles, labels (e.g., appropriate units marked on the axes), and scales (e.g., with appropriate
increments) that suit the range and distribution of the data, using a variety of tools (e.g., graph paper, spreadsheets, dynamic statistical software);</specific>
          <specific>- select an appropriate type of graph to represent a set of data, graph the data using technology, and justify the choice of graph (i.e., from types of graphs already studied);</specific>
          <specific>- distinguish between a census and a sample from a population;</specific>
          <specific>- identify bias in data collection methods (Sample problem: How reliable are your results if you only sample girls to determine the favourite type of book read by students in your grade?).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>make and evaluate convincing arguments, based on the analysis of data;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- read, interpret, and draw conclusions from primary data (e.g., survey results, measurements, observations) and from secondary data (e.g., temperature data or community data in the newspaper, data from the Internet about populations) presented in charts, tables, and graphs (including relative frequency tables and circle graphs);</specific>
          <specific>- identify, through investigation, graphs that present data in misleading ways (e.g., line graphs that exaggerate change by starting the vertical axis at a point greater than zero);</specific>
          <specific>- determine, through investigation, the effect on a measure of central tendency(i.e., mean, median, and mode) of adding or removing a value or values (e.g., changing the value of an outlier may have a significant effect on the mean but no effect on the median) (Sample problem: Use a set of data whose distribution across its range looks symmetrical, and change some of the values so that the distribution no longer looks symmetrical. Does the change affect the median more than the mean? Explain your thinking.);</specific>
          <specific>- identify and describe trends, based on the distribution of the data presented in tables and graphs, using informal language;</specific>
          <specific>- make inferences and convincing arguments that are based on the analysis of charts, tables, and graphs (Sample problem: Use census information to predict whether Canada’s population is likely to increase.).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>compare experimental probabilities with the theoretical probability of an outcome involving two independent events.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>- research and report on real-world applications of probabilities expressed in fraction, decimal, and percent form (e.g., lotteries, batting averages, weather forecasts, elections);</specific>
          <specific>- make predictions about a population when given a probability (Sample
problem: The probability that a fish caught in Lake Goodfish is a bass is 29%.Predict how many bass will be caught in a fishing derby there, if 500 fish arecaught.);</specific>
          <specific>- represent in a variety of ways (e.g., tree diagrams, tables, models, systematic lists) all the possible outcomes of a probability experiment involving two independent events (i.e., one event does not affect the
other event), and determine the theoretical probability of a specific outcome
involving two independent events (Sample problem: What is the probability of rolling a 4 and spinning red, when you roll a number cube and spin a spinner that is equally divided into four different colours?);</specific>
          <specific>- perform a simple probability experiment involving two independent events, and compare the experimental probability with the theoretical probability of a specific outcome (Sample problem: Place 1 red counter and 1 blue counter in an
opaque bag. Draw a counter, replace it, shake the bag, and draw again. Compare
the theoretical and experimental probabilities of drawing a red counter 2 times in a row.).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>