<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/sstudies18curr.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Heritage and Citizenship">
    <strand_text>Heritage and Citizenship</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>* demonstrate an understanding that Canada is a country of many cultures;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* demonstrate an understanding that communities may be made up of people from many cultures;</specific>
          <specific>* outline traditions of various cultures that are passed down from earlier generations (e.g., celebrations, names);</specific>
          <specific>* identify ways in which heritage and traditions are passed on (e.g., stories; community celebrations; special days such as Remembrance Day, Canada Day, Aboriginal Solidarity Day, and religious holidays; the Canadian flag; music, crafts, dance, food, recreation, clothing);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the origins and features of various families (e.g., nationality, culture, size, structure);</specific>
          <specific>* explain the significant traditions and celebrations of families from a variety of cultural traditions.</specific>
        </specifics>
        <overall_text>describe the communities of early settlers and First Nation peoples in Upper Canada around 1800;</overall_text>
        <specifics />
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>* use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate information about similarities and differences among family traditions and celebrations;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* ask simple questions to gain information and seek clarification (e.g., What are the similarities and differences in celebrations among cultures? How are they the same? How are they different?);</specific>
          <specific>* use primary and secondary sources to locate simple information about family history and traditions (e.g., primary sources: interviews, eyewitness visitors, class trips; secondary sources: maps, illustrations, print materials, videos);</specific>
          <specific>* use illustrations, key words, and simple sentences (e.g., timeline of major family events, simple family tree) to sort, classify, and record basic information about family history and traditions;</specific>
          <specific>* make and read a variety of graphs, charts, diagrams, maps, and models to understand information about cultural or religious traditions and share it with members of the class (e.g., Festivals of Lights, First Nation powwows, toys from various cultures);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., culture, celebrations, heritage, traditions) to communicate the results of inquiries and observations about family traditions and celebrations.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>* explain how the various cultures of individuals and groups contribute to the local community.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* identify examples that show the participation of various cultures in the community (e.g., restaurants, places of worship, styles of dress);</specific>
          <specific>* identify community celebrations that reflect their own heritage and/or their Canadian identity (e.g., Remembrance Day, Canada Day, Victoria Day, Aboriginal Solidarity Day, Chinese New Year).</specific>
          <specific>* identify the countries of origin of the people who settled in Upper Canada around 1800 (e.g., United States, United Kingdom, France, Germany);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the areas of early settlement in Upper Canada (e.g., English/Niagara; Francophone/Penetanguishene; African-American/Chatham; Mennonite/ Kitchener; Mohawk/Brantford);</specific>
          <specific>* identify the First Nation peoples in Upper Canada around 1800 (i.e., Ojibway, Iroquois Confederacy), say where they lived, and describe their lifestyles;</specific>
          <specific>* identify factors that helped shape the development of early settlements (e.g., lakes and rivers for trade and transportation; origins of early settlers; climate; natural resources);</specific>
          <specific>* explain how the early settlers valued, used, and looked after natural resources (e.g., water, forests, land);</specific>
          <specific>* describe what early settlers learned from First Nation peoples that helped them adapt to their new environment (e.g., knowledge about medicine, food, farming, transportation);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the major components of an early settlement (e.g., grist mill, church, school, general store, blacksmith's shop);</specific>
          <specific>* describe the various roles of male and female settlers (e.g., farm worker, minister, teacher, merchant, blacksmith, homemaker).</specific>
          <specific>* identify examples that show the participation of various cultures in the community (e.g., restaurants, places of worship, styles of dress);</specific>
          <specific>* identify community celebrations that reflect their own heritage and/or their Canadian identity (e.g., Remembrance Day, Canada Day, Victoria Day, Aboriginal Solidarity Day, Chinese New Year).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Canada and World Connections">
    <strand_text>Canada and World Connections</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding that the world is made up of countries, continents, and regions and that people's lifestyles may differ from country to country;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* recognize that the world is made up of countries, continents, and regions, including Canada in the continent of North America;</specific>
          <specific>* demonstrate an understanding of the relationship between location and climate (e.g., warmer climates occur near the equator);</specific>
          <specific>* describe some similarities and differences in the ways communities around the world meet their needs (e.g., with respect to food, clothing, shelter, recreation);</specific>
          <specific>* identify similarities and differences (e.g., in food, clothing, homes, recreation, land use, transportation, language) between their community and a community in another part of the world.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>use a variety of resources and tools to gather, process, and communicate geographic information about the countries studied;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* ask questions and use factual texts (e.g., illustrated dictionaries and encyclopedias) to obtain information about communities around the world;</specific>
          <specific>* interpret data and draw simple conclusions (e.g., establish connections between climate and clothing, or among artefacts, games, and celebrations);</specific>
          <specific>* sort and classify information using more than one criterion (e.g., how environment affects the ways needs are met);</specific>
          <specific>* use appropriate vocabulary (e.g., globe, model, distance, sphere, hemisphere, culture, countries, equator, North Pole, South Pole) to communicate the results of inquiries and observations about communities around the world.</specific>
          <specific>* recognize and use pictorial symbols (e.g., for homes, roads), colour (e.g., blue line/river), legends, and cardinal directions (i.e., N, S, E, W) on maps of Canada and other countries;</specific>
          <specific>* identify the earth as a sphere and half the earth as a hemisphere;</specific>
          <specific>* demonstrate an understanding that the globe is a model of the earth;</specific>
          <specific>* find the equator and the poles on a map and/or globe;</specific>
          <specific>* locate on a globe or map their local community in Ontario; Canada; and the various countries and continents studied;</specific>
          <specific>* construct and read a variety of graphs, charts, diagrams, maps, and models to clarify and display information (e.g., make graphs to compare the homes in various world communities).</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>explain how the environment affects people's lives and the ways in which their needs are met.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>* present information about children around the world (e.g., country of origin, language, food, clothing, homes, games);</specific>
          <specific>* compare how people living in different climates (e.g., near the poles and near the equator) meet their needs for food, shelter, clothing, and recreation.</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>