<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/healthcurr18.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Active Living">
    <strand_text>Active Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="A1">
        <overall_text>A1. participate actively and regularly in a wide variety of physical activities, and demonstrate an understanding of factors that encourage lifelong participation in physical activity</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A1.1 actively participate in a wide variety of program activities, according to their capabilities (e.g., individual activities, small- and large-group activities, movement and rhythmic activities, dance, outdoor pursuits), while applying behaviours that enhance their readiness and ability to take part (e.g., striving to do their best, displaying good sports etiquette along with healthy competition) in all aspects of the program [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What does healthy competition look like? How does it contribute to active participation?”

Student: “Healthy competition includes doing your best and pushing yourself to play as hard as you can, whether you are competing with yourself or as a member of a team. It contributes to active participation by giving you a goal that makes you want to be completely involved. Competition isn’t healthy if you are just playing to win without following rules of etiquette and fair play.”
</specific>
          <specific>A1.2 demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to their personal enjoyment of being active (e.g., being able to modify games for different purposes; being able to take part in activities that suit their individual abilities and interests; being exposed to a variety of activities, including recreational, team, individual, body management, and dance and fitness activities; feeling comfortable about the activities; being able to take part in activities that are culturally relevant), as they participate in a diverse range of physical activities in a variety of indoor and outdoor environments [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What is a physical activity that you like to do or a skill that you like to practise? What is it in these games or skills that you particularly like?”

Students: “I love to run fast. I can do that in cross-country running, soccer, and tag.” “I love activities that provide a mental challenge as well as a physical challenge. For example, in my karate class after school, I have to think about how I’m going to execute every move that I perform. I also like team games because they involve strategy.”</specific>
          <specific>A1.3 demonstrate an understanding of the factors that motivate or impede participation in physical activity every day (e.g., peer influence, sense of belonging, self-confidence, availability of resources and opportunities, influence of role models, compatibility or conflict with family responsibilities) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What motivates you to be active, and what stops you from being more active?”

Student: “I love to dance. I would like to be able to take a dance class every day, but it is too expensive and I can’t afford the time, so I take a class twice a week and dance on my own or with my friends whenever I can.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the importance of being physically active, and apply physical fitness concepts and practices that contribute to healthy, active living</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A2.1 Daily physical activity (DPA): participate in sustained moderate to vigorous physical activity, with appropriate warm-up and cool-down activities, to the best of their ability for a minimum of twenty minutes each day (e.g., aerobic fitness circuits, floorball, capture the flag, wheelchair soccer) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “How do you know that you are being active to the best of your ability when participating in physical activities?”

Student: “It is a personal measure. I know what it feels like to push myself hard. My heart rate goes up, I breathe faster, I get hot, and my muscles get tired. I know that if I am taking frequent breaks, not breathing very hard, or not feeling my muscles work, I am not working my hardest for that activity.”
</specific>
          <specific>A2.2 identify factors that can affect health-related fitness (e.g., heredity, nutrition, developmental stage, environmental factors, social and emotional factors, mental health, cultural teachings), and describe how training principles (e.g., frequency, intensity, duration, type of activity) can be applied to develop fitness [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “During puberty, bodies change in size and shape. This can have an effect on your energy levels and on your level of participation in fitness activities. What other factors can affect your fitness development?”

Student: “How I am feeling about my body can affect the kind of activities I choose to do. Having access to safe places to be active outdoors would help me be more active. Good nutrition is important for fitness, so I can help to develop my fitness by eating healthy foods that provide energy for being active.” 

Teacher prompt: “What are some things you can do to develop your fitness?”

Student: “I need to do different kinds of activities, such as aerobic, stretching, and strengthening activities, to develop different aspects of fitness. If I am working on my cardiorespiratory endurance, I need to gradually increase the length and frequency of my workouts and also the intensity of my training. I can gradually increase the number of laps I do, or the length of time I am active, to build up my endurance. If I am working on improving my flexibility, I need to do specific stretches for the parts of my body that I’m working on.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.3 assess their level of health-related fitness (i.e., cardiorespiratory endurance, muscular strength, muscular endurance, flexibility) during various physical activities and monitor changes in fitness levels over time (e.g., by tracking heart rates, recovery time, changes in how one feels during and after activity; by comparing activity participation and changes in fitness levels) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What is a good indication that your fitness is getting better?”

Student: “Tracking my heart rate recovery time and how I feel during activities is an indication of my fitness level. If my heartbeat is returning to its resting rate fairly quickly after I work out, then I know that my cardiorespiratory fitness is improving. Checking how I feel after skipping or playing soccer at recess also gives me information about my fitness level.”
</specific>
          <specific>A2.4 develop, implement, and revise a personal plan to meet short-term, health-related fitness goals (e.g., by using personal assessment information to set realistic short-term goals, using appropriate training principles, identifying possible challenges, identifying sources of support, determining what will indicate when goals have been reached, monitoring progress and comparing achievements to planned goals, acknowledging successes, changing goals or approaches as needed) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What things do you need to consider when you set a short-term fitness goal? How do you know if you have accomplished your goal?”

Student: “I need to consider what aspects of health-related fitness I want to focus on, then I need to identify what I can do to improve or maintain those aspects of my fitness. I need to think about what will help me accomplish my plan. If I set a goal to improve my core strength, I would need to think about what activities would be most helpful, and then about what activities I like to do that are both available and affordable for me. I might join a yoga or Pilates class, but if one were not available in my community, I would need to think about alternatives. I could do activities on my own at home, or I might be able to use a video that would help me, or work out with a friend. To know if I had accomplished my goal, I would need to track how I am feeling and compare what I was able to do before I started with what I could do after I had worked on my fitness for a while. Depending on the results, I might need to consider doing some things differently.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate responsibility for their own safety and the safety of others as they participate in physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A3.1 demonstrate behaviours and apply procedures that maximize their safety and that of others (e.g., following appropriate procedures and guidelines, demonstrating social responsibility, checking that they have their puffers and/or epinephrine autoinjectors, checking for hazards such as pencils or other objects on the floor or potholes on the field before beginning activities, using mouth guards when necessary during recreational activities in the community, avoiding pressuring a peer to participate in unsafe activities, being respectful of others who may be hesitant to try new skills) in a variety of physical activity settings (e.g., school, community recreational facilities, outdoor recreational venues) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What does all safe behaviour in physical activity have in common, whether you are participating in activities at school or in the community?”

Student: “Wherever you are participating, you need to be aware of yourself and others in your surroundings. Also, depending on the activity, you need to apply appropriate safety procedures. Using good judgement, thinking for yourself, and thinking before you act are good general guidelines.”</specific>
          <specific>A3.2 demonstrate an understanding of procedures for anticipating and responding to hazards that may lead to injury or ailments while participating in physical activity outdoors (e.g., be aware of common hazards that could be encountered and take appropriate precautions; apply systems thinking to risk assessment by making connections between possible hazards and their outcomes; recognize unexpected hazards, assess the risk, and control the hazard by telling someone about it, removing it, or removing themselves from the danger) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Being safe helps you enjoy your time outdoors. When cycling on a forest trail, what do you need to be mindful of?”

Student: “I need to make sure to wear a helmet, follow trail etiquette, and stay in control, so that if there is a fallen tree or another unexpected object on the trail I can avoid it and not be hurt. By following trail etiquette, I am less likely to get into situations where I can hurt myself or somebody else, or damage the environment.” 

Teacher prompt: “What can you do to protect yourself from the sun’s UV radiation outdoors?”

Student: “I need to be aware of the UV index for the day and limit my time in the sun during peak periods. I can protect myself by wearing sunglasses and a hat and applying sunscreen.” 

Teacher prompt: “What should you do if you find a pothole on the playing field?”

Student: “I should do something to warn everyone of the danger - for example, I could put a pylon on the pothole.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Movement">
    <strand_text>Movement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="B1">
        <overall_text>perform movement skills, demonstrating an understanding of the basic requirements of the skills and applying movement concepts as appropriate, as they engage in a variety of physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B1.1 perform smooth transfers of weight and rotations, in relation to others and equipment, in a variety of situations involving static and dynamic balance (e.g., perform a rhythmic gymnastic sequence such as throwing a ball, performing a shoulder roll, and catching the ball; demonstrate a dance sequence with a partner, including a series of steps, jumps, turns, and balances; perform a smooth high jump approach, take-off, and landing; use a low stance for balance during a pivot turn; move smoothly between positions in a yoga sequence) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “When doing a series of steps, jumps, and balances in a dance routine, what helps you to maintain control and make the movement transitions smooth?”

Student: “Holding my muscles tight, practising transitions between movements, counting the steps in my head, matching my steps to the rhythm of the movement, and asking for feedback from a partner.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.2 perform a wide variety of locomotor movements, with and without equipment, while responding to a variety of external stimuli (e.g., dodge and fake in response to others, accelerate before taking off for a high jump or a running long jump, respond to changes in music during creative dance by changing arm movements, lift feet and show awareness of trail conditions and obstacles when running cross-country on trails) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Describe how your running changes as you approach a long jump. How is it different with a high jump?”

Student: “With a long jump, I should be running my fastest just before I take off, so that I have the maximum forward momentum. With a high jump, I need to change my forward momentum to upward momentum, so I should run in a C or a J pattern, starting out fast, then slowing down a little just before I take off to go over the bar.” 

Teacher prompt: “How can you move your body to show a response to different types of music in a dance sequence that you are putting together?”

Student: “For loud and dramatic music, we could use large movements with lots of arm action. Our movements might be smooth or sharp, depending on the rhythm of the music.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.3 send, receive, and retain a variety of objects, while taking into account their position and motion in relation to others, equipment, and boundaries, while applying basic principles of movement* (e.g., use different strokes and varying degrees of force, depending on their opponent’s position on the court, to return the shuttle in badminton; assume a ready position to prepare to receive a short pass; strike a ball by shifting their weight as they contact the ball and following through in the intended direction to send it between or over opposing players; cradle or control the ball on the side of the body that is away from opponents when moving up the field) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “How do you need to adjust your position when receiving a pass on the move?”

Student: “When receiving a pass, I need to have my weight forward and on my toes so that I’ll be ready to move in different ways, depending on how fast the object is coming. When receiving an object when I am on the move, I may need to back up and be prepared to absorb the force if it is coming quickly. If it is coming slowly, I may need to move forward quickly in time to meet the object.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.4 demonstrate an understanding of the phases of movement (i.e., preparation, execution, followthrough), and apply this understanding to the refinement of movement skills as they participate in a variety of physical activities (e.g., jumping during a dance routine: bend knees to get ready to jump, thrust arms up for extra force while jumping, hold a controlled body position in flight, bend knees and put arms out for a stable landing) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Watch a partner serve a volleyball underhand against a wall. What are some tips you can share with your partner to help him/her send the volleyball successfully?”

Student: “Start in a ready position and prepare by holding the ball in your opposite hand. To serve underhand, bend your knees and step with the opposite foot, swing your striking arm back, then swing it straight forward, with force, in the direction you want the ball to go. Shift your weight forward as your hand contacts the ball. Follow through in the direction of the target.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="B2">
        <overall_text>apply movement strategies appropriately, demonstrating an understanding of the components of a variety of physical activities, in order to enhance their ability to participate successfully in those activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B2.1 demonstrate an understanding of the components of a range of physical activities (e.g., movement skills, game structures, basic rules and guidelines, conventions of fair play and etiquette), and apply this understanding as they participate in a variety of physical activities in indoor and outdoor environments [IS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “We’ve been trying out some traditional Inuit physical activities, like leg wrestling, push-up hop, and jump kick. What movement skills and components of fitness do you need for these activities?”

* See page 26 for background information and a description of movement principles.

Student: “All of these activities require stability skills and some locomotor skills. They also require physical strength, endurance, and agility. With leg wrestling, you need core strength and also balance. With the push-up hop, you need strength to be able to move forward while hopping in a push-up position. For the jump kick, you need flexibility as well as strength and balance to be able to kick an object that is held over your head.” 

Teacher prompt: “Why do you need to consider etiquette and how to work well with others when engaging in various kinds of activities?”

Student: “When doing an activity with others, you need to be able to work together to agree on things like team selection, rules, equipment, and boundaries. If teams are uneven or rules make the activity too challenging, the game isn’t fun. Rules of etiquette are needed to ensure that people show respect for each other. Even with individual activities, you need to be aware of proper etiquette in relation to others. For example, when jogging, you show respect for others when passing on sidewalks. Another part of etiquette is showing that you respect the environment as well as other people. For example, you could show that you respect the environment when running by staying on trails or pathways rather than running off the path.”</specific>
          <specific>B2.2 describe and compare different categories of physical activities* (e.g., individual, target, net/wall, striking/fielding, territory), and describe strategies that they found effective while participating in a variety of physical activities in different categories [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Territory games such as lacrosse, basketball, ultimate disc, rugby, soccer, broomball, speedball, ringette, wheelchair basketball, goal ball, and sledge hockey all involve controlling an object, keeping it away from opponents, and working together as a team to move it across the playing area until someone on the team can score. These games commonly involve the use of kicking, carrying, running, and/or throwing skills. Territory games have the most complex structures of all of the game categories because of the number of variables and the number of people involved. What strategies might you apply in any territory game?”

Student: “Teamwork is very important in all of these games. When you or your team has the object, important strategies involve focusing on ways of working together as a team to keep possession of the object, moving it down the playing area, and getting into an open space so you can either receive a pass or get a clear shot at the goal. When you do not have the object, important strategies include working together as a team to try to regain possession of the object by staying between the offensive player and the goal, and using your hands, feet, or stick (depending on the game) to keep your opponent from scoring.” 

Teacher prompt: “Territory games often involve fast transitions from offence to defence. How is this different from net/wall activities, striking/fielding activities, or target activities?”

Student: “Because the transition from offence to defence is often very quick in territory activities, players need to be ready to switch directions and strategies as the play changes. That also happens in net/wall activities, but in those games, each team stays on its own court while changing from offence to defence. In striking/fielding and target activities, there is a stop in the game as teams switch from offence to defence, so the pace is slower and more controlled.” 

* See pages 27-29 for background information and a description of various categories of physical activities.

Teacher prompt: “Consider what is similar about activities like canoeing, triathlons, and track and field. What do these activities have in common, and what strategies might you use in all of these activities?”

Student: “These activities all involve a combination of skills. With canoeing, you need to paddle, but often you also need to be able to carry the canoe. A triathlon involves swimming, biking, and running. There are a number of activities in track and field, including running races of different distances and different types of jumps and throws. In each of these activities, you need to practise and develop your fitness to improve. Strategies for all these activities focus on pacing and on planning transitions from one phase of the activity to another.”
</specific>
          <specific>B2.3 apply a variety of tactical solutions to increase chances of success as they participate in physical activities (e.g., individual activities: practise a dance or gymnastics sequence in parts to refine each move, then put it back together in a sequence; target activities: adjust force when sending the object so that it will stop or land in a position to block the opponent; net/wall activities: work with teammates to cover space effectively; striking/fielding activities: hit or kick in different ways, varying the distance the object is sent, so that it will be more difficult for opponents to field and return the object; territory activities: use a “give and go” by sending the object to a teammate (give) then running to an open space to receive the object back again from the teammate (go); kick a leading pass to a moving teammate to maintain possession) [IS, CT]* 

Teacher prompt: “How do you make it difficult for opponents to hit the ball in striking/ fielding activities?”

Student: “Change the speed and pathway of the ball. Change the level of the throw. Put a spin on the ball.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Healthy Living">
    <strand_text>Healthy Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="C1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to healthy development</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C1.1 describe benefits and dangers, for themselves and others, that are associated with the use of computers and other technologies (e.g., benefits: saving time; increased access to information; improved communication, including global access; dangers: misuse of private information; identity theft; cyberstalking; hearing damage and/or traffic injuries from earphone use; financial losses from online gambling; potential for addiction), and identify protective responses 

Teacher prompt: “What are some ways of protecting your safety when using a computer at home or in a public place?”

Student: “Everyone should be aware that anything they write or post could become public information. If you do not want someone else to know about something, you should not write about it or post it. You should never share your password. If you are a target of online harassment, you should save and print the messages you received and get help from a parent, teacher, or other trusted adult.” 

Teacher prompt: “The practice of sending explicit sexual messages or photos electronically, predominantly by cell phone, is a practice that has significant risks. What are some of those risks?”

Student: “Photos and messages can become public. They can be manipulated or misinterpreted. If they become public, they can have an impact on future relationships and even jobs.”
</specific>
          <specific>C1.2 demonstrate an understanding of linkages between mental illness and problematic substance use, and identify school and community resources (e.g., trusted adults at school, guidance counsellors, public health services, community elders, help lines) that can provide support for mental health concerns relating to substance use, addictions, and related behaviours [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Problematic substance use is a term that refers to the use of substances in ways that are potentially harmful. It includes both substance misuse, which is the use of substances in ways that are illegal or not recommended medically, and substance abuse, which involves excessive use of substances despite the physical, mental, emotional, social, legal, or economic harm that this may cause to oneself or others. Problematic substance use and mental illness are often closely connected. Many people suffer from both, although it is important to note that one doesn’t necessarily cause the other. In some cases, the causes may be quite different, or both may be caused by a common factor, which could be genetic, developmental, or environmental. For example, traumatic events (an environmental factor) can lead to both mental health and substance use problems. In other cases, mental illness may contribute to problematic substance use: alcohol and drugs may be used as a means to cope with a mental illness and may make the symptoms of the illness worse. Conversely, long-term drug use can lead to a loss of contact with reality and to the development of delusions and other psychotic symptoms similar to those seen in some mental illnesses. What are some mental illnesses that are sometimes connected with problematic substance use?”

Student: “Depression, eating disorders, anxiety disorders, bipolar disorder, and schizophrenia are sometimes associated with problematic substance use.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to apply health knowledge and living skills to make reasoned decisions and take appropriate actions relating to their personal health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C2.1 demonstrate the ability to make healthier food choices, using information about the role that different foods play as contributing or preventive factors in a variety of health disorders (e.g., cancer, Type 2 diabetes, cardiovascular disease, obesity, food allergies and anaphylaxis, tooth decay, osteoporosis) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What you eat can contribute positively to your overall health, but it can also contribute to health problems. Eating healthy foods gives you the vitamins, minerals, and nutrients you need to be healthy. An unhealthy diet is one of many factors, including obesity, physical inactivity, smoking, and high blood pressure, that can increase the risk of illness and disease. Fruit and vegetable consumption helps protect against a variety of cancers, whereas a diet high in red meat and processed meat has been linked to an increased risk of cancer. Avoiding sticky foods and following good oral hygiene practices helps reduce the risk of tooth decay. Getting enough calcium from dairy products, calcium-fortified soy beverages, vegetables, and fish or meat alternatives when your bones are growing can help prevent the development of osteoporosis in later years. Avoiding high-fat foods can help reduce the risk of cardiovascular disease and obesity. A healthy diet that follows the recommendations of Canada’s Food Guide, contains plenty of fruits and vegetables and high-fibre foods, and avoids unhealthy (saturated and trans) fats can help you maintain a healthy weight and prevent illness.”
</specific>
          <specific>C2.2 assess the impact of different types of bullying or harassment (e.g., intimidation, ostracism, pressure to conform, gang activities) on themselves and others, and identify ways of preventing or resolving such incidents (e.g., communicating feelings; reporting incidents involving themselves or others; encouraging others to understand the social responsibility to report incidents and support others rather than maintaining a code of silence or viewing reporting as “ratting”; seeking help from support services; learning skills for emotional regulation; using strategies for defusing tense or potentially violent situations) [IS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What kind of support will the person who was bullied and the bystander need?”

Student: “They need to be listened to and given a chance to express their feelings about the harm that has been done and to contribute their ideas about what needs to be done to put things right. They need to be given help to make sure the bullying stops. They might be afraid and may need counselling to recover emotionally from being bullied or witnessing bullying.”

Teacher: “Repair processes such as restorative justice might be put in place for the person who did the bullying in order to prevent the incident from happening again. Restorative justice puts the emphasis on the wrong done to the person as well as the wrong done to the community. It requires wrongdoers to recognize the harm they have caused, accept responsibility for their actions, and be actively involved in improving the situation. What has to occur before this can happen?”

Student: “The person who did the bullying has to admit guilt and accept responsibility for his or her actions. He or she needs to participate willingly in the process. The person who was targeted also needs to participate willingly, without feeling pressured. It is really important for their participation to be voluntary and for the process of restorative justice not to cause further harm. Trained facilitators can make sure that the restorative justice program is helpful to everyone.” 

Teacher prompt: “What are some of the consequences of using homophobic put-downs or racial slurs? How can this hurtful behaviour be prevented?”

Student: “Using homophobic or racist language is discriminatory. It hurts the people who are targeted and it can have harmful consequences for the whole atmosphere in the school. Sometimes, people speak without thinking about what they are actually saying and how they are hurting others. To change this behaviour, everyone needs to take responsibility for the words they use and also to challenge others who make discriminatory comments or put people down.” 

Teacher prompt: “Inappropriate sexual behaviour, including things like touching someone’s body as they walk by in the hall, making sexual comments, or pulling pieces of clothing up or down, is a type of harassment. What can you do to stop this kind of thing?”

Student: “Don’t accept it if you see it happening. Tell the person to stop or report them.” 

Teacher prompt: “A common form of harassment is spreading hurtful gossip about others. Is this type of bullying any less harmful than physical bullying? How can it be stopped?”

Student: “Verbal and social bullying are just as harmful as physical bullying. There are legal consequences for physical assault and for verbal harassment. If we hear it or see it, we should not accept it. It is up to everyone to make sure that this is not an acceptable thing to do.”

Substance Use, Addictions, and Related Behaviours C2.3 explain how preoccupation with body image can contribute to substance abuse (e.g., misuse of supplements, vitamins, diuretics, diet pills, laxatives, or steroids to alter appearance), and demonstrate the ability to make informed choices about caring for their bodies [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What are the dangers of using substances to alter body shape? What is a healthier alternative?”

Student: “Using substances to change body shape or to control weight is dangerous because of the hazards associated with different substances. Diet pills and laxatives can cause dehydration. Steroids have many side effects, including increased irritability, aggressiveness, mood swings, acne, changes in sex organs, hair loss, and addiction. Prolonged use of high dosages can lead to organ damage. A balanced combination of healthy eating and physical activity is a safer and healthier alternative to using drugs.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to make connections that relate to health and well-being - how their choices and behaviours affect both themselves and others, and how factors in the world around them affect their own and others’ health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C3.1 demonstrate an understanding of personal and external factors that affect people’s food choices and eating routines (e.g., personal: likes and dislikes, busy schedules, food allergies or sensitivities, personal values, cultural practices or teachings; external: family budget, cost of foods, type of food available at home, at school, or in the community), and identify ways of encouraging healthier eating practices 

Teacher prompt: “How can people make healthy food choices if their choices are limited by a dislike of certain foods, by a food allergy, by personal beliefs about ethical food choices, by cultural preferences or religious food rules, or by budget limitations?”

Student: “Some limitations can be removed or overcome. People often dislike certain foods without ever having tried them. We should always consider at least trying a food before rejecting it. Often we can learn to like a food by having it prepared or served in a different way. In other cases, we just have to work within the limitations. A lot of tasty food choices are available for people who are making ethical choices or following religious and cultural food rules, or who have allergies. If we have a limited budget, we can still eat well by making careful food choices. Packaged foods are usually more expensive and less nutritious than fresh foods cooked at home. Local produce can be relatively inexpensive in season, and it is more nutritious than imported or packaged fruits and vegetables.”</specific>
          <specific>C3.2 analyse the personal and societal implications of issues related to substance use and addictive behaviours (e.g., effect of technology dependence on school and workplace performance, risks associated with chewing tobacco, effects of second-hand smoke on non-smokers and children, legal and health implications of underage drinking, body damage and reputation loss among athletes as a result of the use of steroids and other performance-enhancing drugs; risk of HIV/AIDS with intravenous drug use; risk of fetal alcohol spectrum disorder [FASD] as a result of alcohol abuse during pregnancy) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Underage drinking is a concern in our school. Who can be harmed by underage drinking, and how?”

Student: “Underage drinking can be harmful to the person doing it because it can lead to legal charges and physical and emotional harm. Alcohol abuse is connected to violence in relationships and to unwanted pregnancies, so other people are hurt by it. Intoxication can also lead to risky behaviour that can result in injury or death. Alcohol poisoning can even be fatal. Underage drinking can be harmful to family members and the community because of the personal injuries or property damage that can result from actions or behaviour associated with impaired judgement, including car crashes. Irresponsible behaviour can damage not only the reputation of the person involved but also the reputation of teenagers in general. Underage drinkers also risk losing the trust of their parents and other adults.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Living Skills">
    <strand_text>Living Skills</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate personal and interpersonal skills and the use of critical and creative thinking processes as they acquire knowledge and skills in connection with the expectations in the Active Living, Movement Competence, and Healthy Living strands for this grade.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 use self-awareness and self-monitoring skills to help them understand their strengths and needs, take responsibility for their actions, recognize sources of stress, and monitor their own progress, as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: describe the role models that may have influenced some of their choices with respect to physical activity; consider what effect their family and their cultural background have had on the way they think about participation in physical activity or on the activities they choose; Movement Competence: take responsibility for improving a skill by breaking it down, getting feedback on the way they perform each part, and working on parts that need improvement; Healthy Living: describe ways in which they can monitor and stay aware of their own physical, emotional, and psychological health) 

Student: “I am working on improving my front crawl. I need to think about a number of things connected to my arm movement, including where my hand enters the water, the angle of my hand as I pull, the amount of effort I am using, and how my arm moves as I pull it around to begin the stroke again.”</specific>
          <specific>1.2 use adaptive, management, and coping skills to help them respond to the various challenges they encounter as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: use organizational and time-management skills to find a balance when planning time to be active every day, to complete homework, and to spend time with family and friends; Movement Competence: demonstrate how to refine movements by adjusting body position during the preparation, execution, and follow-through stages of an action; Healthy Living: describe how to access different sources of support when dealing with issues connected to substance use or mental health)

* The abbreviation(s) for the three categories of living skills - PS, IS, and CT - appear in square brackets at the end of expectations, in strands A-C, to which those skills are clearly connected. (See pp. 18-21 for a discussion of living skills.)
</specific>
          <specific>1.3 communicate effectively, using verbal or non-verbal means, as appropriate, and interpret information accurately as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: clearly communicate refusal to participate in activities that are unsafe, particularly when peer pressure is involved; Movement Competence: show readiness to receive a pass in a game by moving into position, making eye contact, and holding a hand out to act as a target; when the other team scores in a game of handball, say something supportive, such as “Good try”, to the goalie; Healthy Living: practise effective responses to someone who directs a homophobic or racial slur to them or to another student)</specific>
          <specific>1.4 apply relationship and social skills as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living to help them interact positively with others, build healthy relationships, and become effective team members (e.g., Active Living: make adjustments to activities that will allow all group members to be included and to enjoy participating; Movement Competence: work cooperatively with a partner when hitting a badminton shuttle back and forth; Healthy Living: explain how appreciating differences can contribute to positive relationship building)</specific>
          <specific>1.5 use a range of critical and creative thinking skills and processes to assist them in making connections, planning and setting goals, analysing and solving problems, making decisions, and evaluating their choices in connection with learning in health and physical education (e.g., Active Living: describe how they can use health-related fitness-assessment information when making action plans for personal fitness; Movement Competence: devise and experiment with different tactical solutions for better results in particular sports and other physical activities; Healthy Living: explain the connections between body image, mental health, and the risk of substance abuse; explain the importance of understanding connections between food choices and chronic diseases)
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>