<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/healthcurr18.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Active Living">
    <strand_text>Active Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="A1">
        <overall_text>participate actively and regularly in a wide variety of physical activities, and demonstrate an understanding of factors that encourage lifelong participation in physical activity</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A1.1 actively participate in a wide variety of program activities (e.g., lead-up games, recreational activities, fitness and endurance activities, dance), according to their capabilities, while applying behaviours that enhance their readiness and ability to take part (e.g., encouraging others with positive comments, displaying fair play by respecting the decisions of others) [PS, IS]
</specific>
          <specific>A1.2 demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to their personal enjoyment of being active (e.g., having the opportunity to modify games to make them more inclusive and to increase opportunities for participation, being exposed to new and different activities such as rubber chicken tag, having the opportunity to respond creatively to music and poetry, being able to take part in activities that emphasize healthy competition with themselves and others, having access to play spaces that are clean and attractive), as they participate in a wide variety of individual and small-group activities and lead-up games [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What can you do to keep school and community play spaces clean, tidy, and attractive so that you can enjoy being physically active outside?” Student: “We can get the school or community to put garbage and recycling containers in the area, use them ourselves, and encourage others to use them. We could also volunteer to plant trees. Trees provide shady places where we can go to keep cool.”</specific>
          <specific>A1.3 identify factors that can either motivate or make it difficult for people to be physically active every day (e.g., enjoyment; level of peer support; availability of transportation, equipment, time, and financial resources; availability of community resources; gender barriers or expectations; personal abilities; accessibility of facilities; personal organizational skills; family responsibilities or curfews), and describe ways of overcoming obstacles to staying active [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Identify a challenge that might make it difficult to be active every day and offer a solution that could help.” Students: “I have to take care of my younger brother every day after school, so I cannot join an after-school club. Instead, I play outside with my brother at home and sometimes invite a friend to join us.” “I would like to play in a hockey league, but my family does not have time to drive me to the practices and the equipment is too expensive. Instead, I play road hockey with my friends and family after school and on the weekends.” “I want to join an after-school club, but my parents are concerned about me getting home safely. I’m going to suggest asking my friend to join the club too, so we can walk home or take the bus together.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the importance of being physically active, and apply physical fitness concepts and practices that contribute to healthy, active living</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A2.1 Daily physical activity (DPA): participate in sustained moderate to vigorous physical activity, with appropriate warm-up and cool-down activities, to the best of their ability for a minimum of twenty minutes each day (e.g., power walking, wheeling, playing three-onthree games, skipping rope) [PS]
</specific>
          <specific>A2.2 identify the components of health-related fitness (e.g., cardiorespiratory endurance, muscular strength, muscular endurance, flexibility) and the benefits associated with developing and maintaining each of them (e.g., increased cardiorespiratory endurance provides more stamina for prolonged activity, increased muscular strength and muscular endurance improve performance in activities, good flexibility allows for ease of movement during activities) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Today, you will be doing a variety of fitness activities in this circuit. What is the purpose of each of the different activities?”

Student: “Doing the activities in this fitness circuit helps us work on different areas of fitness. The wall push-ups and crunches help us develop our arm and abdominal muscles. The continuous skipping will help build our cardiorespiratory fitness, and the stretching in the cool-down helps our flexibility when we do bending, twisting, and reaching activities.”
</specific>
          <specific>A2.3 assess a specific component of their health-related fitness by noting physical responses during various physical activities, and monitor changes over time [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Record your pulse before, during, and after the activity. Also, record how you felt. Keep track of the number of steps you take during the day, when you are wearing the pedometer. Come back to this information next week and the following week and comment on any changes you see.”

Student: “I can see that my heart rate goes up during the activity and back down afterwards. I am starting to feel less tired when I move without stopping for twenty minutes. My heart rate recovers to a normal range more quickly. I have been tracking the number of steps I take with my pedometer, and I’ve been able to increase from ten thousand steps in a day to over fifteen thousand on some days.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.4 develop and implement personal plans relating to a specific component of health-related fitness, chosen on the basis of their personal fitness assessments and interests [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What do you need to consider when setting your physical fitness and activity goal?”

Student: “I need to consider which aspect of my fitness I want to improve, assess where I am now, and decide what I will do to reach the level I want to be at. I want to be able to throw farther, so I need to improve my upper-body strength. I can do five push-ups now, but I want to be able to do ten by the end of the month. I can do that by trying to increase the number of push-ups I do every couple of days.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate responsibility for their own safety and the safety of others as they participate in physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A3.1 demonstrate behaviours and apply procedures that maximize their safety and that of others during physical activity (e.g., demonstrating personal responsibility for safety, using proper stretching techniques during cool-down activities, ensuring their actions promote a positive emotional experience for themselves and others, reporting any equipment that is not in good working condition) [PS, IS]

Teacher prompt: “What safety considerations do you need to remember when playing touch football with your friends?” Student: “We need to be in control when we tag and we shouldn’t tackle or push.” 

Teacher prompt: “If a peer is trying a new skill for the first time, what can you do to help that person feel safe or more comfortable in performing the skill in front of the group?”

Student: “I can try to be supportive by making encouraging comments and not being disruptive. I can also be a role model by trying new and challenging things myself.”</specific>
          <specific>A3.2 demonstrate an understanding of proactive measures that should be taken to minimize environmental health risks that may interfere with their safe participation in and enjoyment of outdoor physical activities (e.g., drinking fluids to avoid dehydration, before, during, and after vigorous activities; applying sunscreen and wearing a hat and sunglasses to protect the skin and eyes from sun damage; checking weather reports for the humidex, wind chill, air quality index, and UV index to determine what preparations may be needed to be safe and comfortable outdoors; bringing inhalers and epinephrine autoinjectors if needed; reading warning signs posted in recreational areas) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Using ‘active transportation’ means using muscle power instead of vehicles to get ourselves around. It helps to reduce air pollution. When using active transportation, what can you do to keep yourself safe?”

Student: “I can travel with a buddy or a group because there’s safety in numbers. When I’m biking, walking, or skateboarding, I can follow the rules of the road and also use trails or side streets instead of the main roads whenever I can. That way, I avoid the dangers of travelling in traffic and I don’t have to breathe in the exhaust from cars.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Movement">
    <strand_text>Movement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="B1">
        <overall_text>perform movement skills, demonstrating an understanding of the basic requirements of the skills and applying movement concepts as appropriate, as they engage in a variety of physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B1.1 perform controlled transfers of weight in a variety of situations involving static and dynamic balance, using changes in speed and levels, with and without equipment (e.g., perform a sequence of movements on a floor line or a bench; stay in control while rolling, balancing, twisting, dodging, jumping, skipping quickly and slowly) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “How do you keep your balance when changing speed or levels?” Students: “When I am speeding up while skating, I keep my balance by keeping my knees bent and my body low.” “When I am contracting from a high balance to a low balance, my movement needs to be quick and firm, and I need to keep my core muscles tight to help maintain my balance.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.2 demonstrate the ability to jump in control for height or distance, using a variety of body actions (e.g., push off strongly during take-off when jumping for height; keep a tight body position when turning in the air; land smoothly and safely after a vertical jump and half turn in a dance sequence; maintain body control when landing after a long jump) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “When you are in the air, squeeze your muscles so your body stays in control.” 

Teacher prompt: “When you are landing after a long jump or a jump from a height, what do you need to do to maintain control?”

Student: “When the jump is an especially big one, I need to land on the balls of my feet and bend my knees more than usual to absorb the force of landing and keep my balance. I also need to keep my arms out and my head up.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.3 explore different combinations of locomotor movements with and without equipment, alone and with others, moving at different speeds and levels, and using different pathways (e.g., dodge or change speed or direction to avoid people or objects; incorporate different movements at varying speeds when creating a dance with a partner; use ribbons or balls to develop a movement sequence that includes jumps, turns, movements in different directions, and balances) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Try the movement sequence at full speed, then very slowly. Which movements are easier to do faster and which ones are easier to do more slowly?”

Student: “For some of the moves, like footwork with complicated steps, going slowly gives me time to do the sequence well. For other moves, like a transition from a low balance to a stretched shape, moving more slowly is more difficult because I need good body control to hold the position steady as I move.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.4 send and receive objects using different body parts and equipment, adjusting for speed, while applying basic principles of movement* (e.g., kick a ball with the inside of their dominant foot at varying speeds to a partner who absorbs the ball with his/her body when it is received; strike a beach ball with a hand paddle and follow through in the direction of the intended target; experiment with using different amounts of force to send at different speeds) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What do you need to do to throw an object faster? When catching an object, how do you adjust for different speeds?”

Student: “To throw faster, I need to put my whole body into the throw, stepping with the opposite foot, turning my body, and following through with my arm after I release the ball. When I am catching, I need to keep my eyes on the ball. If the ball is coming slowly, I can step towards it to catch it. If it is coming fast, I need to be ready to absorb the catch with my body so the ball does not bounce away from me. I do the same things if I am receiving with my feet.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.5 retain objects with and without equipment in a variety of situations while moving in different pathways around others and equipment (e.g., dribble a ball around pylons, slowing down as needed to maintain control; stickhandle a felt disc towards a goal or target while shifting the direction of forward movement to avoid defenders or obstacles; catch and carry a ball in a scoop) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “How do you maintain control of the ball when you are moving in a zigzag pattern down the field? Does that change when your speed changes?”

Student: “I need to keep the ball fairly close to my foot or stick to control it. I can let it get a bit farther away when I am moving faster.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="B2">
        <overall_text>apply movement strategies appropriately, demonstrating an understanding of the components of a variety of physical activities, in order to enhance their ability to participate successfully in those activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B2.1 demonstrate an understanding of the components of physical activities (e.g., movement skills, game structures, rules and guidelines, conventions of fair play and etiquette), and apply this understanding as they participate in a variety of physical activities (e.g., lead-up games such as three-on-three lacrosse, mini tennis, and keep-it-up; recreational activities such as disc golf, parachute activities, orienteering, and cooperative games; fitness activities such as yoga, isometric musclebuilding activities, and endurance activities; dance activities such as creative movement, hip hop, and novelty dances) [IS, CT] 

* See page 26 for background information and a description of movement principles.

Teacher prompt: “How is a lead-up game such as four-corner soccer structured to make sure the game is inclusive and works for everyone?”

Student: “A game like four-corner soccer has four different goals and several balls so everyone has lots of opportunities to play. People with different skill levels can play together and everyone has a chance to participate to the best of their ability.”

Teacher: “If we are striving for healthy competition when playing, what does that look like?”

Student: “With healthy competition, everyone is trying their best, supporting each other, and playing fairly. You don’t always have to be in a game situation to compete. For example, I might compete against myself, trying to keep a soccer ball going as I juggle it, hitting it up with my foot, chest, and head.”

Teacher: “What components of an activity could be adjusted to make it challenging and enjoyable for everyone?” Student: “We could change the boundaries to make the game either easier or harder. We could change the type of equipment we use. We could add a rule - for example, all players have to touch the beach ball once before we are allowed to try to score a point. When we are playing with someone who is blind or partially sighted, we can use a ball with a bell inside or make a sound when sending the object so the person who cannot see is able to hear where the object is.”
</specific>
          <specific>B2.2 describe common features of specific categories of physical activities* (e.g., individual, target, net/wall, striking/fielding, territory), and describe strategies that they found effective while participating in a variety of physical activities in different categories [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “The net/wall games of volleyball, wall ball, badminton, squash, table tennis, paddleball, and wheelchair tennis all emphasize moving and controlling an object in a confined space and hitting it over a net or to a wall. What strategies might work in all of these activities?”

Student: “In all of these games, you try to place the object in a spot where the other team or player will have trouble returning it. You need to be ready to move quickly so you can return the object if it comes near you.” 

Teacher prompt: “Consider what is similar about activities like cross-country running or skiing, orienteering, long-distance running in track, and power walking. What strategies might you use in all of these activities?”

Student: “These activities all involve being able to keep going for a long period of time. Most of them don’t need a lot of equipment and can be done anywhere. These activities help build your level of fitness and endurance. A strategy you would use in all of these activities is pacing. It helps to learn how to manage your energy so you can keep going and be able to finish and also have the ability to go faster at different parts of the course.” 

* See pages 27-29 for background information and a description of various categories of physical activities.</specific>
          <specific>B2.3 apply a variety of tactical solutions to increase their chances of success as they participate in physical activities (e.g., individual activities: interpret feedback from a partner and adjust their position in a yoga activity; target activities: choose an appropriate distance from the target to maximize level of challenge and opportunity for success; work on accuracy by maintaining eye contact with the target and following through in the direction of the target; net/wall activities: place shots away from their opponent; striking/fielding activities: choose their position to effectively cover a space when fielding; territory activities: make quick passes to keep the object moving when playing a modified team handball game) [IS, CT]* 

Teacher prompts: “In target games, choose a position (closer to or farther from the target) that will give you the best balance between optimal challenge and the greatest chance of success.” “Why is it important to communicate with your teammates during territory activities?” “What do you need to do to work well with others when creating and performing a creative dance in a group of four?”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Healthy Living">
    <strand_text>Healthy Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="C1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to healthy development</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C1.1 identify people (e.g., parents, guardians, neighbours, teachers, crossing guards, police, older students, coaches, elders) and supportive services (e.g., help lines, 9-1-1, Telehealth, public health units, student services) that can assist with injury prevention, emergencies, bullying, and abusive and violent situations [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “If you are being bullied or you know of someone being bullied, to whom can you turn for help?”

Student: “I can turn to any adult I trust - a parent, a teacher, a coach, or an elder. I need to continue to ask for help until I get the help I need.”

Teacher: “What should you do in a situation in which someone is being violent?” Student: “Get out of the way, get help, and do not try to intervene directly.”
</specific>
          <specific>C1.2 describe the short- and long-term effects of alcohol use, and identify factors that can affect intoxication (e.g., amount consumed, speed of consumption, sex, body size, combinations with other drugs or food, emotional state) 

Teacher prompt: “Drinking even a small amount of alcohol can affect your body. The more you drink, the greater the effects. What are the short-term effects of alcohol use?”

Student: “Short-term effects can include relaxation but also reduced coordination, higher body temperature, slower reflexes, drowsiness, lowered inhibitions, slurred speech, and problems making good decisions. Becoming drunk, or intoxicated, could lead to vomiting, loss of consciousness, or even alcohol poisoning. If any of these things happen, medical attention is needed.”

Teacher: “What long-term consequences can result from alcohol abuse?”

Student: “Addiction, liver damage, financial problems, family or relationship issues, and emotional problems are some of the consequences of long-term alcohol abuse.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to apply health knowledge and living skills to make reasoned decisions and take appropriate actions relating to their personal health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C2.1 explain how to use nutrition facts tables and ingredient lists on food labels to make healthier personal food choices [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Food labels contain a lot of information, including the product name, product claims, an ingredient list, and a nutrition facts table, which identifies the nutrients in the product, the number of calories per serving, the serving size, and other information, such as the amount of trans fats. How can you use this information to evaluate food choices?”

Student: “I can check the nutrition facts table to see how much fat, sugar, and salt is in the product. Foods with less saturated fat, trans fats, salt, and sugar are better than those with more. However, growing bodies do need a certain amount of fat for healthy growth. Foods with more nutrients like fibre and vitamins A and C are healthier than those with smaller amounts of these nutrients. I can use this knowledge to help me make healthier food choices at home and to help my family make healthier choices when we go shopping - for example, by choosing 100% fruit juice instead of fruit-flavoured drinks. I can also use similar information about the ingredients in food at restaurants and fast-food places, if it is available.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.2 demonstrate the ability to deal with threatening situations by applying appropriate living skills (e.g., personal skills, including self-monitoring and anger management; interpersonal skills, including conflict resolution skills; communication skills, including assertiveness and refusal skills) and safety strategies (e.g., having a plan and thinking before acting; looking confident; being aware of surroundings; seeking help; drawing on cultural teachings, where appropriate, to analyse situations and develop responses) [PS, IS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What strategies could you use in a situation where you were being harassed because of your sex, race, religion, sexual orientation, body shape, weight, or ability?”

Student: “Different situations may require different strategies. Sometimes it is best to be assertive and stand up to the person who is harassing by speaking confidently. If you feel threatened, it is safer to avoid confrontation by ignoring the person, making an excuse and walking away, or getting help.” 

Teacher prompt: “As a bystander, what could you do to help if a friend tells you about a situation where he or she is feeling bullied or unsafe?”

Student: “I can listen to my friend and talk about ways we can stand up for ourselves when someone is bullying us. I can stand up for my friend if I am there when it happens, or I can get help by telling an adult.” 

Teacher prompt: “How might the medicine wheel concept, which is used in some First Nation teachings, help you to consider strategies for personal safety?”

Student: “The four elements of the medicine wheel can help me think about my safety and well-being in terms of my physical, emotional, spiritual, and mental health.” Substance Use, Addictions, and Related Behaviours</specific>
          <specific>C2.3 demonstrate the ability to apply decision-making, assertiveness, and refusal skills to deal with pressures pertaining to alcohol use or other behaviours that could later lead to addiction (e.g., smoking, drug use, gambling) [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What might you do if someone is pressuring you to try alcohol or a cigarette?”

Student: “I can try to avoid situations where I might be offered alcohol or cigarettes. If I can’t, I can say strongly and clearly that I do not want to participate. I can also mention problems that I’d rather avoid, like bad breath, disease, and impairment - or I can just make a joke and change the subject.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to make connections that relate to health and well-being - how their choices and behaviours affect both themselves and others, and how factors in the world around them affect their own and others’ health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C3.1 describe how advertising and media influences affect food choices (e.g., TV commercials, product packaging, celebrity endorsements, product placements in movies and programs, idealized body images in movies and programs, magazine articles promoting fad diets), and explain how these influences can be evaluated to make healthier choices (e.g., critically examining the reasons for celebrity endorsements or the plausibility of product claims, checking whether there is information in the advertisement that verifies the claims, asking for information about product ingredients and nutrients, critically examining the reality and healthiness of idealized body images in the media, evaluating diet plans against accepted nutritional criteria such as those used in Canada’s Food Guide) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What might you think about when you see a professional athlete drinking an energy drink in a commercial?”

Student: “The advertisement is trying to influence me to buy the drink. But just because the ad says a professional athlete drinks it does not mean that it is healthy for me or that I need to drink it when I am being active.”
</specific>
          <specific>C3.2 explain how a person’s actions (e.g., negative actions such as name calling, making homophobic or racist remarks, mocking appearance or ability, excluding, bullying, sexual harassment; positive actions such as praising, supporting, including) can affect the feelings, self-concept, emotional well-being, and reputation of themselves and others [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Negative actions that hurt the feelings of others can also result in stigma. When someone appears to be different from us, whether it is because of something visible like a physical disability or something invisible like having an illness such as schizophrenia or HIV/AIDS, we may view him or her in a stereotyped manner and make assumptions. Stereotypes can have a strong, negative impact on someone’s self-concept and well-being. On the other hand, you can also make a big difference in a positive way with your actions. Give an example of an action that can affect someone’s feelings, self-concept, or reputation in a positive way.”

Student: “Actions that can have a positive effect include asking someone who has been left out to be a partner, praising someone for their accomplishments, recognizing someone’s talent or skill, and making sure everyone gets a turn.”

Teacher: “How do your actions - positive or negative - have an impact on your own self-concept and reputation?”

Student: “Having a positive attitude towards other people can make you feel good about yourself. It can also make people want to be around you. Always being negative or putting other people down reflects badly on you and can make you feel worse about yourself.”
</specific>
          <specific>C3.3 identify personal and social factors (e.g., emotional, physical, mental, spiritual, cultural, legal, media, and peer influences) that can affect a person’s decision to drink alcohol at different points in his or her life [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “How realistic are the messages that we get from the media about drinking alcohol?”

Student: “On television, you see people having fun, being sociable, and doing cool things while drinking. You do not often see images in the media of someone who has passed out or who has caused a car crash or who is in an abusive relationship because of alcohol.” 

Teacher prompt: “Some adults choose to drink alcohol in social settings or during celebrations. How is this different from a teen drinking alcohol?”

Student: “It is legal for adults to drink alcohol. Drinking in moderation, avoiding getting drunk, and following the law about drinking and driving are some of the responsibilities that adults who choose to drink alcohol have to accept.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Living Skills">
    <strand_text>Living Skills</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate personal and interpersonal skills and the use of critical and creative thinking processes as they acquire knowledge and skills in connection with the expectations in the Active Living, Movement Competence, and Healthy Living strands for this grade</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 use self-awareness and self-monitoring skills to help them understand their strengths and needs, take responsibility for their actions, recognize sources of stress, and monitor their own progress, as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: monitor progress towards fitness goals, noting improvements or lack of improvement and making changes as needed; note how physical activity makes them feel, particularly when they are experiencing stress; Movement Competence: describe how knowing their strengths and areas for improvement can help when they are learning new skills; Healthy Living: describe some of the factors or situations that cause them to experience stress) 

Student: “When I am playing bocce, I am good at planning where to throw, and that helps my team. Also, my aim is starting to improve because I’m making sure to line up my throw and my follow-through with the target.”</specific>
          <specific>1.2 use adaptive, management, and coping skills to help them respond to the various challenges they encounter as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: demonstrate a positive attitude, persistence, and a willingness to seek support when working at developing fitness, and explain how these factors help them meet their goals; Movement Competence: try different approaches, such as adjusting body position or speed, to help maintain control of a ball with their feet while running down the field; Healthy Living: identify how to get help in different situations - in emergencies, when confronted with violence, when being bullied or witnessing someone else being bullied, to prevent injury) 

Student: “When I am dribbling the ball with my feet, I need to move fairly slowly to keep the ball in control. I am working on keeping my head up. As I practise, I am gradually gaining more control and am able to move faster.”
</specific>
          <specific>1.3 communicate effectively, using verbal or non-verbal means, as appropriate, and interpret information accurately as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: warn others and report to the teacher if any equipment is broken or unsafe to use; Movement Competence: when working with a partner to create a developmental gymnastics sequence, listen to their partner and share ideas for ways to improve the sequence; Healthy Living: practise using refusal skills if presented with choices or peer pressure regarding use of alcohol or tobacco)
</specific>
          <specific>1.4 apply relationship and social skills as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living to help them interact positively with others, build healthy relationships, and become effective team members (e.g., Active Living: demonstrate leadership skills by taking turns leading warm-up activities; Movement Competence: collaborate with teammates to plan how to move the ball up the field, then follow through with the plan; Healthy Living: show respect for others by giving classmates encouragement and praise and by avoiding behaviours such as calling people names or excluding them; show respect for cultural diversity) 

Student: “Our plan to keep the ball away from the other team didn’t work. I think we need to work on using shorter passes to try to hold on to the ball.”</specific>
          <specific>1.5 use a range of critical and creative thinking skills and processes to assist them in making connections, planning and setting goals, analysing and solving problems, making decisions, and evaluating their choices in connection with learning in health and physical education (e.g., Active Living: make connections between being active and working towards personal fitness goals; Movement Competence: explain the idea of “healthy competition”, what it involves and what it should not involve, and how the presence or absence of those features might affect participation in physical activity; explore how using different speeds and pathways can enhance a dance sequence; Healthy Living: describe how the media can influence their food choices)
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>