<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/healthcurr18.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Active Living">
    <strand_text>Active Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="A1">
        <overall_text>participate actively and regularly in a wide variety of physical activities, and demonstrate an understanding of factors that encourage lifelong participation in physical activity</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A1.1 actively participate in a wide variety of program activities (e.g., lead-up and small-group games, recreational activities, cooperative games, fitness activities, dance activities), according to their capabilities, while applying behaviours that enhance their readiness and ability to take part (e.g., taking the initiative to be involved in the activity, being open to playing different positions and playing in different groups, respecting others’ ideas and opinions, encouraging others, speaking kindly, maintaining self-control at all times) [PS, IS]
</specific>
          <specific>A1.2 demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to their personal enjoyment of being active (e.g., knowing rules of etiquette and fair play will be observed, having the opportunity to think creatively and adapt activities to individual needs or preferences, being physically and emotionally comfortable in the activities), as they participate in a wide variety of individual and small-group activities and lead-up games [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “You want the activity to be not too hard, not too easy, but just right. Can you work in your group to come up with another activity that is just right for you and just right for your group? What makes it just right for you and for your group?” 

Teacher prompt: “Some people like keeping score in activities. In class we usually don’t. Why not? What are other ways to challenge yourself besides keeping score?” Student: “In class we play to have fun and to learn. We don’t want people to be more worried about points than about playing a good game. Keeping score isn’t necessarily a bad thing, but not keeping score can help us cooperate and work as a team, and we can concentrate on using and practising what we have been taught in class. To challenge yourself, you can focus on how well you are playing or how well the team is playing.”</specific>
          <specific>A1.3 identify factors that motivate participation in physical activity every day at school, at home, or in their communities (e.g., enjoyment; availability of programs; proximity and accessibility of facilities such as community centres, lakes, or nature trails; availability of bike racks; support of family and peer group; cultural relevance of activities) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What motivates you to be active at school? What motivates you to be active at home?”

Students: “My friends are joining the new cricket intramural program at lunch. I want to join too.” “At school, having good music to move to during DPA makes me want to be active.” “Our environment club at school is making a school garden. I love being outside, digging in the earth and watching things grow, but I don’t have a chance to do it at home because I live in an apartment. I am active every day as I help with digging and watering.” “My friends and I often cycle on the trails near our house. It’s a lot of fun.” “There is a free drop-in program at our local community centre. I am allowed to go there after school. It’s fun because anyone can go.” “I enjoy dancing and playing games at Friendship Centre socials and feasts.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the importance of being physically active, and apply physical fitness concepts and practices that contribute to healthy, active living</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A2.1 Daily physical activity (DPA): participate in sustained moderate to vigorous physical activity, with appropriate warm-up and cool-down activities, to the best of their ability for a minimum of twenty minutes each day (e.g., running, wheeling their wheelchair to music, skipping to music, doing light warm-up aerobic activity before stretching, doing parachute activities) [PS]</specific>
          <specific>A2.2 identify how different physical activities affect the body and contribute to physical fitness and good health (e.g., dancing and cross-country running develop cardiorespiratory fitness and endurance, abdominal crunches develop muscular endurance and/or strength, climbing activities develop muscular strength, yoga develops flexibility and muscular strength, proper stretching activities develop flexibility and prevent injury) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Today we will spend a good deal of time stretching during the warm-up and cool-down. However, stretching alone should not be done as a warm-up to an activity, as you could injure your muscles when they are cold. We will begin by doing three to five minutes of light walking, running, or wheeling so that our muscles gradually warm up. We will then slowly stretch each of the major muscles to get them ready for our fitness routine. Which component of fitness will we be working on when we do this, and why is it important?”

Student: “We will be working on our flexibility. Good flexibility can reduce the chance of getting an injury when we are dancing, playing sports, or just being active.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.3 assess their level of exertion during physical activity, using simple self-assessment techniques (e.g., taking pulse rates before, during, and after taking part in physical activities; checking how they feel during physical activity), and explain how intrinsic and extrinsic factors affect the exertion required to perform physical activities (e.g., intrinsic: level of fitness, state of health, energy level; extrinsic: familiarity with the activity; weather extremes such as heat, humidity, or cold) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Compare how you feel before doing the DPA activity and after. What feels different? What affects how you feel when you are being active?”

Student: “I am definitely warmer and more energized after doing DPA. My heart rate goes up during the activity but goes back to normal fairly quickly after. Lots of things affect how I feel during DPA. The more fit I am, the easier it is to do. It gets easier with practice. I have different amounts of energy on different days. If I have had a good breakfast, a good sleep the night before, and things are going well with my friends and family, I feel better overall and doing DPA feels easier. The temperature of the room also affects how I feel. I like doing DPA in a room that is a bit cool.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.4 develop and act on personal fitness goals based on their interests, self-assessments, and feelings when participating in physical activity [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Now that you have participated in a variety of physical activities that focus on your heart and lungs, what goals do you want to set that relate to cardiorespiratory fitness?”

Students: “I want to develop my cardiorespiratory fitness so that I can ride my bike without stopping for an hour and take part in a charity fund-raiser that’s coming up.” “I want to develop cardiorespiratory fitness so I can push my wheelchair for that race.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate responsibility for their own safety and the safety of others as they participate in physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A3.1 demonstrate behaviours and apply procedures that maximize their safety and that of others during physical activity (e.g., cooperating with others, monitoring their own actions and maintaining control of their bodies and equipment, using equipment such as hula hoops and playground apparatus appropriately, ensuring all chairs are pushed in before beginning DPA in the classroom) [PS, IS] 


Teacher prompt: “What kinds of things do you need to remember in order to participate safely in various physical activities?” 

Student: “If I’m skipping rope, I need to remember that my personal space is much larger. I need to make sure that there is enough room between my classmates and me so that we are not hitting each other with our ropes. If I’m doing activities with a lot of movement, I need to keep my own movement under control so that I don’t bump into other people. If I’m playing floor hockey, I need to use my equipment properly. I should never raise my stick above my waist.” </specific>
          <specific>A3.2 describe common precautions for preventing accidents and injuries while participating in different types of physical activity (e.g., wearing goggles to protect the eyes when playing badminton, wearing a properly fitting helmet to protect the head, tucking in drawstrings to avoid catching them on equipment or other players, fastening all straps on a hockey sledge, staying clear of mud puddles on fields to avoid slipping) [PS, CT]
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Movement">
    <strand_text>Movement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="B1">
        <overall_text>perform movement skills, demonstrating an understanding of the basic requirements of the skills and applying movement concepts as appropriate, as they engage in a variety of physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B1.1 perform a variety of controlled static balances and transitions between balances, using a variety of body parts and shapes, at different levels, individually, and with partners and equipment (e.g., balance on a bench; balance with abdomen on an exercise ball; perform a four-point, threepoint, and two-point balance, with weight on hands; stretch to hold a balance while reaching up while their partner holds a balance at a medium level) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “When balancing with a partner, you can create different shapes when you are supporting each other. You can also create interesting balances together when each person is balancing on their own, for example, with one person in a high shape and one person in a low shape. With a partner, create a balance where a total of three body parts between you are touching the ground. How many different three-point balances can you come up with?”

Student: “We can balance with my hands on the ground and one of my partner’s feet on the ground. We can balance with me on my buttocks and my partner on both feet. We can balance with me on one hand and one foot and my partner on just one foot.” 

Teacher prompt: “Check your body position in your plank balance. Make sure your back is straight and your hips are not up in the air or sagging low.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.2 demonstrate the ability to jump and land, in control, from a low height (e.g., jump off a bench and land in a stable position) [PS] 
 
Teacher prompt: “To have a stable and safe landing, you need to lower your centre of gravity and have a wide base of support. Check your position. Are your arms out, head up, feet shoulder-width apart, and knees bent? Did you make a soft landing on your feet? Pretend there are bells tied to your shoes, and when you land, you want to land gently enough so you don’t hear them.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.3 perform different combinations of locomotor movements with and without equipment, alone and with others, moving at different speeds and levels, using different pathways, and going in different directions (e.g., travel under, over, around, and through equipment in an obstacle course; hop and skip in a zigzag pattern, following a specific rhythm; run and leap over a line; use different levels while performing traditional and creative dances; perform t’ai chi or yoga movements slowly and at a moderate pace; wheel their wheelchair through an obstacle course, turn, and wheel back) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Create a movement sequence. Use a combination of different speeds, directions, pathways, and levels. Make sure to consider how you will transition smoothly from one action to the next.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.4 send and receive objects of a variety of shapes and sizes at different levels and speeds, using different body parts and equipment, while applying basic principles of movement* (e.g., balance on the balls of their feet to be ready to move when receiving; step forward with the opposite foot and use the whole body when throwing a ball to achieve maximum force; use a scoop to explore different ways of catching a ball or beanbag; perform underhand and overhand throws with their dominant and non-dominant hands while keeping their eyes on the target; kick or trap a ball at various heights while remaining aware of their surroundings; move their feet and transfer their weight backwards to absorb force when receiving; move arms or legs faster to send with more force; toss and catch scarves in front of their bodies, following a simple pattern, when learning to juggle) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What do you do when you strike a beach ball in order to get it to your partner?”

Students: “I point my striking hand at my partner to help direct the ball where I want it to go.” “I use a wheelchair. I need to position my wheelchair to face my partner before I hit the beach ball. I need to think about wheelchair position so it suits my strength - I might have to move it closer to my partner to make sure the beach ball reaches him.” “I am visually impaired. I ask my partner to clap his hands or make a noise to help show me where to send the ball.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.5 retain objects of various shapes and sizes in different ways, using different body parts, with and without equipment, while moving around others and equipment (e.g., hold a rubber ring close to their body while running; bounce and cradle a ball while pivoting during a rhythmic gymnastics routine; practise keeping their head up while dribbling a ball between pylons or people with their dominant and non-dominant hand and foot; keep a basketball on their lap while wheeling in a straight line; carry a ball in a scoop from one end of the gym to the other while avoiding contact with others) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “When you are travelling down the field with your stick and ball, be sure to keep your head up and plan your route to avoid contact with others and with equipment.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="B2">
        <overall_text>apply movement strategies appropriately, demonstrating an understanding of the components of a variety of physical activities, in order to enhance their ability to participate successfully in those activities.
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>demonstrate an understanding of the basic components of physical activities (e.g., movement skills, game structures, basic rules and guidelines, conventions of fair play and etiquette), and apply this understanding as they participate in a variety of physical activities (e.g., lead-up games such as two-on-two soccer, beach-ball volleyball, and small-group keep-away; recreational activities such as scooter-board activities, hula hoop challenges, and throwing and catching a disc; cooperative games, such as keep-it-up, team monster walk, and group juggling; fitness activities such as circuits, running, and flexibility exercises; dance activities such as creative movement, folk dance, and First Nation, Métis, and Inuit dances) [IS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “When your group of three is creating a dance movement sequence, what do you need to do to cooperate to create the sequence? What movement skills and concepts do you need to know to do this?”

Student: “To cooperate, we need to respect the abilities of all the group members and choose activities that everyone can do. Different people can do different moves, depending on their abilities. We may have to compromise about what we include, so that everyone agrees on the parts of the movement sequence. We need time to listen to one another, share ideas, and practise together. To put together interesting routines, we need to use our balancing skills and our understanding of how to move in different ways, and also consider how and where our bodies move and how we interact with others.” 

Teacher prompt: “When setting up a game of two-on-two keep-away, what rules do you need to agree to as a group?”

Student: “We need to agree on the equipment we will use and the boundaries, and then on any rules we decide to add, like number of passes, number of steps you can take with the ball, or number of seconds you can hold the ball.”</specific>
          <specific>B2.2 identify common features of specific categories of physical activities* (e.g., individual, target, net/wall, striking/fielding, territory), and identify common strategies and tactics that they found effective while participating in a variety of physical activities in different categories [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Games and activities can be grouped into categories that have similar characteristics. You can use similar strategies and transfer learning from one activity to another in the same category. For example, think of some individual activities that have commonalities. What common strategies might you use in activities like dance, figure skating, diving, and synchronized swimming to refine your movements and develop body control?”

Student: “In all of those activities, you need to have good control of your body as you move. I could work on improving my core muscle strength and body control. I could also get feedback from others and experiment with different pieces of the sequence to get new and creative ideas. I can practise the full sequence so that I can move more smoothly from one body position to the next.” 

Teacher prompt: “The target games of curling, golf, bocce, lawn bowling, bowling, archery, and blind curling all emphasize accuracy and control as you try to get an object as close as possible to a target. What similar strategies might you use in some or all of these activities?”</specific>
          <specific>B2.3 apply a variety of tactical solutions to increase their chances of success as they participate in physical activities (e.g., individual activities: establish a breathing rhythm when swimming, use a video showing tricks and moves with a skipping rope to learn how to break down a new move into simpler steps; target activities: choose a larger target for optimal success; net/wall activities: assume a ready position that will allow them to be ready to move in a variety of directions to defend a space; striking/fielding activities: throw or kick the ball away from fielders; territory activities: help their team keep possession of the ball by making short passes to teammates in a keep-away game or by changing directions quickly when dribbling a basketball) [IS, CT]* 

Teacher prompt: “Why is it important to be on the balls of your feet and ready to move in a net/wall activity?”

Student: “In net/wall activities, you need to be ready to move quickly if the ball comes near you. If you have your feet moving or are on the balls of your feet, you are always ready to react quickly.” 

Teacher prompt: “Is it a good idea to hit the object to one place all the time in a striking/fielding activity?”

Student: “In striking and fielding activities, it is best to hit the ball to different places in order to keep the other team guessing.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Healthy Living">
    <strand_text>Healthy Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="C1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to healthy development</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C1.1 identify the key nutrients (e.g., fat, carbohydrates, protein, vitamins, minerals) provided by foods and beverages, and describe their importance for growth, health, learning, and physical performance 

Teacher prompt: “Report what you found from your research about nutrients.”

Student: “You can get calcium, which is important for healthy bones and teeth, by drinking milk or a fortified soy beverage and eating dairy products like yogurt and cheese.
“Grains are a good source of carbohydrates and fibre. Carbohydrates give you energy. Fibre-rich foods help you feel full and satisfied, help your bowels function normally, and help reduce the risk of heart disease later in life. Grain products that are lower in fat, sugar, and salt are best. At least half of the grain products we eat each day should be whole grain, like oatmeal or whole-wheat pasta, because whole grains have more fibre. 

“All vegetables and fruits have important nutrients like vitamins, minerals, and fibre. Eating dark green and orange vegetables whenever you can is beneficial. Dark green vegetables have lots of folate and orange vegetables have lots of vitamin A. Folate is especially important during times of rapid growth (infancy and pregnancy), and vitamin A plays a key role in vision.” </specific>
          <specific>C1.2 identify risks associated with communications technology (e.g., Internet and cell phone use, including participation in gaming and online communities and the use of text messaging), and describe precautions and strategies for using these technologies safely [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Modern communications technology has greatly increased our ability to get and share information and to communicate with each other. Possible risks associated with communications technology include loss of privacy, addiction, and exposure to sexual predators. What are some things you should do to use communications technology safely? How can you get help if you get into trouble?”

Student: “I should make sure that an adult knows what I am doing when I’m using the computer, the Internet, or a cell phone, so I have someone who can help if needed. When I can, I should use a computer in a public space like a kitchen, living room, or library, instead of alone in my bedroom. I shouldn’t share my password or personal information. I should be aware that people are not always who they say they are online. I should close and delete pop-ups and spam messages without responding. If there’s a problem, I should stop right away and tell an adult instead of trying to solve the problem online. I should help my friends by reminding them of these tips.”</specific>
          <specific>C1.3 describe various types of bullying and abuse (e.g., social, physical, verbal), including bullying using technology (e.g., via e-mail, text messaging, chat rooms, websites), and identify appropriate ways of responding [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What is an example of social bullying? Physical bullying? Verbal bullying?”

Student: “Social bullying could include leaving someone out of the group, refusing to be someone’s partner, spreading rumours in person or online, or totally ignoring someone. Physical bullying could include pushing someone, pulling hair, or knocking a person down. Verbal bullying could include name calling, mocking, teasing about appearance, including weight, size, or clothing, and making sexist, racist, or homophobic comments in person or online. Any of these kinds of bullying could cause emotional pain.” 

Teacher prompt: “Do girls and boys bully in different ways? Is one type of bullying any more or less hurtful than another?”

Student: “It might be more common for boys to bully physically or for girls to bully socially by spreading rumours or leaving people out, but that’s not always true. Social or emotional bullying is more difficult to see but it can be just as hurtful.” 

Teacher prompt: “In cases of abuse, it is not uncommon for the person being abused to know the person who is abusing them. If a friend told you that she had a secret and that she was being abused, how could you help?”

Student: “I would tell my friend to ask an adult that she trusts so that she can get help. I would listen and be there to support my friend.” 

Teacher prompt: “If you are a bystander and you see bullying online, what can you do?”

Student: “I can stand up for the person. I can tell the person being bullied to get offline and try to help them get help.”

Substance Use, Addictions, and Related Behaviours C1.4 identify substances (e.g. nicotine, carbon monoxide, tar) found in tobacco products and smoke (e.g., cigarettes, cigars, pipe tobacco, chewing tobacco, snuff), and describe their effects on health 

Teacher prompt: “What are the dangers of nicotine? What are the dangers of tar?”

Student: “Nicotine is very addictive and is absorbed quickly in your body. The craving for nicotine can make a person very uncomfortable, and that can be stressful. Tar is made up of thousands of chemicals. Many of these chemicals can cause cancer and other illnesses.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to apply health knowledge and living skills to make reasoned decisions and take appropriate actions relating to their personal health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C2.1 analyse personal food selections through self-monitoring over time, using the criteria in Canada’s Food Guide (e.g., food groups, portion size, serving size), and develop a simple healthy-eating goal appropriate to their age and activity level (e.g., eat breakfast every day; include at least one fruit or vegetable at each meal and snack; help with food shopping and meal preparation at home; plan a meal using the First Nation, Inuit, and Métis food guide) [CT]
 
Teacher prompt: “When making food choices, how do you know how much food you need?”

Student: “Canada’s Food Guide tells us how many servings we need in each food group and how big each serving should be. For example, one serving of grain products could be one slice of bread, half a pita, or half a cup (about a handful) of cooked rice.” 

Teacher prompt: “When setting your healthy-eating goal, what do you need to do to ensure you accomplish your goal?” 

Student: “I need to keep track of where I start and how I am doing. I need to have a plan. I can help to accomplish my goal by talking with my family about healthy eating, learning how to cook simple meals, and helping with making my lunch.” 

Teacher prompt: “Being aware of your eating habits is important. As a Grade 4 student, you don’t always have control over what you eat, but you can do your best to make the best choices from what is available. For example, if you have a choice between pop or milk, you could choose milk. Instead of fries, you could choose a baked potato or brown rice, if they were available. Describe something you have eaten recently and identify a healthier alternative.”

Student: “I ate a sandwich with mayonnaise, margarine, mustard, and bologna on white bread. A healthier choice would have been a sandwich on whole wheat bread or a pita wrap, with either mayonnaise, margarine, or mustard instead of all three of these. Adding vegetables like tomatoes, lettuce, bean sprouts, or cucumbers to my sandwich and having an unprocessed meat such as chicken breast or a bean/chickpea spread instead of bologna would also be healthier. Another healthier choice might be to eat something completely different, such as rice and fish.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.2 apply a decision-making process (e.g., identify potential dangers and risks, consider ways to stay safe, consider the pros and cons of each option, consider whether they need to check with an adult, choose the safest option, act, reflect on their decision, consider whether there is anything they could improve for next time) to assess risks and make safe decisions in a variety of situations (e.g., when using a wheelchair, cycling, preparing food) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What safety considerations do you need to think about when you make a snack after school?”

Student: “I need to think about whether food that needs refrigeration has been kept cold and whether my hands, work surfaces, and utensils are clean. I also need to be sure that I know how to use the appliances and utensils safely.” 

Teacher prompt: “Before riding your bike to school, what do you need to think about and what do you need to do to be safe?”

Student: “I should think about what I need to have and how to stay safe. Do I have a helmet that fits right and that’s properly fastened? Do I need to take any precautions because of the weather? What routes can I take, and how much traffic is there on them? How will I carry my books and lunch? Will I be riding with anyone else, and should we ride side by side or in a line? What is my plan if there is a problem, like a crash, or if something breaks on my bike?”
</specific>
          <specific>C2.3 demonstrate the ability to make and support healthy, informed choices about smoking, using their understanding of factors that affect decisions about smoking and a variety of personal and interpersonal skills and thinking processes (e.g., applying decision-making, assertiveness, and refusal skills; thinking in advance about values and personal choices; identifying the pros and cons of both making a change and not making a change; being aware of peer pressure; avoiding situations where people will be smoking; using conversational strategies, such as saying no strongly and clearly, giving reasons, changing the topic, making a joke, asking a question) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some examples of things that might influence someone to smoke or not to smoke?”

Student: “Kids might be more likely to try smoking if their friends and family members smoke, or if someone dares them to smoke, or if it is easy for them to get cigarettes. They might be less likely to try smoking if they are not old enough to buy cigarettes legally so cigarettes are harder to get or if they know someone who got cancer or emphysema because of smoking.” 

Teacher prompt: “How is tobacco used traditionally in First Nation and Métis societies? What is the difference between the spiritual or sacred use of tobacco in First Nation and Métis culture and the commercial use of tobacco?”

Student: “Among the First Nations and the Métis, tobacco is often used in small amounts in ceremonies connected to cleansing and communicating with the spirit world. In these cultures tobacco is one of the four sacred medicines (natural tobacco, cedar, sage, and sweetgrass). In its original form, tobacco had a spiritual purpose. The tobacco used in cigarettes and cigars is harmful to our health and not connected to spirituality.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to make connections that relate to health and well-being - how their choices and behaviours affect both themselves and others, and how factors in the world around them affect their own and others’ health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C3.1 identify ways of promoting healthier food choices in a variety of settings and situations (e.g., school, arena, recreation centre, stores, food courts, special events; when camping, having a snack or meal at a friend’s house, eating on weekends versus weekdays) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Our school is a healthy school, and we have a breakfast program and a snack program. How do these programs affect people’s food choices? How can the programs promote healthier food choices?”

Student: “The programs give us more healthy foods to choose from. They give all the students a chance to try different kinds of healthy foods that they might not otherwise be able to try.”

Teacher: “If you had to go directly to a lesson or practice after school, what could you plan for a snack that would be healthy and give you sustained energy?”

Student: “If I planned ahead, I could bring a healthy snack like yogurt or a piece of cheese and fruit or cut-up vegetables. If I buy a snack, I need to think about what would be the healthiest choice from what is available.”

Teacher: “What can you do to promote the availability of healthier food choices in community settings?”

Student: “I can ask for healthier choices - for veggie dogs at the arena, for example, instead of just regular hot dogs. If people keep asking for healthier choices, businesses might start to sell them.”

Teacher: “What kinds of things might you consider before inviting a friend to your home for a meal or a sleepover?”

Student: “I would ask if my friend has any food allergies or cannot eat certain foods for religious or cultural reasons and make sure my parents know about these.”
</specific>
          <specific>C3.2 describe the short- and long-term effects of first- and second-hand smoke on smokers and on people around them 

Teacher prompt: “What are some effects of smoking?”

Student: “Some of the short-term effects can include bad breath and bad clothing and hair odours, and possibly some problems with family and friends, like arguments with parents. Young people who smoke are more likely to be less active, hang out with other kids who smoke, try other drugs, and not do as well at school. Longer-term effects can include addiction, yellow teeth, getting out of breath easily, reduced energy and activity levels, respiratory diseases, and lung or oral cancer. Second-hand smoke makes the air unpleasant to breathe and makes clothing smell. Over the long term, exposure to secondhand smoke increases a person’s risk of getting lung cancer or other respiratory diseases.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Living Skills">
    <strand_text>Living Skills</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate personal and interpersonal skills and the use of critical and creative thinking processes as they acquire knowledge and skills in connection with the expectations in the Active Living, Movement Competence, and Healthy Living strands for this grade</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 use self-awareness and self-monitoring skills to help them understand their strengths and needs, take responsibility for their actions, recognize sources of stress, and monitor their own progress, as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: explain what makes them enjoy their favourite activities, and consider what this tells them about themselves; Movement Competence: identify which skills they perform with the most confidence and which ones are most difficult for them; Healthy Living: set a healthy eating goal connected to Canada’s Food Guide serving requirements for their age) 

Student: “I am nine years old, and Canada’s Food Guide says someone my age should eat six servings of fruits and vegetables every day. I should try to eat a piece of fruit plus at least one vegetable at every meal.”
</specific>
          <specific>1.2 use adaptive, management, and coping skills to help them respond to the various challenges they encounter as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: describe how joining a school-wide activity such as an intramural team or club can benefit them; Movement Competence: choose equipment that will help them succeed in learning a skill or refining a skill; Healthy Living: describe how being aware of their feelings can help them adjust to physical and emotional changes at puberty) 

Student: “I am getting better at throwing and catching, so I want to try it now with a smaller ball. I’m picking a tennis ball - it will be a good challenge.”</specific>
          <specific>1.3 communicate effectively, using verbal or non-verbal means, as appropriate, and interpret information accurately as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: use encouraging words to support teammates when playing in small groups; Movement Competence: signal with one hand or another to indicate whether they want to receive a pass using their dominant or their non-dominant hand; Healthy Living: identify what a bystander could do or say when someone calls another person names) 

Student: “When you say things like ‘nice play’ and ‘good throw’, it makes other people feel good when they are playing with you.”
</specific>
          <specific>1.4 apply relationship and social skills as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living to help them interact positively with others, build healthy relationships, and become effective team members (e.g., Active Living: play fairly by maintaining self-control and sharing opportunities to play; Movement Competence: cooperate with group members to develop a creative movement sequence; Healthy Living: explain what they can do, when sending text messages or communicating online, to avoid saying something that they wouldn’t say face to face; identify some of the teachings of First Nation, Métis, or Inuit cultures that can help them strengthen their own relationships) Critical and Creative Thinking (CT)*
</specific>
          <specific>1.5 use a range of critical and creative thinking processes to assist them in making connections, planning and setting goals, analysing and solving problems, making decisions, and evaluating their choices in connection with learning in health and physical education (e.g., Active Living: think through and apply the steps they will take to avoid injury while participating in a physical activity; Movement Competence: group different games and activities according to features they have in common; explore different body positions [arms up or down, body stretched or loose] when doing a log roll to determine which position works best for keeping the roll straight; Healthy Living: with a classmate, brainstorm ways of avoiding unhealthy behaviours or situations that make them feel uncomfortable, and list healthy alternatives)
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>