<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/healthcurr18.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Active Living">
    <strand_text>Active Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="A1">
        <overall_text>participate actively and regularly in a wide variety of physical activities, and demonstrate an understanding of factors that encourage lifelong participation in physical activity</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A1.1 actively participate in a wide variety of program activities (e.g., lead-up games, recreational activities, fitness activities, dance), according to their capabilities, while applying behaviours that enhance their readiness and ability to take part (e.g., being engaged and moving throughout the activity, using time effectively, being open to new activities, displaying fair play by taking turns and sharing, listening to others, not blaming or taking advantage of others) [PS, IS]
</specific>
          <specific>A1.2 demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to their personal enjoyment of being active (e.g., having the opportunity to participate in activities in various sizes of groups and using various types of equipment, having a choice of activities, being able to take part in activities that are modified to suit their individual needs, being able to participate actively in a game or activity rather than having to sit it out, having a chance to take part in both team games and individual activities, experiencing pleasure in both the physical experiences and the aesthetic aspects of movement), as they participate in a wide variety of individual and small-group activities and lead-up games [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Involving everyone in the activity makes the activity more enjoyable for all. How can you ensure everyone is involved?”

Student: “By playing in groups of four instead of groups of eight, everyone gets lots of turns. Our group adjusted the boundaries to make it easier for everyone to play.” 

Teacher prompt: “When your group creates its dance sequence, all of you have to agree about what you are going to do and participate fully. If someone doesn’t agree, you need to find ways to negotiate or compromise.”
</specific>
          <specific>A1.3 describe factors that motivate them to participate in physical activity every day, at school and during leisure time, and that influence their choice of activities (e.g., influence of friends, enthusiasm for the outdoors, a preference for either team or individual activities, encouragement from others, increased time with friends, availability of a program, enjoyment of healthy competition, influence of media role models) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “How do the things that motivate you to be active affect what you choose to do?”

Students: “I really like being outdoors, so I will pick activities that give me a chance to be outside. There is a new hiking and outdoor activities club being started at lunch. None of my friends are joining, but I think it sounds interesting, and I might meet someone new.” “I am learning traditional dancing because I want to learn about something that has a connection to my culture.” “I love competing and I love team sports and activities. Lots of team sports, like soccer, are available in my community.” “I do not like team sports, but I do like being active with other people. I kayak with my aunt on the weekends and, whenever I can, I go to the skateboard park with my friends.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the importance of being physically active, and apply physical fitness concepts and practices that contribute to healthy, active living</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A2.1 Daily physical activity (DPA): participate in sustained moderate to vigorous physical activity, with appropriate warm-up and cool-down activities, to the best of their ability for a minimum of twenty minutes each day (e.g., hiking, playing lead-up soccer, doing fitness circuits, doing aerobic routines, orienteering; walking to reduce heart rate after activity, holding stretches after running) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “After our vigorous activity during DPA, we will walk slowly as our heartbeats return to a resting rate. We will stretch when our muscles are warm. Why is it important to stretch when our muscles are warm, and what should we remember as we do our stretches?”

Student: “Stretching when our muscles are warm reduces the risk of injury. It is important to stretch after doing any physical activity. As we do our stretches, we need to hold each stretch at the point of tension or tightness, but not to the point of pain.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.2 explain how participation in physical activities affects personal health-related fitness (e.g., muscular strength and endurance activities help tone and strengthen muscles, flexibility activities can help prevent injuries, cardiorespiratory activities can improve the immune system) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Canada’s Physical Activity Guide for Youth recommends doing a combination of flexibility, strength, and endurance activities - both cardiorespiratory and muscular. How does your participation in physical activity affect your physical and mental health?”

Student: “I go swimming once a week, I ride my bike or walk to school every day, and I play road hockey as often as I can after school. The walking, biking, swimming, and hockey all help my ‘cardio’, because they are activities that make my heart beat faster and make me breathe deeply. These activities also help to build my muscular endurance. They help with my flexibility too, but I probably need to do more work specifically on my flexibility and also on my muscular strength. As I develop my fitness I find I have more energy, I get sick less often, and I generally feel more positive and happier.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.3 assess their level of health-related fitness (i.e., cardiorespiratory endurance, muscular strength, muscular endurance, flexibility) as they participate in various physical activities (e.g., comparing how they feel before, during, and after an activity or simple fitness tasks), and monitor changes in their physical fitness over time (e.g., comparing their personal results and physical activity participation over a period of time, such as the beginning, middle, and end of the school term) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Can you give me examples of things that would be signs of fitness development over time?”

Students: “Holding myself in a front support or plank position has gotten easier from the beginning of the school year. I used to have to put my knees down after about ten seconds. I have been practising a lot and now I can hold a solid plank position for more than twenty seconds. I can tell that my core muscles are getting stronger.” “I felt a burning sensation again in my legs after doing the wall-sit, but it is not as difficult to hold as it was last month. I think my legs are getting stronger.” “I am working on being able to hold myself up out of my wheelchair for longer periods of time. My arms used to get very shaky, and I would just drop into the seat. I am getting stronger. I can hold myself for longer before I begin to shake.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.4 develop and implement plans of action based on both their assessments of their health-related components of fitness and their interests, in order to achieve personal fitness goals (e.g., improving cardiorespiratory fitness by doing activities that increase the heart rate in order to be able to walk or run faster or wheel a specified distance; enhancing flexibility by holding a stretch for a designated amount of time) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “You have identified which health-related component of fitness you are going to focus on for your fitness goal. What will you do to help achieve your goal?”

Students: “I want to work on my cardiorespiratory fitness so I can go around the school property five times without stopping. I know that I will have to build up to this goal gradually. I will start by running and taking walking breaks when I need to, but gradually I won’t need to take them as often.” “I want to be able to play in a wheelchair basketball league, but I know I need to develop my arm strength to be able to play for as long as I need to during a game. I plan to work on doing lifts from my chair to help develop my arm strength.” “Because of my muscular dystrophy, I have muscle weakness. I have an individualized fitness plan, which was developed by my health care team - my doctor, my occupational and physical therapists, and my teacher. My plan outlines the kinds of exercise and the movements I can do safely. I will work towards the goals in my plan at my own pace, and I’ll ask for support when I need it.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate responsibility for their own safety and the safety of others as they participate in physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A3.1 demonstrate behaviours and apply procedures that maximize their safety and that of others during physical activity (e.g., demonstrating personal responsibility; checking that equipment is in good working order; wearing an appropriate and properly fitting helmet when taking part in activities such as bike riding, downhill skiing, or skateboarding; helping someone adjust the straps on his/her wheelchair) [PS, IS] 


Teacher prompt: “What do you need to check to make sure your equipment is safe to use?”

Student: “I need to make sure the equipment fits and that it’s not broken. For example, if a bat is cracked, it shouldn’t be used.”
</specific>
          <specific>A3.2 describe appropriate methods for treating minor injuries that may occur while participating in physical activity (e.g., applying pressure and ice to reduce swelling, cleaning and bandaging minor cuts, applying pressure to reduce bleeding, treating injuries quickly so they do not become worse) [PS, CT]
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Movement">
    <strand_text>Movement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="B1">
        <overall_text>perform movement skills, demonstrating an understanding of the basic requirements of the skills and applying movement concepts as appropriate, as they engage in a variety of physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B1.1 perform smooth transfers of weight in relation to others and equipment in a variety of situations involving static and dynamic balance (e.g., shift weight smoothly during hip hop dancing; perform twists and balances on a stability ball; with a partner, use resistance [pushing] and counter-tension [pulling] by shifting and adjusting their weight and position to create a stable partner balance; move smoothly from a downward dog pose in yoga to a standing pose) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “When creating a partner balance, how do you use your weight and your balance skills to create a stable balance?”

Student: “My partner and I experiment with leaning backwards and forward to find the spot where we feel most balanced and secure. We sometimes need to change where our feet are positioned or how close we are to the ground to find a position where we feel stable. Just like when we are balancing on our own, keeping low to the ground, using a wide base of support, and keeping our muscles tight are things that help to make the balance more stable.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.2 perform a wide variety of locomotor movements, in combination, at different speeds, in different directions, and using different pathways, while moving around others and/or equipment (e.g., wheel their wheelchair around objects and at different speeds in a fitness circuit; create a developmental gymnastics sequence with a partner that uses a range of movements and shows changes in speed, level, and formation) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “When creating your sequence to the music using a hula hoop, consider how to use your hula hoop in different ways - spinning it, tossing it to a partner, rolling it in different directions. Consider also how you move your body through, around, over and under the hoop, changing your own speed in relation to the movement of the hoop.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.3 send and receive a variety of objects (e.g., rubber chickens, rings, beanbags, soft foam balls, discs, tennis balls, utility balls), adjusting for speed and distance, while applying basic principles of movement* (e.g., use different amounts of force to send an object to a teammate, depending on relative positions and type of object being thrown, batted, or kicked; send an object through a hoop, into a bucket, to a target on a wall, to a specific spot on the other side of a net, to a partner; bend knees, keeping arms out and head up in a ready position to prepare to receive an object; use the body to absorb an object that is sent with greater force; follow through in the direction of the target to improve aim and accuracy) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Once you are comfortable throwing and catching an object with a partner when you are stationary, try sending the object so your partner needs to move to catch it. After that, try sending and receiving it when both people are moving.”</specific>
          <specific>B1.4 retain objects in a variety of situations while travelling in different pathways and at different speeds in relation to others and equipment (e.g., run to catch a football, then carry it in a “down and out” pattern that first goes down the field, then turns abruptly right or left; stickhandle a felt disc slowly and then quickly while keeping their head up) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “Experiment with how you need to cradle the ball with the lacrosse stick as you run quickly, slowly, forwards, backwards, change direction, and spin around.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="B2">
        <overall_text>apply movement strategies appropriately, demonstrating an understanding of the components of a variety of physical activities, in order to enhance their ability to participate successfully in those activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B2.1 demonstrate an understanding of the basic components of physical activities (e.g., movement skills, game structures, basic rules and guidelines, conventions of fair play and etiquette), and apply this understanding as they participate in a variety of physical activities (e.g., lead-up games such as four-on-four rubber-chicken keep-away, basketball shooting games, and two-base softball; recreational activities such as mini-triathlons, hiking, skipping rope, and cooperative games; fitness activities such as t’ai chi, activities with exercise bands and exercise balls, and personal fitness challenges; dance activities such as cultural dance, jazz, and creative movement) [IS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “How can you apply basic dance steps like a grapevine or a step touch in different dances and other activities?”

Student: “The grapevine step - step-behind-step-touch - or a simple step-touch is used in many folk dances, but you can use those same movements in a jazz, hip hop, or creative dance and make the steps look totally different by changing the way you move or adding arm movements. The same kind of footwork as a grapevine step, without stepping behind, is used when playing basketball or badminton as you shuffle or slide sideways.” 

Teacher prompt: “What movement skills and concepts do you use when you are playing a game like beach ball volleyball?”

Student: “You use skills like sending and receiving in control, getting under the ball to send it upwards, and using different amounts of force. You have to be able to move quickly to different positions on the court to hit the beach ball into an open space.”
</specific>
          <specific>B2.2 describe common features of specific categories of physical activities* (e.g., individual, target, net/wall, striking/fielding, territory), and describe strategies that they found effective while participating in a variety of physical activities in different categories [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Striking/fielding games such as cricket, softball, lob ball, three-pitch, stickball, kickball, soccer baseball, and beep baseball all involve striking, running, retrieving an object, and returning it. Runners hit, kick, or throw an object, then score runs by running around a designated area or areas, usually called bases. Fielders work to retrieve the object quickly and return it to stop the runner. What strategies might be common to all of these activities?”

Student: “In all of these games, sending the object away from the fielders can help you score more runs. You need to watch the position of the ball, think about how far you have to run, and think about how fast you can run in order to plan when it is safe to run from base to base. Fielders need to be ready to retrieve the object quickly and work together to try to stop the runner.” 

Teacher prompt: “Consider what is similar about activities like fencing, t’ai chi, yoga, karate, kendo, qigong, and Pilates. What strategies might you use to improve your performance in all of these activities?”

Student: “Some of these activities are martial arts and were originally about defending yourself. With most of these activities, body form, control, breathing, flexibility, and alignment are important. There is a mind-body connection in these activities, and they require focus and concentration. To improve in these activities, I would need to work on overall fitness, core strength, and flexibility. Developing better control of my breathing would be an important strategy for improving my concentration and control of my movements.”</specific>
          <specific>B2.3 apply a variety of tactical solutions to increase their chances of success as they participate in physical activities (e.g., individual activities: find a comfortable pace when running, wheeling a wheelchair, or speed-walking; work with a partner to develop different ways of using an exercise ball to improve core strength; target activities: in a game like bocce, hit opponents’ balls out of the way in order to make space for their own ball closer to the target; net/wall activities: assume a position of readiness to move to receive an object; practise sending the ball to specific parts of the opposite court; striking/fielding activities: throw the ball promptly to teammates after retrieving it to stop opponents from scoring; territory activities: defend territory by anticipating an opponent’s actions; bounce a utility ball at different heights to keep it from an opponent in a keep-away game; throw a disc to a stationary partner, then move down the field to receive a return pass) [IS, CT]** 

Teacher prompt: “When you are running, how do you find and maintain a steady, comfortable pace?”

Student: “Finding a comfortable pace takes practice. I try different paces and pay attention to how I feel. Running with a partner who likes to run at the same speed is sometimes a good way to maintain a steady pace.” </specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Healthy Living">
    <strand_text>Healthy Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="C1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to healthy development</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C1.1 describe the range of effects associated with using cannabis and other illicit drugs (e.g., crack, cocaine, Ecstasy, crystal methamphetamine) and intoxicating substances (e.g., gas, glue, prescription medications) 

Teacher prompt: “Different types of drugs can have very different effects on your body, depending on whether they are stimulants, depressants, hallucinogens, or psychiatric drugs. Cannabis is a commonly used illicit drug. The effect of cannabis on your body depends on a number of things: how much you use, how often and how long you use it, whether you smoke it or swallow it, your mood, your environment, your age, whether you’ve taken other drugs, and your medical condition. What are some possible effects of using cannabis?”

Student: “Cannabis can change the way you see and feel things - distances can seem shorter or longer than they really are, and things that are serious can seem funny. Larger amounts can lead to feelings of losing control, panic, or confusion. Physical effects include red eyes, dry mouth, a higher heart rate, and a feeling of hunger. Using cannabis often and for a longer time can lead to being physically dependent on it. Then, when people stop using cannabis, they can have withdrawal symptoms, which can include feeling irritable, anxious, or nauseated, not having an appetite, or not being able to sleep well.”

Teacher: “How can these effects of cannabis affect a person’s life?”

Student: “Cannabis can affect your performance at school because it makes it harder to concentrate. It can be dangerous if it’s used with alcohol because it makes the effect of the alcohol stronger and makes you more intoxicated. It can affect your ability to drive safely. It can get you into trouble with the law because it is illegal to grow, possess, or sell cannabis. If you are pregnant, it can affect your baby. But cannabis is also used for some medical purposes, such as relieving nausea and stimulating appetite in patients who have cancer or AIDS.”</specific>
          <specific>C1.2 identify people and community resources (e.g., elders, family members, community agencies, churches, mosques, synagogues, public health units, telephone help lines, recreation facilities) that can provide support when dealing with choices or situations involving substance use and addictive behaviours 

Teacher prompt: “How can calling a telephone help line provide support?” Student: “Talking with someone about problems can help you look at things from different perspectives. Sometimes you need to get help to deal with stress and to cope.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to apply health knowledge and living skills to make reasoned decisions and take appropriate actions relating to their personal health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C2.1 apply their knowledge of medical, emotional, practical, and societal factors that influence eating habits and food choices (e.g., allergies and sensitivities, likes and dislikes, dental health, food availability, media influences, cultural influences, influence of family and friends, school food and beverage policies, environmental impact, cost) to develop personal guidelines for healthier eating [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “How can a busy lifestyle lead to poor eating habits and food choices, and what can you do to eat better when you are busy?” Student: “When you’re busy, it is easy to eat whatever is quick and convenient, which is not always healthy. To eat better, you have to fit your healthy eating goals into your lifestyle. If I bring a snack with me, I usually eat healthier food than if I grab something on my way. If I have to pick something up on the way, I try to make the healthiest choice from what is available. In our family, we eat meals together whenever we can. When our family eats together, we eat healthier food and have time to enjoy the food and the company.” 

Teacher prompt: “How do you handle emotional and social factors that could lead to poor eating habits or choices?”

Student: “I try to be aware of why I am eating. Sometimes I eat because I’m bored or lonely and have a treat to make me feel better or because the people I am with are eating. Sometimes I eat without thinking because I’m distracted. I make healthier choices when I’m feeling better. If I think about why I want to eat and whether I’m really hungry, I might decide to do something different instead of eating. I make better food choices when I’m with people who are also making healthy choices. Thinking about the situations where it’s easier to make healthy choices is useful for me. I also try to be aware of media messages about eating and know that what I am seeing and hearing may not always match up with healthy eating practices.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.2 apply their recognition of internal hunger and thirst cues and their knowledge of physical factors that influence the desire to eat and drink (e.g., stage of development, growth spurts, level of physical activity, eating larger portions) to develop personal guidelines for healthier eating [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “How do you feel if you wait until you are very hungry to eat? How does your body feel when you have eaten too much?” Student: “When I’m very hungry, I eat quickly and I don’t really taste my food. Sometimes I keep eating before I realize that I’m full. I end up feeling uncomfortable. I need to be aware of those things and try to eat when I’m hungry and stop when I’m full.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.3 apply personal skills and interpersonal skills (e.g., self-awareness and self-management skills, including anger management; communication skills, including listening skills and assertiveness skills) to promote positive interaction and avoid or manage conflict in social situations (e.g., classroom groups, groups of friends, sports teams, school clubs) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “If someone does something that makes you feel very angry, what can you do to manage your anger?”

Student: “I can take some deep breaths, walk away, and give myself some time and space to cool down. Doing something outdoors and physical, like running, swimming, playing basketball, or biking, helps me. When I am calmer, I can think about what made me angry and about whether there is anything I can do to prevent the situation from happening again.” 

Teacher prompt: “When working in groups, what have you found helpful in making your group function well?”

Student: “Our group works best when we make sure everyone gets a turn to speak, when we are clear about what everyone is supposed to do, and when we listen to each other and treat each other with respect.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.4 use decision-making strategies and skills and an understanding of factors influencing drug use (e.g., personal values, peer pressure, media influences, curiosity, legal restrictions, cultural teachings) to make safe personal choices about the use of drugs such as alcohol, tobacco, and cannabis [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “How can peers influence your decisions about using drugs? How might you respond to those influences?”

Student: “Some peers may try to influence you to do drugs by saying it’s cool to do them, or sometimes you may just want to be part of a crowd that’s doing drugs. To avoid this kind of influence, you have to be strong as an individual, think about what you really want and what you value, and make up your own mind about things. Even if someone tells you ‘everyone is doing it’, your decisions are your own, and so are the consequences. But peers can be a positive influence too. Hanging out with friends who don’t use drugs can keep you from using drugs. It also helps to have good role models in your family or community.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to make connections that relate to health and well-being - how their choices and behaviours affect both themselves and others, and how factors in the world around them affect their own and others’ health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C3.1 explain how healthy eating and active living work together to improve a person’s general health and well-being (e.g., both provide more energy and contribute to improved self-concept, greater resistance to disease, and better overall health; both help a person to maintain a weight that is healthy for them) and how the benefits of both can be promoted to others [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Why is healthy eating important for active living? How does active living affect the way we eat and the way our bodies use the food we eat?” Student: “Eating healthy foods gives me the nutrients I need to be energetic and active. Healthy food and physical activity are both necessary to build stronger bones and muscles. Being active also gives me more of an appetite. When I am more active, I need to eat more because I am using more energy and burning more calories.” 

Teacher prompt: “How can you promote the benefits of healthy eating and active living at school?” Student: “I can lead by example. I can be a role model for younger students at recess by having a healthy snack, like a piece of fruit, and playing an active game, like tag, instead of standing around.”
</specific>
          <specific>C3.2 recognize the responsibilities and risks associated with caring for themselves and others (e.g., while babysitting, staying home alone, caring for pets, volunteering in the community, assisting someone with a disability, preparing meals, travelling to and from school and other locations), and demonstrate an understanding of related safety practices and appropriate procedures for responding to dangerous situations (e.g., safe practices for preparing food; responses to allergic reactions, fire, sports injuries, dental emergencies, hypothermia, bullying) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What should you do to protect yourself before volunteering in the community?”

Student: “Have a parent or caregiver check to make sure the situation is safe.”

Teacher: “What are some ways in which you could help someone who has a physical disability?”

Student: “I could ask the person if they would like help and, if so, what kind of help. I could help someone who is blind or partially sighted by walking with them as a guide. I might be able to help a person in a wheelchair transfer to a chair, if I were given instructions about how to help.”

Teacher: “If you are preparing a meal for yourself or others, what are some things to be aware of to stay safe?”

Student: “Be cautious and handle all equipment carefully when preparing food and using appliances, sharp knives, or utensils. Keep young children away from sharp knives, hot things, and other objects that could cause injury.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Living Skills">
    <strand_text>Living Skills</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate personal and interpersonal skills and the use of critical and creative thinking processes as they acquire knowledge and skills in connection with the expectations in the Active Living, Movement Competence, and Healthy Living strands for this grade</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 use self-awareness and self-monitoring skills to help them understand their strengths and needs, take responsibility for their actions, recognize sources of stress, and monitor their own progress, as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: identify which of the factors known to motivate participation in physical activity in most people are the strongest factors affecting their own motivation to be active; Movement Competence: assess their technique for catching throws of different speeds - are they remembering to move farther away when a ball is thrown hard and fast?; Healthy Living: reflect on how their body image affects their self-concept, and identify other factors, including acceptance by others, that influence their sense of themselves)
</specific>
          <specific>1.2 use adaptive, management, and coping skills to help them respond to the various challenges they encounter as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: explain why properly fitted helmets and well-secured straps on wheelchairs allow them to participate in physical activities with greater confidence; Movement Competence: explain how adopting a positive attitude and a willingness to try new things helped them have more fun and make progress in learning a new skill or game; Healthy Living: describe how their management and organizational skills are applied when they are preparing to babysit a younger child) 

Student: “When I am preparing to babysit, I always make sure I have the emergency contact information for the parents before I leave. I check to make sure I know what rules and guidelines they expect the children to follow. I also make sure I have a plan to get immediate help if I need it.”
</specific>
          <specific>1.3 communicate effectively, using verbal or non-verbal means, as appropriate, and interpret information accurately as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: use encouraging words to support other students when being active; Movement Competence: communicate clearly when working together in small groups to create a movement sequence; Healthy Living: describe what verbal and non-verbal signals could be used to send messages to others about how you feel about them)
</specific>
          <specific>1.4 apply relationship and social skills as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living to help them interact positively with others, build healthy relationships, and become effective team members (e.g., Active Living: promote fair play, share equipment, take turns, and follow rules when playing lead-up games; show respect for the decisions and calls of teammates when refereeing their own activities; Movement Competence: contribute ideas when working in a group to accomplish a collaborative task; Healthy Living: show awareness of how best to help others by asking questions and responding as directed by the person) 

Students: “Here is a plan: If the ball is hit to left field, I’ll run and get the ball. You run and cover my spot. I’ll throw the ball to you. You throw the ball in to the infield. What do you think of that plan?” “I saw someone with crutches trying to go up the stairs. I asked them if they wanted help instead of assuming that they needed help, because they might have been trying to do it on their own.”</specific>
          <specific>1.5 use a range of critical and creative thinking skills and processes to assist them in making connections, planning and setting goals, analysing and solving problems, making decisions, and evaluating their choices in connection with learning in health and physical education (e.g., Active Living: describe the steps that should be taken when responding to minor injuries; Movement Competence: plan a variety of offensive and defensive tactics that could be used in different situations in striking/fielding games; Healthy Living: describe what can be done to challenge stereotypes and assumptions, and to encourage respect for and acceptance of differences and inclusion of all people in social activities)
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>