<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/scientec18currb.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Understanding Life Systems ">
    <strand_text>Understanding Life Systems </strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>assess ways in which plants have an impact on society and the environment, and ways in which human activity has an impact on plants and plant habitats; </overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 assess ways in which plants are important to humans and other living things, taking different points of view into consideration (e.g., the point of view of home builders, gardeners, nursery owners, vegetarians), and suggest ways in which humans can protect plants 
Sample prompts: Plants provide oxygen and food that other living things need to survive. Plants use and store carbon dioxide, helping reduce the amount of this greenhouse gas in the atmosphere. Trees reduce humans' energy use in summer by providing cooling shade. Leaves, twigs, and branches of trees and shrubs block erosion-causing rainfall. Grass and shrubs prevent soil from washing away. Roots, leaves, and trunks provide homes for wildlife. Aboriginal people use plants for many medicines.</specific>
          <specific>1.2 assess the impact of different human activities on plants, and list personal actions they can engage in to minimize harmful effects and enhance good effects 
Sample prompts: When humans provide common house plants and blooming potted plants with an appropriate environment, they help fight pollution indoors. When humans plant trees, they benefit the environment in many different ways. When humans fill in wetlands to build houses, they destroy an important habitat that supports many plants. When humans pick wildflowers or dig them up to replant in their home gardens, they harm a natural habitat that supports many living things. When humans plant non-native plants and trees that need pesticides and/or a lot of water to survive, they drive out native plants and trees that are adapted to our climate and that provide habitat and food for native birds, butterflies, and mammals. </specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>investigate similarities and differences in the characteristics of various plants, and ways in which the characteristics of plants relate to the environment in which they grow; </overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>2.1 follow established safety procedures during science and technology investigations (e.g., avoid touching eyes when handling plants; never taste any part of a plant unless instructed to do so by the teacher)</specific>
          <specific>2.2 observe and compare the parts of a variety of plants (e.g., roots of grass, carrot, dandelion; stem of cactus, carnation, tree; leaves of geranium, spider plant, pine tree) </specific>
          <specific>2.3 germinate seeds and record similarities and differences as seedlings develop (e.g., plant quick-growing seeds - nasturtium, morning glory, sunflower, tomato, beet, or radish seeds - in peat pellets to observe growth) </specific>
          <specific>2.4 investigate ways in which a variety of plants adapt and/or react to their environment, including changes in their environment, using a variety of methods (e.g., read a variety of non-fiction texts; interview plant experts; view DVDs or CD-ROMs) </specific>
          <specific>2.5 use scientific inquiry/experimentation skills (see page 12), and knowledge acquired from previous investigations, to investigate a variety of ways in which plants meet their basic needs 
Sample guiding questions: How do plants meet their need for air, water, light, warmth, and space? What are different ways in which we can help plants meet their needs?</specific>
          <specific>2.6 use appropriate science and technology vocabulary, including stem, leaf, root, pistil, stamen, flower, adaptation, and germination, in oral and written communication</specific>
          <specific>2.7 use a variety of forms (e.g., oral, written, graphic, multimedia) to communicate with different audiences and for a variety of purposes (e.g., make illustrated entries in a personal science journal to describe plant characteristics and adaptations to harsh environments)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding that plants grow and change and have distinct characteristics.
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>3.1 describe the basic needs of plants, including air, water, light, warmth, and space </specific>
          <specific>3.2 identify the major parts of plants, including root, stem, flower, stamen, pistil, leaf, seed, and fruit, and describe how each contributes to the plant's survival within the plant's environment (e.g., the roots soak up food and water for the plant; the stem carries water and food to the rest of the plant; the leaves make food for the plant with help from the sun; the flowers grow fruit and seeds for new plants) </specific>
          <specific>3.3 describe the changes that different plants undergo in their life cycles (e.g., some plants grow from bulbs to flowers, and when the flowers die off the bulb produces little bulbs that will bloom the next year; some plants grow from germination of a seed to the production of a fruit containing seeds that are then scattered by humans, animals, or the wind so that new plants can grow) </specific>
          <specific>3.4 describe how most plants get energy to live directly from the sun (e.g., plants turn the energy from the sun into food for themselves) and how plants help other living things to get energy from the sun (e.g., Other living things, which cannot "eat"sunshine, eat the plants to get the energy. They also get energy when they eat the animals that eat the plants.) </specific>
          <specific>3.5 describe ways in which humans from various cultures, including Aboriginal people, use plants for food, shelter, medicine, and clothing (e.g., food - from rice plants; houses for shelter - from the wood of trees; medicines - from herbs; clothing - from cotton plants)</specific>
          <specific>3.6 describe ways in which plants and animals depend on each other (e.g., plants provide food for energy; animals help disperse pollen and seeds, and provide manure that fertilizes the soil in which plants grow; plants need the carbon dioxide that animals breathe out, and animals need the oxygen that plants release into the air)</specific>
          <specific>3.7 describe the different ways in which plants are grown for food (e.g., on farms, in orchards, greenhouses, home gardens), and explain the advantages and disadvantages of locally grown and organically produced food, including environmental benefits</specific>
          <specific>3.8 identify examples of environmental conditions that may threaten plant and animal survival (e.g., extreme heat and cold; floods and/or droughts; changes in habitat because of human activities such as construction, use of gas-powered personal watercraft on lakes)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Structures and Mechanisms ">
    <strand_text>Structures and Mechanisms </strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>assess the importance of form, function, strength, and stability in structures through time;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 assess effects of strong and stable structures on society and the environment (e.g., reliable load-bearing structures are essential in all areas of life for shelter, transportation, and many other everyday purposes; strong and stable structures can endure for long periods of time and provide a historical record of other societies and cultures; strong and stable structures can be hard to dispose of when their usefulness is ended and may then have a negative effect on the environment) 
Sample guiding questions: What are some structures that we see or use every day that we depend on to be strong and stable (e.g., bicycle, table, airplane, bridge, tractor, skyscraper)? What features of structures such as old covered bridges, heritage homes, the Pyramids, and the Parthenon have enabled them to still be standing today? What can we learn about strength, stability, form, and function from studying these structures? </specific>
          <specific>1.2 assess the environmental impact of structures built by various animals and those built by humans 
Sample guiding questions: What kinds of materials are used in human constructions (e.g., bricks, cement, wood, adobe, clay/mud, ice/snow)? In animal constructions? How do the purposes of animal structures compare to those of humans? What is the impact on the environment of a dam built by a beaver? Of a nest built by a tent caterpillar in a tree? Of an anthill built in a backyard? What is the impact of homes, shopping plazas, playgrounds, and bridges built by humans? What effects do traditional Aboriginal homes have on the environment? </specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>investigate strong and stable structures to determine how their design and materials enable them to perform their load-bearing function;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>2.1 follow established safety procedures during science and technology investigations (e.g., carry scissors and other cutting tools in a safe manner)</specific>
          <specific>2.2 investigate, through experimentation, how various materials (e.g., paper and wood) and construction techniques (e.g., folding, adding layers, twisting/braiding, changing shapes) can be used to add strength to structures </specific>
          <specific>2.3 investigate, through experimentation, the effects of pushing, pulling, and other forces on the shape and stability of simple structures (e.g., the effect of adding one or more struts on the strength of a tower; the effect of adding ties on the strength of a bridge; the effect of adding weight to the base of a tower on the stability of the tower)</specific>
          <specific>2.4 use technological problem-solving skills (see page 16), and knowledge acquired from previous investigations, to design and build a strong and stable structure that serves a purpose (e.g., a place to store lunch bags, a place to put wet boots)</specific>
          <specific>2.5 use appropriate science and technology vocabulary, including compression, tension, strut, ties, strength, and stability, in oral and written communication</specific>
          <specific>2.6 use a variety of forms (e.g., oral, written, graphic, multimedia) to communicate with different audiences and for a variety of purposes (e.g., an oral report to the class on the results of experiments to strengthen materials) </specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the concepts of structure, strength, and stability and the factors that affect them.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>3.1 define a structure as a supporting framework, with a definite size, shape, and purpose, that holds a load (e.g., a running shoe, a tepee, a bicycle, an igloo)</specific>
          <specific>3.2 identify structures in the natural environment (e.g., a tree, a bees' nest/hive) and in the built environment (e.g., a totem pole, a fence, a pyramid, the CN Tower) </specific>
          <specific>3.3 identify the strength of a structure as its ability to support a load </specific>
          <specific>3.4 identify the stability of a structure as its ability to maintain balance and stay fixed in one spot </specific>
          <specific>3.5 identify properties of materials (e.g., strength, flexibility, durability) that need to be considered when building structures </specific>
          <specific>3.6 describe ways in which the strength of different materials can be altered (e.g., by folding, adding layers, twisting/braiding, changing their shape)</specific>
          <specific>3.7 describe ways to improve a structure's strength (e.g., by using triangulation or cross-members) and stability (e.g., by lowering the centre of gravity)</specific>
          <specific>3.8 explain how strength and stability enable a structure (e.g., bridge, tent) to perform a specific function</specific>
          <specific>3.9 describe ways in which different forces can affect the shape, balance, or position of structures (e.g., a load may cause a cardboard box to buckle)</specific>
          <specific>3.10 identify the role of struts and ties in structures under load (e.g., a strut is added to a wooden frame to resist compression that might cause its collapse; a tie is added to a roof truss to resist tension that might cause the roof to collapse from the weight of the shingles)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Matter and Energy ">
    <strand_text>Matter and Energy </strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>assess the impact of various forces on society and the environment;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 assess the effects of the action of forces in nature (natural phenomena) on the natural and built environment, and identify ways in which human activities can reduce or enhance this impact 
Sample prompts: Erosion: Heavy rains and water run-off naturally erode soil. Humans make erosion happen faster by cutting down trees, removing shrubs and plants, and having too many animals on farmland. When soil is lost through erosion, it pollutes rivers, lakes, and other water systems. When soil is lost on farmlands, farmers cannot grow as many crops. Depleted soil produces crops that provide less nourishment to people. What action can humans take to help prevent erosion? 
Landslides: Landslides can happen anywhere and are triggered by rains, floods, earthquakes, and other natural events. Humans contribute to landslides when they change the land to put in lawns, gardens, roads, and houses. Landslides can destroy houses, transportation routes, and utilities. They can cause flooding and pollute water. They can carry trees and plants away with them. What action can humans take to help prevent landslides? </specific>
          <specific>1.2 assess the impact of safety devices that minimize the effects of forces in various human activities
Sample prompts: What are the costs and benefits of using seatbelts in cars, knee and elbow pads and wrist guards for roller blading, helmets for cycling and hockey, sport shoes designed for high impact sports like aerobics and basketball? </specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>investigate devices that use forces to create controlled movement;</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>2.1 follow established safety procedures during science and technology investigations (e.g., use eye protection when twisting, bending, compressing, or stretching materials) </specific>
          <specific>2.2 investigate forces that cause an object to start moving, stop moving, or change direction (e.g., release a wound-up elastic band to propel a toy vehicle; pull on a leash to stop a dog; hit a ball with a bat; hold papers on a refrigerator door using magnets)</specific>
          <specific>2.3 conduct investigations to determine the effects of increasing or decreasing the amount of force applied to an object (e.g., using two magnets instead of one to pick up pins; changing the number of people on one side of a tug of war; rubbing a balloon ten times instead of five times on a wool sweater to create a static charge)</specific>
          <specific>2.4 use technological problem-solving skills (see page 16), and knowledge acquired from previous investigations, to design and build devices that use forces to create controlled movement (e.g., an airplane propelled by hand or by an elastic band; a boat that holds paper clips and moves through water using magnets; a crane that lifts a load; a timed marble run) 
Sample guiding questions: What is the purpose of your device? What force(s) are being used? How does your device move? How do the force(s) control the movement? How might your device be improved?</specific>
          <specific>2.5 use appropriate science and technology vocabulary, including push, pull, load, distance, and speed, in oral and written communication </specific>
          <specific>2.6 use a variety of forms (e.g., oral, written, graphic, multimedia) to communicate with different audiences and for a variety of purposes (e.g., give a demonstration to show how a device was constructed and how it performs; use a drawing to illustrate the design alterations needed to improve a device; describe with pictures and/or in writing the steps required to build a device)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of how forces cause movement and changes in movement. 
</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>3.1 identify a force as a push or a pull that causes an object to move </specific>
          <specific>3.2 identify different kinds of forces (e.g., gravity - the force that pulls objects towards the earth; electrostatic force - the push or pull that happens with charged objects; magnetic force - the force of a magnet that attracts objects containing iron or nickel) </specific>
          <specific>3.3 describe how different forces (e.g., magnetism, muscular force, gravitational force, friction) applied to an object at rest can cause the object to start, stop, attract, repel, or change direction </specific>
          <specific>3.4 explain how forces are exerted through direct contact (e.g., pushing a door, pulling a toy) or through interaction at a distance (e.g., magnetism, gravity)</specific>
          <specific>3.5 identify ways in which forces are used in their daily lives (e.g., magnetism - fridge magnet; gravity - a falling ball; friction - bicycle brakes) </specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Earth and Space Systems ">
    <strand_text>Earth and Space Systems </strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>assess the impact of soils on society and the environment, and of society and the environment on soils; </overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 assess the impact of soils on society and the environment, and suggest ways in which humans can enhance positive effects and/or lessen or prevent harmful effects 
Sample prompts: Poor soil affects both a plant's ability to take up the nutrients it needs and the quality of the nutrients that are passed from the plant to humans. Some soils do not provide any of the nutrients that are needed to support plant life (e.g., sand in the desert). Landslides can be caused in part by soil conditions and the type of soil in a particular area. </specific>
          <specific>1.2 assess the impact of human action on soils, and suggest ways in which humans can affect soils positively and/or lessen or prevent harmful effects on soils 
Sample prompts: Erosion caused by natural events such as heavy rain or waves and erosion caused by human actions affect soil conditions and cause water pollution. When houses and other buildings are constructed, trees and plants and the top or best layer of soil are often removed from the building site. </specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="2">
        <overall_text>investigate the composition and characteristics of different soils; </overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>2.1 follow established safety procedures during science and technology investigations (e.g., wash hands after working with soil samples)</specific>
          <specific>2.2 investigate the components of soil (e.g., nonliving things such as pebbles and decaying matter; living things such as organic matter, bacteria, earthworms, and insects), the condition of soil (e.g., wet, dry), and additives found in soil (e.g., pesticides, fertilizers, salt), using a variety of soil samples (e.g., sand, clay, loam) from different local environments, and explain how the different amounts of these components in a soil sample determine how the soil can be used </specific>
          <specific>2.3 use scientific inquiry/experimentation skills (see page 12), and knowledge and skills acquired from previous investigations, to determine which type(s) of soil (e.g., sandy soil, clay soil, loam) will sustain life 
Sample guiding questions: What question(s) are you trying to answer with your experiment? What do you predict will happen in your experiment? In what ways will you control the light and/or water? In what ways will you record your observations? What conclusions can you make from your observations? How would this information help someone else (e.g., a gardener)? </specific>
          <specific>2.4 investigate the process of composting, and explain some advantages and disadvantages of composting (e.g., set up a pop-bottle composter in the classroom, and observe what happens over time) 
Sample guiding questions: What is composting? Where does composting happen naturally? What are some good things about composting? Why might people not be able to or want to compost? What "ingredients" do we need to start a classroom composter? What things should not go into the composter? As the compost "cooks", what changes do you notice? What happens to the things that we put into the classroom composter? How will we use our compost? </specific>
          <specific>2.5 use appropriate science and technology vocabulary, including clay, sand, loam, pebbles, earth materials, and soil, in oral and written communication </specific>
          <specific>2.6 use a variety of forms (e.g., oral, written, graphic, multimedia) to communicate with different audiences and for a variety of purposes (e.g., record in words and pictures what happens when soil and water are shaken together in a container; prepare a display comparing the composition of soils from different locations)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the composition of soils, the types of soils, and the relationship between soils and other living things. </overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>3.1 identify and describe the different types of soils (e.g., Sandy soil is made up of minerals and tiny pieces of rock that have come from the erosion and weathering of rocks. It feels gritty and does not stick together well. Sandy soil drains easily and quickly after a rain and warms up quickly in the spring, but does not hold water and nutrients as well as clay soil, and is eroded more easily. Loamy soil is made up of sand, silt, and clay in relatively equal amounts. It sticks together better than sand but not as well as clay. Loamy soil holds water and nutrients well, and also drains well so that sufficient air can reach the roots. Clay soil is a very fine-grained soil that is plastic when wet but hard when dried. It feels slick and smooth. Clay soils have poor drainage and aeration.)</specific>
          <specific>3.2 identify additives that might be in soil but that cannot always be seen (e.g., pesticides, fertilizers, salt) </specific>
          <specific>3.3 describe the interdependence between the living and non-living things that make up soil (e.g., earthworms ingest the soil and absorb the nutrients, then their castings return the nutrients to the soil; the roots of plants use the soil as an anchor to keep the plants from blowing away) </specific>
          <specific>3.4 describe ways in which the components of various soils enable the soil to provide shelter/homes and/or nutrients for different kinds of living things (e.g., microscopic bacteria and micro-organisms feed on decaying matter in the soil; roots of plants absorb minerals from the soil)</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>