<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <strand id="Oral Communication">
    <strand_text>Oral Communication</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>a) communicate in various contexts and for a variety of purposes; b) demonstrate an understanding of a variety of simple oral texts; c) use correctly the grammar and vocabulary elements specified for this grade; d)  use information technology to communicate in the Native language; e) demonstrate a variety of research skills; f) demonstrate knowledge and understanding of aspects of the Native culture studied.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>participate in informal conversations as well as in more formal dialogues (e.g., interview a Native speaker from the community on some local issue);
</specific>
          <specific>demonstrate an understanding of a variety of short oral texts (e.g., compare short oral stories, identify ideas in short oral texts);
</specific>
          <specific>participate in a variety of oral language activities appropriate for the grade (e.g., identify and use various kinds of negative constructions, identify and use different kinds of verbs);</specific>
          <specific>
          </specific>
          <specific>use the local pronunciation correctly;
</specific>
          <specific>give oral presentations on aspects of the Native culture studied (e.g., legends, values, traditions).
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Reading">
    <strand_text>Reading</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>a) communicate in various contexts and for a variety of purposes; b) read for a variety of purposes in the writing system used in the program, including information and enjoyment; c) use information technology to communicate in the Native language;
		d) demonstrate a variety of research skills; e) demonstrate knowledge and understanding of aspects of the Native culture studied.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>read a variety of simple written texts (e.g., short stories by Native authors, local newsletter in the Native language);</specific>
          <specific>demonstrate an understanding of the information and ideas conveyed in written materials (e.g., identify the main ideas and supporting details in short stories);
</specific>
          <specific>participate in a variety of reading activities	appropriate for the grade (e.g., explore the language patterns in short stories);
</specific>
          <specific>use a variety of reading strategies appropriate for the grade (e.g., draw on personal experience, examine context);
</specific>
          <specific>read sentences aloud using proper intonation to convey meaning.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Writing">
    <strand_text>Writing</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>a) communicate in various contexts and for a variety of purposes; b)  use correctly the grammar and vocabulary elements specified for this grade; c) write for a variety of purposes in the writing system used in the program; d) use information technology to communicate in the Native language; e) demonstrate a variety of research skills;
		+ demonstrate knowledge and understanding of aspects of the Native culture studied.</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>write a variety of materials (e.g., summaries of information, dialogues, short stories);
</specific>
          <specific>participate in a variety of writing activities appropriate for the grade (e.g., write a dialogue based on an interpretation of a short story);
</specific>
          <specific>use vocabulary and language structures correctly in their writing;
</specific>
          <specific>use a variety of sentence structures correctly in their writing;
</specific>
          <specific>use information technology to communicate in the Native language with other students;
</specific>
          <specific>use correct spelling in their writing, drawing on a variety of resources (e.g., personal lexicon, classroom-displayed vocabulary lists, print and electronic dictionaries, spell-check feature of software programs);
</specific>
          <specific>demonstrate knowledge and understanding of aspects of the Native culture studied in their writing.
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>