<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>http://www.edu.gov.on.ca/eng/curriculum/elementary/healthcurr18.pdf</pdf>
  <strand id="Active Living">
    <strand_text>Active Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="A1">
        <overall_text>participate actively and regularly in a wide variety of physical activities, and demonstrate an understanding of the value of regular physical activity in their daily lives</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A1.1 actively participate in a wide variety of program activities, according to their capabilities (e.g., individual and small-group activities, dancing to music, cooperative games), while applying behaviours that enhance their readiness and ability to take part (e.g., being engaged and moving throughout the activity; knowing what to do; demonstrating appropriate interpersonal skills, such as active listening, communicating with respect, and providing help to and asking for help from group members) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What does it look like when you are ready to participate?” Student: “I am wearing my running shoes, I’m listening to instructions, and I’m excited about doing the activities. I try to find a partner or get into a group quickly.”</specific>
          <specific>A1.2 demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to their personal enjoyment of being active (e.g., having the opportunity to participate fully in all aspects of an activity, being able to choose the activities they participate in and having choice within the activities, having adequate practice time, having access to safe outdoor play space, being able to take part in activities that are connected to their cultural background) as they participate in a wide variety of individual and small-group activities [PS]
</specific>
          <specific>A1.3 identify reasons for participating in physical activity every day (e.g., to have fun, learn through play, be with classmates who are involved in after-school physical activities, pursue personal interests in certain kinds of activities, enjoy a change from the classroom routine, emulate a role model, interact with family members, improve health, follow cultural teachings) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Canada’s Physical Activity Guide for Children recommends that children build physical activity into their daily routines to create a pattern that will stay with them for the rest of their lives. The guide recommends that children gradually increase active time and decrease non-active time, including screen time. Why is it important to be active every day? What do you like to do to be active?”

Student: “Being active every day helps to make you strong and healthy. I like to do outdoor activities with my friends or family.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of the importance of being physically active, and apply physical fitness concepts and practices that contribute to healthy, active living</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A2.1 Daily physical activity (DPA): participate in sustained moderate to vigorous physical activity, with appropriate warm-up and cool-down activities, to the best of their ability for a minimum of twenty minutes each day (e.g., playing continuous tag games, skipping, wheeling their wheelchair, using hula hoops) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Today, we will be doing a chair aerobics routine for our DPA activity. We will be starting with slow music, and we will move our arm and leg muscles slowly in order to stretch them and warm them up. We will stretch again during the cool-down after our muscles are warm. How will that help us?”
</specific>
          <specific>A2.2 describe different types of activities that improve the strength of the heart and lungs (e.g., running, wheeling fast, walking fast, skipping, dancing to music, doing a fitness circuit, other whole-body or large muscle activities) 

Teacher prompt: “What types of activities do we do that make our hearts and lungs stronger?”

Student: “We can make our hearts and lungs stronger by doing activities that make our hearts beat faster and make us breathe hard. Activities like dancing, running, and jumping do that for me.”</specific>
          <specific>A2.3 recognize their degree of exertion in physical activities by using simple assessment methods (e.g., putting their hand on their chest to feel the increase in heart rate as they move faster, using the talk test [monitoring whether they can talk while being physically active]), and identify factors that affect their performance level (e.g., humidity, extremely cold or warm air, poor air quality, personal fitness level) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Think about how you feel when you are active. Put your thumb up if you feel you were working really hard. Put your thumb down if you feel you were not working hard. Put your thumb somewhere in between if you feel that you were in between.”

Student: “I put my thumb at the ‘in between’ spot because my heart was beating faster and I was breathing harder, but I think I could have done even more. I was a bit tired today because I went to bed late last night, so I did not go as fast as I could have.”
</specific>
          <specific>A2.4 participate in setting and achieving realistic personal and group goals related to physical activity (e.g., a personal goal of doing a physical activity for a specified period of time, a group goal of completing a collective number of class star jumps in a given time frame) [PS, IS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “For the next two songs, keep moving fast for as long as you can. See if you can keep moving in different and interesting ways - galloping, skipping, jumping, wheeling, moving in a zigzag pattern. When you need to rest, walk or wheel slowly, then start moving faster again. Before you start, set a goal for yourself about how long you will try to move. How many breaks do you think you will need to take? What is realistic for you? What will help you achieve your goal?”

Students: “I am going to try to move for the next two songs, and I’ll only take one ‘slow down’ break. I love this music, so that will help me keep going.” “If I am tired, it helps me if someone encourages me.” “I like trying to beat my record.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="A3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate responsibility for their own safety and the safety of others as they participate in physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>A3.1 demonstrate behaviours and apply procedures that maximize their safety and that of others during physical activity (e.g., being aware of personal space, making sure their shoelaces are tied, warming up to prevent injury, taking turns when sharing equipment, avoiding overcrowding when using equipment both in class and on the playground, making sure straps are done up before pushing a wheelchair) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “You and your partner are each going to be given a beanbag, a pylon, and a plastic hoop to make up your own game. How will you make sure that both of you have a chance to play safely?” 

Student: “We will make sure that we have enough space around us so that we are not throwing near another group. We will take turns throwing.” 

Teacher prompt: “When you are skipping or hopping in the gym or classroom, what do you need to think about to move safely?”

Student: “I need to keep my head up and pay attention to the people and equipment around me so that I do not bump into anyone. I need to be able to stop in control when the teacher gives a signal.”
</specific>
          <specific>A3.2 identify ways of protecting themselves and others, including those with medical conditions, from safety risks while participating in physical activity (e.g., wearing a properly fitting helmet to protect the head, avoiding broken glass on the field or on the playground and reporting it to the teacher, carrying an epinephrine autoinjector if needed, reducing intensity of physical activity if poor air quality causes breathing difficulties, bringing an inhaler if needed, tucking in the tubing of an insulin therapy pump to prevent it from getting caught) [PS, CT] 

Teacher prompt: “Before we go outside to be active, what do you need to have with you to be safe?”

Students: “I need to have my puffer in my pocket in case I need it for my breathing.” “I need to have my medicine [epinephrine autoinjector] in my pouch in case I get stung by a bee.”</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Movement">
    <strand_text>Movement</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="B1">
        <overall_text>perform movement skills, demonstrating awareness of the basic requirements of the skills and applying movement concepts as appropriate, as they engage in a variety of physical activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B1.1 perform a variety of static balances with and without equipment (e.g., balance on the floor, on a line, on a bench; balance objects on different body parts), using different body parts at different levels and making different body shapes (e.g., low level - perform a V-sit: balance on buttocks with legs in the air, hold with muscles tight and legs together and arms either supporting the body or held at their sides; medium level - perform a standing scale: balance on one foot with the other leg stretched behind in the air, torso bent forward, and arms out parallel to the floor for balance; high level - perform a standing balance: using a walker for balance, lift one foot or one hand) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Create an interesting balance, with your weight on one or two feet. Now create a balance with one body part touching the floor and another on a bench. How did you change your balance - by shifting your weight, changing your body position, changing the body parts your weight was on, or by using another method?” 

Teacher prompt: “Show me three balances that you can hold steady for ten seconds without moving. Make one balance a low one close to the ground, one at a medium level, and one stretched to a high level. Now make three new balances at each level, using different body parts. What do you need to do to hold your body steady in each position?”

Student: “Squeezing my muscles tight, using bigger body parts, and keeping my eyes on one spot make it easier to balance. Balances where I have my arms and legs stretched out into a wide position are easier to hold steady than ones where I am balancing on one body part or in a narrow position. It is easier to balance in positions that are closer to the ground than ones where I am stretched up high.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.2 demonstrate the ability to jump, hop, and land safely and in control, taking off from one foot or from two feet [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “When you start a jump taking off from two feet, bend your knees and swing your arms forward to help push you forward and up. To land safely, think about putting your body into a position as if you were riding a bicycle. Keep your hands out, knees bent, and head up. While you land, think ‘toes-heels-kneesfreeze’, which means that as you land you should touch the ground with your toes first and then your heels, then bend your knees to absorb the impact, and finally ‘stick’ the landing by holding your position in control.” 

Teacher prompt: “When hopping on one foot, keep your head up and use your arms for balance. Practise hopping with each of your feet.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.3 perform a variety of locomotor movements with and without equipment, travelling in different directions and at different speeds, and using different pathways (e.g., hop sideways across a line, gallop in a curved pathway around trees or objects, skip quickly using a rope, slide or wheel slowly in a zigzag pattern, move at different speeds in response to the beat of a drum, run quickly following a curving pathway, jog slowly backwards while checking over their shoulder) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “In how many different ways can you travel along the lines of the gym? Can you skip? Run? Hop? Use tiny steps or giant steps? Wheel forward and backwards? Go slowly? Go quickly? Go sideways? Jump over lines that cross the one you are travelling on? Can you walk or wheel at different speeds while balancing a beanbag on your head? In how many ways can you move the ribbon as you skip around the gym?”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.4 send objects of different shapes and sizes at different levels and in different ways, using different body parts (e.g., slide a beanbag across the floor to a partner; throw a beanbag or ball underhand, using two hands or their dominant hand, and catch it or have a partner catch it; throw a disc through an upright hula hoop; kick a utility ball to a partner; strike a beach ball, using their hands, knees, chest, or foot ) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “Strike a ball with your hand so that your partner can catch it in the air. Now strike the ball with your hand so that it rolls along the ground to your partner. Now do the same using your feet. What do you do that is the same in all these cases? What changes when you send a different type of object?”

Student: “No matter how I send an object, it helps to face my partner and stretch my hand or foot towards my partner when I throw or kick, so that the object will travel in a straight line. That works for any kind of object, but bigger objects are easier to hit. Lighter objects move more slowly.”

Teacher: “What part of your foot should you use to contact the ball if you want to kick it along the ground?”

Student: “I should use the side of my foot, not my toe.”
</specific>
          <specific>B1.5 receive objects of different shapes and sizes at different levels and in various ways, using different body parts (e.g., stop a low bouncing ball with their hands or feet; catch or trap a beanbag that they or a partner toss, using two hands or their dominant hand) [PS, IS]

Teacher prompt: “In how many different ways can you stop a ball without using your hands? Can you stop it with your feet? Your thigh? Your chest? Your shin?” 

Teacher prompt: “What do you do to make it easier to catch the ball?”

Student: “I keep my eyes on the ball the whole time it is coming to me.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="B2">
        <overall_text>apply movement strategies appropriately, demonstrating an understanding of the components of a variety of physical activities, in order to enhance their ability to participate successfully in those activities</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>B2.1 demonstrate an understanding that different physical activities have different components (e.g., movement skills, basic rules and boundaries, conventions of fair play and etiquette), and apply this understanding as they participate in and explore a variety of individual and small-group activities [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some skills that you might use when you are playing ball with a partner? What do you need to do and watch for when you practise these skills? What changes in a bigger group?”

Student: “When I am playing with a ball with a partner, we can work on sending the ball in different ways - by kicking it, throwing it, striking it, or rolling it. We can also try to receive it in different ways - by catching it with our hands or stopping it with our feet. My partner and I need to stand close enough to each other that we can get the ball to each other. I need to make sure my partner sees that I am going to throw the ball before I throw it. We need to watch out for other pairs of students and make sure we don’t get too close to them. If I’m in a bigger group, we need to make sure that everyone gets to throw the ball sometimes and that we’re not too close together or too far apart.” 

Teacher prompt: “When you are sharing a scooter with your partner, how do you show that you are playing fair? What can you do to follow good playing etiquette?”

Student: “If we are sharing the scooter, we take turns so we both have about the same time with the scooter. When we are finished with the scooter, we show good etiquette by putting the scooter away where it belongs.”
</specific>
          <specific>B2.2 apply a variety of simple tactics to increase their chances of success during physical activities (e.g., wheel their wheelchair or run into open space when playing tag games in order to more easily avoid being tagged; choose an object for a throwing activity that they think they can successfully throw and catch multiple times - a cloth ball, a utility ball, a tennis ball, a beanbag; use adapted or specialized equipment, such as a ball with a bell inside that can provide an auditory cue) [PS, CT]* 

Teacher prompt: “When you choose an object to throw and catch, what do you think about to make a choice that is good for you?”

Students: “Catching is hard for me, so I picked a bigger ball.” “I picked a bouncy ball because I like running fast to get it if I drop it.” “I can’t see very well, so I chose a ball with a bell inside. Hearing the bell lets me know where the ball is.” “I use a walker and have a hard time moving around, so I picked a beanbag that won’t roll away if I drop it.” “I picked a stuffed animal to catch because it is fun, and I can practise with my own stuffed animals at home. It is also really easy to catch because it is soft.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Healthy Living">
    <strand_text>Healthy Living</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="C1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate an understanding of factors that contribute to healthy development</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C1.1 demonstrate an understanding of practices that enhance personal safety in the home (e.g., observing precautions for answering the phone and door, establishing home fire escape strategies, respecting electrical outlet covers, following precautions for preparing and storing foods, washing hands) and outdoors (e.g., using UV protection; observing safety rules when riding the bus, riding a bicycle, walking to school, approaching railway tracks and crossings; carrying medication for allergic reactions; being cautious when approaching animals) [PS] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some things you should do to stay safe when you are at home, outside, or riding on the school bus?”

Students: “At home, you should make sure that an adult always knows where you are when you’re playing outside. You should not touch any household product that has a symbol on it that means danger or poison. You should have a plan and know what to do in an emergency.” “When you’re outside, you should wear a hat to protect you from the sun and a helmet when you’re riding your bike.” “You should sit facing the front of the school bus, and always cross the road in front of the bus when you get off. Don’t get so close to the bus that you can touch it. Get help from the driver or another adult if you drop something in the ‘danger zone’ - the area around the bus where the driver can’t see you.” “If you have a nut allergy, tell your friends and their parents about it when you’re playing at their house. Make sure your snacks do not have nuts, and always carry an autoinjector.” “If you want to come up to an animal or touch it, you have to ask permission from an adult and learn how to do it safely.”</specific>
          <specific>C1.2 identify common food allergies and sensitivities (e.g., to peanuts, tree nuts, milk, eggs, fish) and the reactions they might cause (e.g., swelling, skin rash, difficulty breathing, abdominal cramps, vomiting, diarrhea, coma, death) 

Teacher prompt: “Anaphylaxis is a serious allergic reaction that can be life threatening. Food is the most common cause of anaphylaxis, but insect stings, medicine, latex, or exercise can also cause a reaction. What is the reason for our school policy that asks students not to bring nut products to school?”

Student: “A lot of people have allergies to nuts. If you have a nut allergy, you can have a very dangerous reaction if you eat or come into contact with nuts or something that is made with nuts.”
</specific>
          <specific>C1.3 describe the difference between prescription medicines and non-prescription medicines, giving examples of each, and identify rules for the proper use of all medicines 

Teacher prompt: “Prescription medicines, such as penicillin and other antibiotics, are prescribed by a doctor and are available only at a pharmacy. How can you recognize a prescription medicine?”

Student: “On the label of the bottle, it has the name of the patient, instructions for using the medicine, and a prescription number.”

Teacher: “How are commonly used non-prescription medicines and health care supplements - for example, cough syrup; vitamins; herbal, homeopathic, and naturopathic remedies; and First Nation, Métis, and Inuit traditional medicines - different from prescription medicines?”

Student: “You don’t need a prescription from a doctor to get them. You can get them in places like health food stores and not just in pharmacies. Traditional First Nation, Métis, and Inuit medicines are usually made from things like plants that grow in the forest.”

Teacher: “What should we do to ensure that medicines are used safely and correctly?”

Student: “You should only take medicine that an adult who is caring for you gives you. You should never share prescription medicines. All instructions, like how much you should take and when you should take it, for all medicines should be followed carefully.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C2">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to apply health knowledge and living skills to make reasoned decisions and take appropriate actions relating to their personal health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C2.1 use Canada’s Food Guide to assess the nutritional value of meals (e.g., in terms of food groups and number and size of servings), and identify food and beverage choices that enhance healthy growth and development 

Teacher prompt: “Here is a picture of a school lunch. What food groups do you see in this lunch? Is this a healthy lunch? What might make it healthier?”

Student: “A healthy lunch has foods from different parts of the food guide. This lunch has rice from the grain products group, a piece of chicken from the meat and alternatives group, and carrots from the vegetables and fruit group. There are cookies for dessert. This is a healthy lunch. If there were also a piece of fruit, or yogurt from the milk and alternatives group, it would be even healthier.”</specific>
          <specific>C2.2 demonstrate an understanding of how to make healthy food choices for meals and snacks, considering the factors they can and cannot control (e.g., the food that’s available in the home; the food that’s available when eating out; energy needed at different times of day; allergies; food guidelines associated with medical conditions such as diabetes or celiac disease; food safety related to food preparation, storage, handling, and cleanliness) [CT] 

Teacher prompt: “What are some things to consider when choosing a snack?”

Student: “A snack should give me energy and it should be safe and easy to eat. Snacks with less sugar - like fruit and vegetables - are better for my teeth. Also, some foods need to be kept cold to be safe to eat.”

Teacher: “What can you do if you are going to be somewhere where there are only a few healthy choices or none at all?”

Student: “I should try to make the healthiest choice I can, like having a salad instead of fries at a fast-food restaurant. Or I can go ahead and eat what is available, as long as I don’t do it regularly or too often. If I’m not too hungry, I can wait to eat something healthier later. I can try to bring a healthy snack from home next time, or if my school has a healthy snack program, I can have a snack at school.”
</specific>
          <specific>C2.3 explain the importance of standing up for themselves, and demonstrate the ability to apply behaviours that enhance their personal safety in threatening situations (e.g., speaking confidently; stating boundaries; saying no; reporting exploitive behaviours, such as improper touching of their bodies or others’ bodies) [PS, IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What can standing up for yourself look like?”

Student: “You can hold your head up high, make eye contact, and speak strongly.”

Teacher: “In some cultures, making eye contact is considered disrespectful. What can you do then?”

Student: “You can stand up for yourself in other ways, by saying no in a polite but firm way, and not doing anything that makes you uncomfortable. You can also try to stay away from people or places where there may be trouble.”

Teacher: “Why is standing up for yourself important in a friendship?”

Student: “It helps you when you can say what you think or what you need. Friends should listen to each other and show respect. For example, if someone teases me about my allergy to nuts, I can tell them to stop and let them know that contact with nuts could make me stop breathing.”

Teacher: “If someone does something that you do not like, touches you in an inappropriate way, or asks to touch you in a way that makes you feel uncomfortable or confused, how can you stand up for yourself?”

Student: “I can say no and move away. My body is mine. I can tell someone - like a parent, a teacher, an elder, a doctor - that I need help. I can keep telling until I get help.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
      <overall id="C3">
        <overall_text>demonstrate the ability to make connections that relate to health and well-being - how their choices and behaviours affect both themselves and others, and how factors in the world around them affect their own and others’ health and well-being</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>C3.1 describe how to relate positively to others (e.g., cooperate, show respect, smile, manage anger), and describe behaviours that can be harmful in relating to others (e.g., verbal abuse, including name calling, insults, and mocking; deliberately ignoring someone; physical violence, including pushing, kicking, and hitting) [IS] 

Teacher prompt: “What does being a good friend look like? How can you show that you’re a friend while working in groups?”

Student: “I can make sure to include everyone, be nice to anyone who wants to be my partner, share toys and equipment, be encouraging, keep my hands to myself, and speak nicely.”

Teacher: “Calling someone a name or leaving them out of a group because of how they learn, speak, or look are examples of abusing or mistreating someone with your words or behaviour. What could you do if you saw someone doing something like this?”

Student: “I could tell the person to stop, or get help from an adult, or be friendly to the person who is being treated badly.” 

Teacher prompt: “Getting help for someone or telling can be a positive or helpful thing. Tattling on someone can be harmful. What is the difference between telling and tattling?”

Student: “When you tattle, you are telling to get someone into trouble. When you are telling, you are telling to get someone out of trouble.”
</specific>
          <specific>C3.2 describe methods that may be used instead of or in combination with medication to maintain good health and prevent or treat various health problems (e.g., getting more sleep to help get rid of a cold; getting more fresh air and physical activity to relieve headaches; eating healthier meals as recommended in Canada’s Food Guide; using natural healing practices) [CT]
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
  <strand id="Living Skills">
    <strand_text>Living Skills</strand_text>
    <overalls>
      <overall id="1">
        <overall_text>demonstrate personal and interpersonal skills and the use of critical and creative thinking processes as they acquire knowledge and skills in connection with the expectations in the Active Living, Movement Competence, and Healthy Living strands for this grade</overall_text>
        <specifics>
          <specific>1.1 use self-awareness and self-monitoring skills to help them understand their strengths and needs, take responsibility for their actions, recognize sources of stress, and monitor their own progress, as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: monitor their body’s response to physical activity; Movement Competence: after jumping, consider what they did well as they tried to land in a stable position, and what they could do better; Healthy Living: complete a checklist to monitor their daily care of their teeth) 

Student: “I know I might be moving too fast if I’m breathing so hard that I can’t talk.”</specific>
          <specific>1.2 use adaptive, management, and coping skills to help them respond to the various challenges they encounter as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: dress appropriately for outdoor activity; Movement Competence: describe the value of experimenting when trying new activities; Healthy Living: in response to teasing, try different solutions - walking away, telling the person to stop, telling the person how the teasing makes them feel, getting help) 

Student: “When I’m learning something new and I can’t do it right away, if I keep trying, I always get better. Not doing it perfectly helps me learn what not to do. If I throw a ball and it goes way too far, I know I need to throw a little softer.”

* The abbreviation(s) for the three categories of living skills - PS, IS, and CT - appear in square brackets at the end of expectations, in strands A-C, to which those skills are clearly connected. (See pp. 18-21 for a discussion of living skills.)</specific>
          <specific>1.3 communicate effectively, using verbal or non-verbal means, as appropriate, and interpret information accurately as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living (e.g., Active Living: to understand instructions properly, stop and look at the teacher when instructions are being given; Movement Competence: copy a partner’s movements in a mirroring activity while standing face to face by following non-verbal signals and body language that indicate the movements; Healthy Living: effectively communicate their objections or refusal to participate if someone is doing something that they do not like)
</specific>
          <specific>1.4 apply relationship and social skills as they participate in physical activities, develop movement competence, and acquire knowledge and skills related to healthy living to help them interact positively with others, build healthy relationships, and become effective team members (e.g., Active Living: demonstrate how they can help one another while using equipment; Movement Competence: work cooperatively with a partner when throwing and catching balls and other objects of varying sizes; Healthy Living: use positive language when talking to peers, as part of developing good relationships, and encourage others to do the same) 

Students: “If someone’s ball rolls into my space when I am playing, I stop and give it back.” “If my partner is learning to catch, we will start by choosing a bigger ball or an object with soft edges to make it a little easier.” “I don’t call anyone names, because that can hurt as much as hitting them.”
</specific>
          <specific>1.5 use a range of critical and creative thinking skills and processes to assist them in making connections, planning and setting goals, analysing and solving problems, making decisions, and evaluating their choices in connection with learning in health and physical education (e.g., Active Living: explain how participating in moderate to vigorous activity is connected to better fitness and better health; describe what is needed to play safely and comfortably outside in different kinds of weather; Movement Competence: explore the use of many pieces of equipment and explain how each is different and why they prefer one over another; Healthy Living: explain how to stay safe by identifying household products that might be dangerous) 

Student: “I like using the mitt that the ball sticks to better than the scoop, because the mitt makes it easier to catch the ball. The ball sometimes bounces out of the scoop.”
</specific>
        </specifics>
      </overall>
    </overalls>
  </strand>
</curriculum>