<curriculum>
<pdf>https://www.edonline.sk.ca/bbcswebdav/xid-181832_1</pdf>
  <outcomes>
    <goal_section collapsable="true">
      <goal_heading>Communication Media 20</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 2B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Discuss and reflect on the need for societal standards (e.g., legal, ethical, and community norms, and values) and cultural sensitivity in media.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Formulate a list of societal standards in relation to issues including sexism, racism, and homophobia and support the list with positive media examples.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compose a strategy for inclusion of appropriate language, content, and images reflective of societal standards in personal, class, and school projects and assignments.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and discuss various rating systems for media such as television, movies, and games.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and discuss some issues regarding posting of images on the web including safety, possible consequences, and permanence of web postings.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 6B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Develop, refine, and appraise personal skills and understandings acquired in Module 6A while experimenting with postproduction activities.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Refine storyboarding techniques used in Module 5 to plan shots for video to include transition techniques.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Correctly apply common industry terminology such as fade in, fade out, action safe, title safe, reverse angle, voice over, cut to, and over the shoulder.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Critique the composition of some sample videos looking for examples of techniques that add interest to shots such as adding depth, and the rule of thirds.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Frame faces to create interest for the viewer by applying the rule of thirds, using correct headroom and nose room.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with motivated lighting effects to gain an understanding of how light is used effectively.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Discuss and demonstrate the differences between transitional devices such as dissolves and cuts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate increasing skill in editing by completing various shot-to-shot transitions such as an entrance cut, an exit cut, and an action cut.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a personal assessment of acquired skills and understandings to share with the instructor.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 7B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Refine and assess audio production skills based on accepted practices related to recording concepts, processes, and equipment selection.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop increasing sensitivity regarding audio quality including concepts such as perspective, continuity, and presence.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop digital work station skills in audio mixing and editing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Critique personal recordings within a group context to give and receive constructive feedback from self and peers.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a personal assessment of acquired skills and understandings to discuss with the instructor.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 8B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Create and assess interactive media using multiple platforms.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use a variety of effective planning techniques to create a media project complete with a management plan.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Collaborate on creation of a unique messaging project involving more than one media format.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Employ software to increase personal skills and abilities to communicate effectively.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a self-assessment of acquired skills based on given criteria.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 9B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Create a project displaying increasing complexity and sophistication based on an individual or group vision to communicate with society at large.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop increasing skill using more advanced techniques (e.g., video mixing, audio mixing, creating titles) along with previously acquired skills.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop assessment criteria for the project (e.g., rubric) in consultation with the teacher.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Participate in the planning of a public or invitational exhibition of class projects.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 10</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Research innovative ideas in technology and media and share their potential to influence our lives.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Argue either for or against a statement such as, “Individuals must accept ongoing independent research into innovation as part of one’s professional responsibility” by reflecting on and expressing personal opinions with one’s own justification about the issues involving technological change.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Examine and evaluate websites or other resources that demonstrate new conceptions and techniques in communication media.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Share personal research (e.g., blog, presentation).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 11</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Create an assessment of the effectiveness of a production based on the message, the intended audience, and the chosen medium.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explore and interpret the interrelationship between the message, the audience, and the medium.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a rubric using agreed-upon effectiveness criteria and use it to assess a production.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Choose a professional production and critique its success in terms of effectiveness of reaching its target audience.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 14</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Evaluate and draw conclusions about using animation as an effective means of enhancing communication to a target audience.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Reflect on the purposes and advantages of using animation rather than live action.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a project or portion of a personal or group project using animation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>View and analyze animation styles and techniques and share insights with peers.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 16A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Recognize how school-based skills development will be used to meet workplace expectations.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: Work Study is used to prepare students for employment through specific skill development within a workplace. The number of work study opportunities is equal to the number of courses available in the curriculum area at the 20 and 30 level.</outcome_note>
        <outcome_note>Note: For more information about implementing work study in schools, see the Work Study Guidelines for the Practical and Applied Arts included in the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook. The training plan for the student should be designed to relate to the outcomes of the course modules chosen in collaboration with the cooperating employer.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Obtain a list of roles and responsibilities of the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Brainstorm a list of factors which may affect workplace performance.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Discuss effective and positive verbal and non-verbal communication in the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop a résumé which can be forwarded to a potential employer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Practise effective interview techniques based on established guidelines (e.g., the greeting, the exchange, and the parting).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 17A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Gain experience in the world of work in the communication media industry to make more informed choices about careers by expanding the career research and exploration beyond the classroom.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: For more information about implementing work study in schools, see the Work Study Guidelines for the Practical and Applied Arts included in the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook. The training plan for the student should be designed to relate to the outcomes of the course modules chosen in collaboration with the cooperating employer.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop an awareness of career opportunities in Saskatchewan and beyond.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Gain an opportunity for the development of entry level workplace skills that may lead to sustainable employment in the communication media industry.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Establish standards of work performance acceptable to the student and employer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and report on essential skills and employability skills as they relate to a work environment.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 18A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Reflect and report on the work experience including but not limited to hours of work, personal relationships, employer expectations, evaluation criteria, and overall personal performance.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Design and participate in an exit interview with the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present a report on the work study experience including aspects such as: expected hours of workdress codejob descriptionemployer expectationsemployer evaluation processabsent and late policiespersonal relationshipsproblem solvingcommunication.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 99B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">The extended study module is designed to provide schools and teachers with an opportunity to meet current and future demands not provided for in current modules in the PAA curriculum.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: The extended study module may be used only once in each 100 hour course. In the Student Data System, record 99A for the first extended study module offered in the course series, and, if needed, 99B for the second and 99C for the third.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Module Overview:Evolving societal and personal needs, advances in technology, and demands to solve current problems require a flexible curriculum that can accommodate new ways and means to support learning in the future. The extended study module is designed to provide schools and teachers with an opportunity to meet current and future demands not provided for in current modules in the PAA curriculum. This flexibility allows a school or teacher to design one new module per credit to complement or extend the study of the core and optional modules to meet the specific needs of students or the community. The extended study module is designed to extend the content of the pure courses and to offer survey course modules beyond the scope of the available selection of PAA modules. The list of possibilities for topics of study or projects for the extended study module approach is as varied as the imagination of those involved in using the module. The optional extended study module guidelines should be used to strengthen the knowledge, skills, and processes advocated in the PAA curriculum. For more information on the guidelines for the Extended Study module, see the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
  </outcomes>
</curriculum>