<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
<pdf>https://www.edonline.sk.ca/webapps/moe-curriculum-BBLEARN/index.jsp</pdf>
  <outcomes>
    <goal_section collapsable="true">
      <goal_heading>ELA A30 - Canadian Voices (First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts only)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR A 30.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>View, listen to, read, comprehend, and respond to a variety of grade-appropriate First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts that address:identity (e.g., Define the Individual, Negotiate the Community)social responsibility (e.g., Shift Centres, Blur Margins), andsocial action (agency) (e.g., Understand Beliefs, Initiate Action).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explore topics and contemporary and traditional visual, oral, multimedia (including digital) and written First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts that present different viewpoints and perspectives including those that reflect the diversity of Canada and its citizens’ diverse personal identities, worldviews, and backgrounds (e.g., community, culture, values, spirituality, socio-economic status, language, ability, age, gender, appearance).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze and respond to a variety of First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts representative of various time periods and of the diverse cultures and regions of Canada in order to extend understanding of the ideas, themes, and issues explored in the texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts to identify particular perspectives presented, and the forms and stylistic means used to communicate those perspectives.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze how historical, regional, cultural, political, and social contexts and events influence the presentation and interpretation of ideas, issues, and themes in First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify connections between personal experiences and prior knowledge of language and texts to develop interpretations of a variety of First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Respond personally and critically to perspectives and styles of a variety of First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts and explain how the study of those texts enhances understanding of self, others, and Canadian identity.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze ways in which language and texts reflect and influence the values and behaviours of people and diverse communities.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify the various elements of style used in First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts, and explain how the elements help communicate meaning and enhance the effectiveness of the texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explain how First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian texts raise awareness about a variety of regional issues, ideas, cultures, events, and people, and promote social and personal change.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR A 30.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>View and evaluate critically information and ideas obtained from First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian visual and multimedia texts including an advertisement, news broadcast, poster, and film.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>View and respond to grade-appropriate visual and multimedia texts created by First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian artists and authors from various cultural communities.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select deliberately and use effectively a variety of before (page 27), during (page 28), and after (page 29) strategies to construct and confirm meaning when viewing texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language cues and conventions (page 24) of a variety of informational and literary texts to construct and confirm meaning when viewing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate critical viewing behaviours:Determine what the text is representingIdentify and analyze how the text was constructedIdentify the purposes, intended audiences, messages, points of view, and techniques of the textInfer the assumptions, interests, beliefs, and values embedded in the text, and the credibility and purpose of the authorIdentify and analyze speaker’s, artist’s, or author’s tone, attitude, and biasAnalyze how the text uses argument, images, placement, editing, and/or music for effect and impactEvaluate and critique the persuasive techniques including emotion and propaganda.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate critically information (i.e., whose voice is heard, whose is not) obtained from viewing a visual or multimedia text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explain and evaluate the effectiveness of persuasive strategies and techniques in a range of visual and multimedia texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Infer point of view and biases explicit in visual and multimedia texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze, compare, and critique different visual and multimedia presentations of the same ideas, information, or issues.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess the accuracy and balance of information presented in visual and multimedia texts.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR A 30.3</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Listen to, comprehend, and develop coherent and plausible interpretations of grade-appropriate literary and informational texts created by First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian speakers and authors from various communities.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Listen to, respond to, and interpret oral texts created by First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian speakers and authors from various cultural communities.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select deliberately and use effectively a variety of before (page 27), during (page 28), and after (page 29) strategies to construct and confirm meaning when listening to texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language cues and conventions (page 24) of a variety of informational and literary texts to construct and confirm meaning when listening.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate critical listening behaviours:Concentrate, focus, and attendFilter distractions and recognize factors that interfere with effective listening, including personal biasesIdentify the thesis of a speech and determine the essential elements that develop the thesisRecognize speaker’s values, perspective, biases, and toneAnalyze explicit and implicit messages/concepts, viewpoints, theme, and toneRecognize overall plan or organization including transitional expressionsDistinguish between emotional appeal and reasoned argumentEvaluate and verify facts and argumentsIdentify logical fallacies in oral argumentsIdentify key allusions and symbolsUse effective note making strategies and a variety of written or graphic forms to organize and share ideas acquired from what was listened toPrepare and ask relevant questions, and respond appropriatelyAnalyze the overall effectiveness of the presentation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Outline and summarize an oral presentation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate proficiency in reflective, critical, empathetic, and appreciative listening.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compare and contrast interpretations of oral texts with the interpretations of others and research points of contention.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Provide appropriate feedback in a variety of situations including discussions and informative, persuasive, and artistic presentations.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR A 30.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Read, demonstrate comprehension of, and apply knowledge from grade-appropriate informational (including editorials, reviews, and articles) and literary (including fiction, script, poetry, and non-fiction) texts from First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian authors as a basis for understanding self and the multiplicity of voices and perspectives that make up Canadian culture.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read, comprehend, and respond to informational and literary texts by First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, and Canadian authors, and explain how the texts represent our Canadian literary and cultural heritage.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select deliberately and use effectively a variety of before (page 28), during (page 29), and after (page 30) strategies to construct and confirm meaning when reading texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language cues and conventions (page 24) of a variety of informational and literary texts to construct and confirm meaning when reading.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate critical reading behaviours to analyze meanings, ideas, language, and literary quality in a range of contemporary and historical texts: Establish a purpose for reading such as to learn, interpret, andenjoySkim, scan, and read closelyIdentify and analyze explicit and implicit messages, viewpoints, and conceptsAnalyze the ways in which a text’s organizational structure and elements support or confound its purposeRelate understanding of a range of texts to personal experience, purposes, audience, and other textsEvaluate accuracy (e.g., differentiate fact from opinion), credibility, logic, and usefulness of ideas and information presentedDifferentiate between literal and figurative statementsRecognize and comprehend symbols and allusionsTest ideas and values presented in textsUse note making and outlining to enhance understanding of texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recognize and evaluate major literary forms and techniques and how the forms are shaped into an artistic unit.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify the elements of the authors’ styles and the methods by which they are achieved.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Paraphrase the main ideas, events, or themes in a variety of sophisticated literary and informational texts, along with supportive evidence.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop coherent and plausible interpretations of a variety of sophisticated print texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Support a position, interpretation, or response by citing specific details, features, and ideas from what was read.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate an appreciation of the power and beauty of language, past and present, in print texts.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC A 30.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create a range of visual, multimedia, oral, and written texts that explore:identity (e.g., Define the Individual, Negotiate the Community),social responsibility (e.g., Shift Centres, Blur Margins), andsocial action (agency) (e.g., Understand Beliefs, Initiate Action).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a range of visual, oral, multimedia, and written texts that include the following:A clear thesis or main ideaDetails that logically and effectively support the thesis or main ideaStyle, voice, format, and organizational pattern appropriate to purpose and audienceUnity, coherence, and emphasisA plausible and effective conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop independently an inquiry project relating to a particular topic or issue with reference to purpose and audience and employing a variety of research tools and resources:Consider own and others’ expertise to explore breadth and depth of knowledge and focus inquiry or research based on parameters of taskFormulate inquiry or research questions, and refine them through reflection and discussion of topic, purpose, and contextConsider whether thesis claim is personally relevant, interesting, and meaningful; relevant and meaningful to the audience; aligned with purpose and goals; logical; and can be supportedDevelop and select from a repertoire of inquiry strategies, and adjust plan according to needs (audience, purpose, context)Evaluate and select ideas and information from prior knowledge of inquiry or research topic appropriate for audience, purpose, and perspective or focusUse a variety of digital and informational resources (e.g., human, libraries, databases, networks, video) to gather, evaluate, and synthesize information and perspectives to create and communicate knowledge to achieve purpose and suit audienceEvaluate factors that affect the credibility, authenticity, accuracy, and bias of information sourcesEvaluate information for completeness, accuracy, currency, historical context, relevance, balance of perspectives, and biasOrganize and reorganize information and ideas to clarify thinking and to achieve desired effectIncorporate, strategically, source material in a variety of ways including directly quoting, paraphrasing, summarizing, and using ellipses and brackets, and document sources accurately.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC A 30.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create and present visual and multimedia representations including using photographs to explain a range of contemporary course-related perspectives or landscapes.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present visual and multimedia presentations:Exhibit logical structures appropriate to audience, purpose, and contextDevelop a central focus and craft strong messagesOrganize ideas in logical and appropriate sequencesInclude smooth transitionsUse a variety of forms and technologies such as sound, photographs, and modelsUnderstand how ideas are communicated through elements of design such as colour, shape, line, and textureProvide logical and convincing conclusions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate deliberately a wide variety of before, during, and after strategies to communicate meaning when representing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply accurately and effectively the language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when representing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare a visual or multimedia presentation on a contemporary Canadian landscape or perspective:Develop a presentation that is appropriate to the subject, audience, and purpose, including informing, persuading, and entertainingFocus on main points of presentation and include only details that strongly support main pointsUse question, fact, anecdote, or visual aids to get audience’s attentionSequence visuals in best possible order and support them with sound, maps, charts, objects, or other visual and auditory aidsConclude by restating main points in a memorable wayUse posture, gestures, and facial expressions to send the same message as visuals and words.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Communicate thoughts, ideas, and feelings using two or more media.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Present information on a topic in a planned and focused group session using a variety of audio-visual aids.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use a variety of technologies to facilitate and enhance representation including computer software and multimedia technology.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Describe and evaluate alternative approaches to presentations for specific audiences and purposes.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with a variety of text forms (e.g., video documentary) and techniques (e.g., dissolve, fade).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC A 30.3</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Present and express a range of ideas and information in formal (including a panel presentation and a business or community meeting) and informal (including discussions and collaborative work) situations for differing audiences and purposes.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Function both as a group member and a group leader and demonstrate effective group interaction skills and strategies:Demonstrate commitment and flexibility in a group and to the team’s and project’s goalsMonitor own and others’ contributionsBuild on others’ strengths to achieve group goals by collaborating and consulting effectively with others in completing communications tasksAssume responsibility for roles in teamsRepresent and promote respect for contributions of other team membersApply a variety of strategies including formal decision-making techniques and consensus-building skills to solve problems and achieve group goals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate deliberately a wide variety of before, during, and after strategies to communicate meaning when speaking.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply accurately and effectively the language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when speaking.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create and present oral presentations:Employ and exhibit a logical structure appropriate to the context, audience, and purposeGroup related ideas and maintain a consistent focusInclude smooth transitionsSupport judgements with sound evidence and well-chosen detailsMake skillful use of rhetorical devicesProvide coherent conclusionsEmploy appropriate eye contact, speaking rate, volume, enunciation, inflection, and gestures to communicate ideas.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and participate in a panel presentation (findings from an inquiry) (e.g., dialects in Canada): Determine what a knowledgeable, skilled individual or expert might knowOrganize group effectivelyGive an effective introduction (chairperson or moderator introduce the topic, the members of the panel, the aspect of the topic each panel member will address, and the overall thesis of the panel presentation)Present, as a panelist, own section in a clear and logical manner by defining or explaining necessary terms, presenting ideas in logical order, and using and explaining examplesConnect different sectionsShow thorough knowledge of topicPresent an effective conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Attend a formal meeting, note aspects of formal procedure, organize, and participate in a business or community meeting:Practise the rules and procedures that govern business or community meetingsPresent purpose of meeting clearly, and as an individual member present one part of the background analysis of a problem (e.g., history of problem, effects of problem, causes of problem, importance of problem, evolution of problem)Prepare an agenda that lists the order of business (e.g., call to order, minutes of previous meeting, discussion on unfinished business, reports, new business, adjournment)Present one part of the background analysis and bring ideas and voices to the discussion as well as own solution to the group problemParticipate in bringing items forward for discussion and decision (carried, defeated, tabled)Follow formal procedures (e.g., Robert’s Rules of Order) and acknowledge role of chairperson (leads meeting, sees that everyone has an opportunity to speak , takes the votes, and ensures that minutes are recorded).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate a willingness to explore diverse perspectives to develop and modify viewpoints.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess the value, limitations, and ethical issues associated with collaborative work.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Interact purposefully, confidently, and ethically in a variety of interpersonal and electronic school and community contexts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recognize and adjust oral presentation elements effectively (i.e., articulation, pronunciation, volume, tempo, pitch, stress, gestures, eye contact, facial expression, and poise) in keeping with purpose, audience needs, and individual cultural and linguistic background.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC A 30.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create a variety of informational (including an inquiry/research paper and an editorial) and literary (including a real or invented narrative and a literary criticism essay) texts that are appropriate to a variety of audiences and purposes including informing, persuading, and entertaining.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a variety of written communications using various elements of discourse (e.g., purpose, speaker, audience, form), in narrative, expository, persuasive, informative, and/or descriptive texts: Choose focus to address audience needs, stated purpose, and contextDevelop a thesis statementCreate an organizing structure appropriate to purpose, audience, and contextInclude relevant information and exclude extraneous informationProvide facts and details, describe or analyze subject, explain benefits or limitations, compare or contrast, or provide graphics or illustrationsClarify and defend positions with relevant evidence, including facts, expert opinions, quotations, and/or expressions of commonly accepted beliefs and logical reasoningUse a variety of rhetorical devices to support assertions (e.g., appeal to logic through reasoning, case study, and analogy)Anticipate potential misunderstandings, problems, or mistakes that might arise for audienceUse appropriate format and structure drafts using standard forms and predictable structures such as headings, white space, and graphicsProvide a coherent conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate deliberately a wide variety of before (page 31), during (page 32), and after (page 33) strategies to communicate meaning when writing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply accurately and effectively the language cues and conventions (page 24) to construct and communicate meaning when writing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and write an inquiry/research paper (approximately 1,500 words in length, 5-6 pages typed, double-spaced):Focus on an important topic that interests self and emphasizes a specific part about the topicSize up the topic and include important details, facts, ideas, quotations, statistics, and other dataUse primary and secondary sources that have been judged for their accuracy, completeness, currency, and biasesCite sources and avoid plagiarismIntroduce the topic, get the reader’s attention, and present the thesis statementExplain why the topic is importantArrange ideas so the reader can followInclude sources and a works-cited page and title pageConclude in a logical and interesting way, leaving the reader with something to think about.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write an editorial:Focus on a current issue or topicIdentify the purpose (e.g., criticize, condemn, advise, commend, congratulate)Develop a thesis statement that clearly defines the issue and attends to the purposeConduct research to collect evidence and to provide examplesCraft an introduction that states the writer’s view and captures the audience’s attentionUse evidence and ethical, logical arguments to support the thesis statement and purpose, and to persuade the audienceConstruct an effective conclusion related to the purpose and thesis statement.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a real or invented narrative: Introduce the character(s), the setting, and the conflict in the beginningBuild suspense through the rising action to a high or turning pointResolve the conflict and create a satisfactory or reasonable conclusion in the endingFocus on what character(s) does, and “show” what the person does (instead of “tell”) and how he or she does itShow character through dialogue, thoughts, and actionUse external and internal dialogueUse action verbs.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a literary analysis and critical evaluation (print, film, new media) essay: Read to find out what the author said, how the writer was affected, what important issues the text made the writer think about, and what was enjoyed about itRead the text again to analyze how the author achieved these effects (what forms and techniques were used) and how successful the text wasRespond to key questions (e.g., What was the author’s purpose? How was it achieved? What were your reactions?)Use the text as evidence.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with and explore a variety of written text forms (e.g., chapter of a novel, short story, minutes of a meeting) and techniques (such as satire, tone, mood) and explain their appeal.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR A 30.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Assess own work for precision, clarity, and artistry.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Review and analyze own work (e.g., for content, organization, delivery, audience response, style).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify a variety of skills and strategies in viewing, listening, reading, representing, speaking, writing; and explain how the skills and strategies improve communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify appropriate steps to take to improve comprehension and communication skills.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a variety of products that most clearly reflect own growth and competencies as a communicator, and explain the reasons for the choices.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess the effect of new understandings and strategies on self and others.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR A 30.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Reflect on personal growth and successes in language learning and consider the role and importance of language learning when developing personal goals and plans as a self-directed, curious, self-appraising, and open-minded learner.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Review and analyze own work (e.g., for content, organization, delivery, audience response, style).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify a variety of skills and strategies in viewing, listening, reading, representing, speaking, writing; and explain how the skills and strategies improve communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify appropriate steps to take to improve comprehension and communication skills.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a variety of products that most clearly reflect own growth and competencies as a communicator, and explain the reasons for the choices.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess the effect of new understandings and strategies on self and others.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
    <goal_section collapsable="true">
      <goal_heading>ELA B30 - Global Perspectives (international, including indigenous, texts only)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR B 30.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>View, listen to, read, comprehend, and respond to a variety of grade-appropriate international, including indigenous, texts that address:identity (e.g., Sense of Self)social responsibility (e.g., Social Criticism), andsocial action (agency) (e.g., Addressing the Issues).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explore topics and contemporary and traditional visual, oral, written, and multimedia (including digital) texts that present different viewpoints and perspectives on issues related to identity, diverse personal identities, worldviews, and backgrounds (e.g., culture, socio-economic status, ability, age, gender, language).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>View, listen to, read, and respond to a variety of historical and contemporary literary and informational (including business and technological communication) texts by authors from a variety of cultures, backgrounds, and time periods.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Make connections between the ideas in texts and personal knowledge, experiences, and insights; between other texts; and between texts and the world.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Consider how historical, cultural, political, and social contexts influence the presentation of ideas, themes, and issues in texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze texts in terms of messages, ideas, information, universal questions, themes, and issues; provide evidence from the texts to support analysis.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explain how informational and literary texts contribute to an understanding of human nature and of self, and raise awareness about a range of topics, ideas, cultures, events, people, and issues.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify ways in which informational and literary texts might promote social and personal change.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate appreciation for a variety of texts.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR B 30.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>View, comprehend, and evaluate critically a variety of visual and multimedia texts by international, including indigenous, artists and authors from various cultural communities, and identify how the texts address beliefs, values, and power.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>View, respond to, and interpret visual and multimedia texts created by artists and authors from various cultural communities including indigenous peoples.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select deliberately and use effectively a variety of before (page 27), during (page 28), and after (page 29) strategies to construct and confirm meaning when viewing texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language cues and conventions (page 25) from a variety of informational and literary texts to construct and confirm meaning when viewing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate critical viewing behaviours to evaluate how effectively information, ideas, issues, and opinions are communicated in visual and multimedia texts and whether the texts achieve their intended purpose:Determine what the text is representingIdentify and analyze how the text was constructedIdentify and analyze the artist’s/author’s intentIdentify the intended audiences and points of view in the textDetermine the historical context of the text and its impact on the textIdentify and explain the overt and implied messages conveyedInfer the assumptions, interests, beliefs, and values embedded in the text and the credibility and purpose of the authorIdentify and analyze artist’s/author’s tone, attitude, and biasAnalyze how the text uses argument, images, placement, and/or music for effect and impactEvaluate and critique the persuasive techniques including emotion and propaganda.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explain how visual and multimedia texts are created to suit particular purposes and audiences.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explain why the same visual or multimedia texts might prompt different responses from different audiences.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify characteristics, conventions, and/or techniques used in a variety of media forms, and explain how they shape content, convey meaning, and influence their audience(s).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify the perspectives and/or biases evident in visual and multimedia texts and comment on questions the texts may raise about beliefs, values, and power.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify the aesthetic effects of media presentations and evaluate the techniques used to create them.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR B 30.3</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Listen to and comprehend grade-appropriate informational and literary texts created by international, including indigenous, speakers and authors, and analyze the perspectives, biases, beliefs, values, identities, and power presented in each text.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Listen to and develop interpretations of oral and multimedia texts created by international speakers and authors from various cultural communities.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select deliberately and use effectively a variety of before, during, and after strategies to construct and confirm meaning when listening to texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language cues and conventions of a variety of informational and literary texts to construct and confirm meaning when listening.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Adopt and demonstrate critical listening behaviours to analyze the overall effectiveness of oral presentations: Focus attention on the speaker’s messageFilter distractions and recognize factors that interfere with effective listening, including personal biasesIdentify the thesis of a speech and determine the essential elements that support itAnalyze explicit and implicit messages/concepts, viewpoints, values, theme, and toneRecognize overall plan or organization including transitional expressionsDistinguish between emotional appeal and reasoned argumentEvaluate and verify facts and arguments, and identify fallacies in oral argumentsIdentify key allusions and symbolsUse effective note making strategies and a variety of written or graphic forms to organize and share ideas acquired from what was listened toIdentify and analyze the effect of artistic elements (e.g., imagery, language, character development) within texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify the purpose of a variety of listening tasks and set goals for specific tasks (e.g., comprehension, collaboration, facilitation, persuasion, mediation, empathy, evaluation).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use evidence from the texts to support interpretations.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and analyze the perspectives and/or biases evident in oral texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Listen to, discuss, interpret, and evaluate spoken texts in terms of their structure and their social, cultural, political, and historical contexts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze historically significant speeches (e.g., Gettysburg Address, Mandela’s Hope and Glory, Churchill’s speeches) to find rhetorical devices and features that make them memorable.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Describe and analyze potential sources of bias in oral presentations including those that attempt to persuade.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR B 30.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Read and demonstrate comprehension of a range of contemporary and classical grade-appropriate informational (including position papers, magazine and newspaper articles, and electronic communications) and literary (including drama, novels, poetry, short stories, essays, biographies, and autobiographies) texts from various international, including indigenous, cultures and analyze the philosophical, ethical, and social influences that have shaped information, issues, characters, plots, and themes.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read and interpret a range of literary and informational texts written by international authors including indigenous authors.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select deliberately and use effectively a variety of before, during, and after strategies to construct and confirm meaning when reading texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language cues and conventions of a variety of informational and literary texts to construct and confirm meaning when reading.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate critical reading behaviours to analyze meanings, ideas, language, and literary quality in a range of contemporary and historical texts: Establish a purpose for reading such as to learn, interpret, and enjoySkim, scan, and read closelyIdentify the main ideas and supporting details of informational textsIdentify and analyze explicit and implicit messages, viewpoints, and conceptsAnalyze the ways in which a text’s organizational structure and elements support or confound its purposeIdentify and analyze persuasive techniquesEvaluate the accuracy (e.g., differentiate fact from opinion) and usefulness of information presentedDifferentiate between literal and figurative statements and recognize satire, parody, and ironyInterpret allusions and symbols and symbolic patterns in literary textsTest ideas and values.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use knowledge from texts as a basis to understanding self and society by using literary texts for understanding individual and social issues.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read historical and contemporary literary and informational texts to understand, appreciate, and respond to international and global perspectives.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Contrast major text forms and characteristics of major literary periods in world history.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Interpret, evaluate, and discuss a range of texts, identifying their language and literary qualities and considering the personal, social, cultural, political, and historical contexts in which the texts were created.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read silently with comprehension for a sustained period of time.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use note making and outlining to better understand texts.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B 30.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create a range of visual, multimedia, oral, and written texts that explore:identity (e.g., Sense of Self)social responsibility (e.g., Social Criticism), andsocial action (agency) (e.g., Addressing the Issues).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop and articulate defensible positions on individual, community, national, and world issues.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate originality and inventiveness in work.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Critique the effectiveness of a piece of satire as a commentary on current events.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use spoken, written, and other forms of representing to achieve specific purposes (e.g., for learning, enjoyment, persuasion, and the exchange of information).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Research a global social issue and develop a problem scenario and position paper to teach others about this issue: Consider own and others’ expertise and knowledge to explore breadth and depth of knowledge and focus inquiry or research based on parameters of taskFormulate inquiry or research questions and refine them through reflection and discussion of topic, purpose, and contextDevelop and select from a repertoire of inquiry strategies, and adjust plan according to needs (audience, purpose, context, topic parameters, time available)Evaluate and select ideas and information from prior knowledge of inquiry or research topic appropriate for audience, purpose, and perspective or focusIdentify and examine diverse information sources relevant to particular inquiry or research needsEvaluate factors that affect the credibility, authenticity, accuracy, and bias of information sources for inquiry or researchSynthesize information, ideas, and perspectives from a variety of sources to solve problems, answer questions, and seek solutions; document sources accuratelyEvaluate information for completeness, accuracy, currency, historical context, relevance, balance of perspectives, and biasAccess information efficiently and effectively, evaluate information critically and competently, and use information accurately and creatively for the issueUse technology as a tool to research, organize, evaluate, and communicate information, and demonstrate a fundamental understanding of the ethical and legal issues surrounding the access and use of information.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B 30.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create a visual or multimedia presentation that suits the topic, purpose, and audience; teaches others about a global social issue; and persuades them to act on the issue in a responsible manner.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present visual and multimedia presentations: Exhibit logical structures appropriate to audience, purpose, and contextHave a central foci and strong messagesOrganize ideas in logical and appropriate sequencesInclude smooth transitionsUse a variety of forms and technologies such as sound, photographs, models and understand how ideas are communicated through elements of design (e.g., colour, shape, line, texture, placement) and principles of design (e.g., proximity, alignment, repetition, and contrast)Provide logical and convincing conclusions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate deliberately a wide variety of before, during, and after strategies to communicate meaning when representing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply accurately and effectively the language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when representing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create and present a visual or multimedia presentation persuading an audience to act on an issue using presentation techniques most appropriate to audience and purpose: Identify and establish that a problem exists (e.g., crime in a community)Analyze the problem (e.g., what are the causes?)Provide possible solutions (What has been tried? What has not been tried?)Select a solution (What’s best? What are possible future obstacles?)Persuade audience to implement solutionUse digital presentation tools or other media to highlight the problem and point to possible solutions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a media form to suit the topic, purpose, and audience for a visual or multimedia text, and explain why it is an appropriate choice.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify a variety of conventions and/or techniques appropriate to a visual or multimedia form, and explain how these will help communicate specific aspects of intended meaning.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use appropriately a variety of audio-visual aids to support and enhance oral presentations and to engage an audience.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use a visual as a basis for creating an analysis of recurrent themes and variations in a piece of text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze how media messages are constructed, for what purposes, and using which tools, characteristics, and conventions.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B 30.3</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create and defend an informed critical response to a global issue in formal (including a workshop presentation, a debate, and an oral reading of poetry or a prose passage related to the issue) and informal (including discussion and collaborative group work) situations.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Function both as a group member and a group leader, and demonstrate effective group interaction skills and strategies: Demonstrate commitment and flexibility in a groupMonitor own and others’ contributionsBuild on others’ strengths to achieve group goalsCollaborate and consult effectively with others in completing communications tasksRepresent and promote respect for contributions of other team membersApply a variety of strategies including formal decision-making techniques and consensus-building skills to solve problems and achieve group goalsExercise flexibility and willingness to be helpful in making necessary compromises to accomplish a common goalAssume shared responsibility (including roles) for collaborative workDemonstrate ability and commitment to work effectively with diverse teamsWork effectively in a climate of ambiguity and changing priorities.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate deliberately a wide variety of before, during, and after strategies to communicate meaning when speaking.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply accurately and effectively the language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when speaking.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create and present oral presentations: Communicate orally in a clear, coherent manner, using a structure and style appropriate for a variety of purposes, subject matters, and intended audiencesEmploy a logical structure appropriate to the context, audience, and purposeGroup related ideas and maintain a consistent focusInclude smooth transitionsSupport judgements with sound evidence and well-chosen detailsMake skillful use of rhetorical devicesProvide engaging introductions and coherent conclusionsIdentify a variety of vocal strategies, including tone, pace, pitch, and volume, and use them appropriately and with sensitivity to audience needs and cultural differencesIdentify a variety of non-verbal cues, including facial expression, gestures, and eye contact, and use them appropriately to help convey meaning and sensitivity to audience needs and cultural differencesRecognize and adjust oral presentation elements (i.e., articulation, pronunciations, volume, tempo, pitch, stress, gestures, eye contact, facial expression, and poise) in keeping with purpose, audience needs, and individual cultural and linguistic background.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Plan and lead a workshop/seminar presentation: Define topic, goals, and specific objectives for workshopDetermine who the participants will be and what their knowledge of the topic isDetermine the appropriate subject matter, format, presentation method, and venue that will best meet workshop objectivesIntroduce the group members to self and each otherOutline the objectives and agendaProvide relevant and practical information (speaker gives address) and resources (e.g., handouts)Select and use appropriate technologyPlan for and encourage active participation, and allow for skill acquisition, problem solving, and small group discussionSummarize session and feedback.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and participate in a debate (structured argumentation) on an international issue: Focus on a defensible positionParticipate on the affirmative team or the opposing or negative teamEngage in necessary research and demonstrate understanding of topic and related conceptsDefend or attack given propositionDemonstrate organization and forethoughtAdhere to procedural and parliamentary rulesMake relevant, well-researched, and accurate statements in a clear and concise manner without too much reliance on notesRespond with rebuttal statements that are appropriate and that demonstrate comprehension and understanding of the opposing positions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate an understanding of a variety of interpersonal speaking strategies and adapt them to suit the purpose, situation, and audience, exhibiting sensitivity to and respect for cultural differences.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B 30.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Compose and create narrative, descriptive, expository, and persuasive writings that include a position paper, a comparative essay, a letter of inquiry, a critique of an author’s style, and a short story or essay that uses parody, satire, and/or irony.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a variety of written communications using various elements of discourse (e.g., purpose, speaker, audience, form) in narrative, expository, persuasive, informative, and/or descriptive texts:Address audience needs, stated purpose, and contextDevelop a thesis statementCreate an organizing structure appropriate to purpose, audience, and contextInclude relevant information and exclude extraneous informationProvide facts and details, describe or analyze subject, explain benefits or limitations, compare or contrast, or provide graphics or illustrationsClarify and defend positions with relevant evidence, including facts, expert opinions, quotations, and/or expressions of commonly accepted beliefs and logical reasoningUse a variety of rhetorical devices to support assertions (e.g., appeal to logic through reasoning, case study, and analogy)Anticipate potential misunderstanding, problems, or mistakes that might arise for audienceStructure drafts using standard forms and predictable structures (e.g., headings, white space, and graphics) and customary formats (including proper salutations, closing, and signature when writing a letter)Provide a coherent conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate deliberately a wide variety of before, during, and after strategies to communicate meaning when writing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply accurately and effectively the language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when writing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a position paper (convincing argument): Address an issue the writer feels strongly aboutIntroduce topic and state position in beginningSupport writer’s position with the most important facts, details, and logical reasons arranged in a coherent and convincing orderDefend position against an important objectionEnd with a strong restatement of the writer’s positionDefend position well and compel reader to actCreate confidence in position through a clear and strong voiceUse inclusive and respectful languageUse “fair” words and qualifiersEnsure all parts work together to build a thoughtful convincing position.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a comparative essay: Reveal new insights about topic because of the comparisonCapture reader’s attention and provide details that lead up to thesis or focus statement in a well-developed introduction Discuss each topic point by point in the bodySum up, reflect on, or comment on the comparison in a coherent, convincing conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a letter of inquiry (or request):Explain adequately what the inquiry is about and what the reader is to do in response to the letter (e.g., advice; information from a government agency; information on a product or service; copy of an official document; request for credit; application materials; estimates or bids)Make letter courteous and clearState who the writer is and give status or positionState what the inquiry is about and explain specifically what the recipient should doInclude the necessary details (e.g., date information is needed, services, etc.)Thank the recipient for his/her timeFollow a standard letter format.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a story or essay using parody, satire, and/or irony: Choose one scene from a print textUse a tone that seems straightforward but leads the reader to know that the real intention is to criticize or ridicule and, in the end, illuminate a problem.Use exaggeration and/or understatement.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a critique of an author’s style: Consider purpose and intended audienceAddress author’s treatment of subject (specific, concrete, direct, general, abstract, philosophical)Analyze form chosen to express ideas: tone (e.g., informal, conversational, professional critical, satirical, amused, encouraging, pensive); point of view (e.g., first person or third person); arrangement and organization of ideas; sentence structures; diction (e.g., formal or informal; colloquial or technical); images and symbols; use of rhetorical devices; other distinctive mannerismsIdentify the writer’s overall, distinctive approach or “style.”</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with different forms and formats (e.g., proposal, script, letter to government officials advocating change) and techniques, and explain their appeal.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR B 30.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Assess own and others' work for precision, clarity, and artistry.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Review and analyze own and others’ work for content, organization, delivery, audience response, and style.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify a variety of skills and strategies in viewing, listening, reading, representing, speaking, and writing; and explain how the skills and strategies improve communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify appropriate steps and implement plans to improve comprehension and communication skills.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a range of products that clearly reflect own growth as a communicator, and explain the reasons for choices.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess the effect of new understandings and strategies on self and others.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR B 30.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Reflect on and assess understanding of self as a self-directed, self-appraising, and strategic learner.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Review and analyze own and others’ work for content, organization, delivery, audience response, and style.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify a variety of skills and strategies in viewing, listening, reading, representing, speaking, and writing; and explain how the skills and strategies improve communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify appropriate steps and implement plans to improve comprehension and communication skills.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a range of products that clearly reflect own growth as a communicator, and explain the reasons for choices.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess the effect of new understandings and strategies on self and others.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
  </outcomes>
</curriculum>