<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>https://www.edonline.sk.ca/bbcswebdav/xid-181774_1</pdf>
  <banner>english/ELAB10_flat.png</banner>
  <dark_colour>#5493ad</dark_colour>
  <light_colour>#dde9ef</light_colour>
  <goals>english/englishlanguagearts10aimsgoals.htm</goals>
  <teaching>english/englishlanguagearts10teaching.htm</teaching>
  <curriculum_name>English Language Arts B10</curriculum_name>
  <classification_id>english language arts B10</classification_id>
  <outcomes>
    <goal_section>
      <goal_heading>Comprehend and Respond (CR)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR B10.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Comprehend and respond to a variety of visual, oral, print, and multimedia texts that address:identity (e.g., Diversity of Being);social responsibility (e.g., Degrees of Responsibility); andsocial action (agency) (e.g., Justice and Fairness).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>View, listen to, read, comprehend, and respond to a variety of contemporary and traditional texts including First Nations and Métis resources that present different viewpoints and perspectives on issues and reflect diverse personal identities, worldviews, and backgrounds (e.g., appearance, culture, socio-economic status, ability, age, gender, language).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply personal experiences and prior knowledge of texts and language to develop understanding and interpretations of variety of texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Respond personally and critically to individuals, events, and ideas presented in a variety of First Nations, Métis, Canadian, and international texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Discuss ways in which texts convey and challenge individual and community values and behaviours.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify how human experiences and values are reflected in texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Test ideas and values against ideas and values in texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>View, listen to, read, and respond to historically or culturally significant works (texts) that reflect and enhance studies in history and social science.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify recurrent patterns and themes in texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Analyze how a text is related to the themes and issues of a particular period in time.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR B10.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>View, interpret, and report on ideas and information from more than one source to develop and support positions on various topics related to the course including identity, social responsibility, and personal agency.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>View, comprehend, interpret, and summarize grade-appropriate visual and multimedia texts created by First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, Canadian, and international developers and artists from various cultural communities that address identity, social responsibility, and personal agency.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate purposefully a variety of before (page 24), during (page 25), and after (page 26) strategies to construct meaning when viewing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand and apply language communication cues and conventions to construct and confirm meaning when viewing including:Pragmatic cues: recognizing and comprehending language registers that are varied and used for effect.Textual cues: recognizing and comprehending the organization of thoughts and ideas of a range of visual and multimedia texts and their organizational features.Syntactic cues: recognizing and comprehending a variety of sentence patterns for communicating and clarifying meaning.Semantic/Lexical/Morphological cues: using a dictionary or other source to determine a word’s meaning(s).Graphophonic cues: recognizing the correct form and usage of a word.Other cues: recognizing and comprehending how features including graphic aids (e.g., diagrams, graphs, timelines) support and enhance the message.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>View, interpret, and draw conclusions about the ideas and information presented in a variety of illustrations, maps, charts, graphs, and other visual texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate how genders and various cultures and socio-economic groups are portrayed in representations by the mass media.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recognize persuasive techniques (including propaganda) being used in visual and multimedia texts, and analyze and assess the impact of specific media, techniques, and designs.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present critical response to what was viewed.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and evaluate the verbal and visual features including images, colour, layout, graphics, and messages in consumer products (e.g., clothing, electronic products, food, entertainment services).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Respond to and discuss various meanings, ideas, and effects describing how verbal and static and moving visual features are combined for different purposes and audiences in CD covers, posters, and videos of popular songs and singers.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Attend a performance of a play and discuss the specific scenes, main character, and technical production aspects of the presentation.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <outcome_text>Listen to, comprehend, interpret, and summarize information and ideas presented in a variety of literary and informational texts including group discussion, oral readings, interviews, prepared talks, and a talk-back show about a topic or issue being studied.</outcome_text>
        <identifier>CR B10.3</identifier>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Listen to, interpret, and summarize grade-appropriate literary and informational texts created by First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, Canadian, and international authors from various cultural communities that address identity, social responsibility, and personal agency.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate purposefully a variety of before (page 24), during (page 25), and after (page 26) strategies to construct meaning when listening.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand and apply language cues and conventions to construct and confirm meaning when listening including:Pragmatic cues: recognizing and comprehending language registers that are varied and used for effect (e.g., characterization, dialect) and that have been influenced by the context (e.g., community in which it was learned).Textual cues: recognizing and comprehending the organization of thoughts and ideas of a range of oral texts and their organizational features.Syntactic cues: recognizing and comprehending how word order and sentence patterns communicate meaning in English and also when they do not communicate clearly.Semantic/Lexical/Morphological cues: using a dictionary or other source to determine a word’s meaning(s) and etymology.Graphophonic cues: recognizing the correct form and usage of a word.Other cues: recognizing and comprehending how features including voice production factors (e.g., articulation, tone, tempo, pronunciation, volume, emphasis, pitch, pause) and non-verbal cues (e.g., gestures, stance, eye contact) clarify intent of message.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate active listening behaviour including:concentrate, focus, attend, and filter distractionsanalyze explicit and implicit messages, viewpoints, and conceptsrecognize overall plan or organization including transitional expressionsparaphrase what was listened to and hearddistinguish fact from opinionidentify and analyze persuasive techniquesevaluate perspective, credibility, and logicuse effective notemaking strategies and a variety of written or graphic forms to organize, summarize, and share ideas acquired from listeningprepare and ask relevant questions and respond appropriatelyanalyze the overall effectiveness of the message.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand the factors that interfere with good listening (e.g., environment, speaker, listener) and filter out distractions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present critical response to what was listened to and heard supporting conclusions with reference to what was presented.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply appropriate listening strategies when interviewing (including preparing and asking relevant questions, making notes, responding correctly and effectively, compiling and reporting responses).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Formulate and support judgements (using convincing evidence) about the ideas under discussion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Listen to and evaluate several excerpts from a range of phone-in talk-back shows about a particular issue.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR B10.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Read, interpret, and summarize a wide variety of classical and contemporary literary (including drama, biography, autobiography, poetry, short stories, novels) and informational (including letters, diaries, memoranda, electronic communications) texts.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read, interpret, and summarize grade-appropriate literary and informational texts created by First Nations, Métis, Saskatchewan, Canadian, and international authors from various cultural communities that address identity, social responsibility, and personal agency.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate purposefully a variety of before (page 24), during (page 25), and after (page 26) strategies to construct meaning when reading.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand and apply language cues and conventions to construct and confirm meaning when reading including:Pragmatic cues: recognizing and comprehending language registers that are varied and used for effect (e.g., characterization, dialect) and that have been influenced by the context (e.g., community in which it was learned).Textual cues: recognizing and comprehending the organization of thoughts and ideas in a variety of written and other texts including distinctive features of genres (e.g., prose, poetry) and organizational patterns within each genre (e.g., chronological, spatial, enumerative, problem and solution, cause and effect, comparison and contrast).Syntactic cues: recognizing and comprehending how word order and sentence patterns communicate meaning in English and also when they do not communicate clearly.Semantic/Lexical/Morphological cues: using a dictionary or other source to determine a word’s meaning(s), usage, pronunciation, and etymology.Graphophonic cues: recognizing and using the correct form and usage of a word to determine the pronunciation (e.g., “project” as a noun versus as a verb).Other cues: recognizing and comprehending how features such as layout and accompanying graphics clarify intent of message.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate active reading behaviours including:establish a purpose for reading such as to learn, interpret, and enjoyskim, scan, and read closelyidentify and analyze explicit and implicit messages, viewpoints, concepts, persuasive techniques, and propaganda techniques (e.g., testimonial, band wagon, stereotyping)recognize and analyze text structures and elementsrelate understanding of a range of texts to personal experience, purposes, audience, and other textsevaluate perspective, credibility, and logicdifferentiate fact from opiniondifferentiate between literal and figurative statementstest own ideas and values against those in textrecognize, comprehend, and discuss the significance of allusions and symbols in contextconstruct images based on text descriptionsdiscuss and analyze meanings, ideas, language, and literary quality in a range of contemporary and historical texts, taking account of purpose, audience, and timeuse notemaking, marginal notes, and outlining to better understand texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read fluently and independently a wide range of contemporary and historical texts, adapting reading processes and strategies for different purposes (including for information and enjoyment).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recognize stylistic devices and techniques such as characterization, flashback, foreshadowing, and hyperbole.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Describe, discuss, and analyze the distinctive conventions, structures, and language features of a range of texts and explain how they suit the topic and purpose.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read about a particular event or issue, using texts from a range of sources, including magazines, newspapers, cartoons, and letters to the editor to identify different points of view or angles.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compare the characteristics of different texts and consider the reason for these differences, in terms of topic, purpose, and point of view.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read and interpret critically the main ideas, events, and themes of a variety of literary texts including stories, novels, scripts, poetry, and non-fiction works, and prepare and present critical responses to what was read.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Read and make generalizations, supported by specific details and examples, about key concepts, characters, themes, and techniques in literary texts.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
    <goal_section>
      <goal_heading>Compose and Create (CC)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B10.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Compose and create a range of visual, multimedia, oral, and written texts to explore:identity (e.g., Diversity of Being);social responsibility (e.g., Degrees of Responsibility); andsocial action (agency) (e.g., Justice and Fairness).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop and articulate defensible points of view on individual, community, national, and world issues.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create spoken, written, and other representations that include:a clear thesis and logical points to support thesisappropriate details to support thesisa style and voice appropriate to audience and purposecoherence, logical progression, and support for ideasclear patterns of organizationa justifiable conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop a project-focused inquiry related to a theme or issue of the course:generate relevant questions that can be researchedrefine topics and clarify ideascompile information from primary and secondary sources in systematic wayssynthesize the content from several sources or works by various authors dealing with a single issueinterpret and report on ideas and information from more than one source to develop and support positions on various topicsextend ideas presented in primary or secondary sources through original analysis, evaluation, and elaborationcompile ideas and information into reports, summaries, and other formats and draw conclusions.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B10.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create and present a visual or multimedia presentation supporting a prepared talk on a researched issue, using either digital or other presentation tools.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present visual and multimedia presentations and a research talk/report that:use logical structures appropriate to audience, purpose, and contexthave a central foci and strong messagesorganize ideas in a logical and appropriate sequenceinclude smooth transitions and ensure smooth flow from visual to visualexhibit a variety of forms and technologies such as sound, photographs, and models, and understand how ideas are communicated through elements of design such as colour, shape, line, and textureuse props, visual aids, graphics, music, sound effects, photos (“clip-art”), and electronic media to enhance the appeal and accuracy of presentations, and ensure words on visuals are easy to readensure each visual fits audience and purposeprovide logical and convincing conclusions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate purposefully a variety of before (page 28), during (page 29), and after (page 30) strategies to construct and communicate meaning when using other forms of representing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand and apply language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when using various forms of representing including:Pragmatic cues and conventions: selecting and using language that includes people across cultures, races, genders, ages, and abilities and avoids common usage problems including imprecision and the use of jargon, slang, euphemism, clichés, gobbledygook, and “abusages” (such as “Me and John…”, “I can’t get no…,”“Like,…”).Textual cues and conventions: creating visual and multimedia texts that are unified (i.e., all elements combined to form a single whole or “oneness”) and coherent (i.e., consistent, logically arranged, and connected).Syntactic cues and conventions: using sentences that are varied in form (e.g., parallelism, inversion, subordination); are free of misplaced qualifiers and dangling qualifiers; show agreement of subject and verb, consistency in verb tense, pronoun agreement, and clear pronoun reference; and use correctly that/which, who/whom, and punctuation.Semantic/lexical/morphological cues and conventions: using words correctly including prepositions (e.g., suited to, suited for), homonyms (e.g., to, too, two), plurals and possessives (e.g., the cat’s paws, students’ projects, people’s pets), and meaning (e.g., then/than; few, fewer/less, lesser).Graphophonic cues and conventions: recognizing and using Canadian spelling conventions and clear pronunciation to aid spelling (e.g., accept, except).Other cues and conventions: using appropriate visual elements (e.g., colour, layout, graphics, illustrations) and media technologies to clarify and enhance message.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, interpret, and synthesize information from visual texts and present it effectively, using a range of visual and layout features and appropriate technologies for variety of purposes.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a section of narrative text and use it as a basis for a dramatization using narrator where appropriate, dialogue, action, backgrounds, costumes, props, music, sound effects, and language that retain the intent and tone of the original text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present a real-life action or role play an event such as buying or selling something and present the role play to class.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a character from a novel and plan a seminar that gives an analysis of the character and includes the use of digital or other presentation tools to show the relationships between the character and other characters in the novel (e.g., a family tree), video or still photography to demonstrate ideas for a film setting, and a sound recording to record dialogue from the text or an interview with the character with appropriate musical accompaniment.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop imaginative or creative representations to share interpretations and ideas.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use persuasive techniques (e.g., rhetorical question, repetition, parallelism, analogy, appeal to authority) in visual and multimedia texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with a variety of text forms (e.g., advertisements, posters, videos) and techniques (e.g., colour, typeface, graphics).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B10.3</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Use oral language to express a range of information and ideas in formal (including a prepared talk on a researched issue, an interview, an oral reading of prose or poetry, and an explanation and defence of a personal point of view) and informal (including discussion and group work) situations.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Participate in small- and large-group discussion, observing the courtesies of group discussion, and demonstrate effective group interaction skills and strategies including:assume some of the work necessary to maintain discussion and advance it (e.g., by summarizing, raising questions, seeking clarification, extracting significant points, making connections, setting agenda).maintain and demonstrate respectful behavioursstick to topic and keep goals in mindlisten carefullyco-operate by staying positive, waiting turn, and avoiding put-downsdisagree respectfullyencourage others by trying to understand their ideas and asking for opinionsclarify and restate speaker’s ideas to confirm meaning.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate purposefully a variety of before (page 28), during (page 29), and after (page 30) strategies to construct and communicate meaning when speaking.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand and apply language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when speaking including:Pragmatic cues and conventions: selecting and using language that includes people across cultures, races, genders, ages, and abilities and avoids common usage problems including imprecision and the use of jargon, slang, euphemism, clichés, gobbledygook, and “abusages” (such as “Me and John…”, “I can’t get no…,”“Like,…”).Textual cues and conventions: creating oral texts that are unified (i.e., all elements combined to form a single whole or “oneness”) and coherent (i.e., consistent, logically arranged, and connected).Syntactic cues and conventions: using sentences that are varied in form (e.g., parallelism, inversion, subordination); are free of misplaced qualifiers and dangling qualifiers; show agreement of subject and verb, consistency in verb tense, pronoun agreement, and clear pronoun reference; and use correctly that/which, who/whom, and punctuation.Semantic/lexical/morphological cues and conventions: using words correctly including prepositions (e.g., suited to, suited for), homonyms (e.g., to, too, two), plurals and possessives (e.g., the cat’s paws, students’ projects, people’s pets), and meaning (e.g., then/than; few, fewer/less, lesser).Graphophonic cues and conventions: recognizing and using Canadian spelling conventions and clear pronunciation to aid spelling (e.g., accept, except).Other cues and conventions: using appropriate oral elements (e.g., volume, intonation); using appropriate non-verbal cues and body language; using appropriate gestures, facial expressions, sound, and visual and multimedia aids to enhance message.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use oral language to interact purposefully, confidently, and appropriately in a variety of situations including participating in one-to-one, small-group, and large-group discussions (demonstrating an awareness of the relationship of language to group and community membership, acknowledging and paraphrasing views that differ from own, reassessing own viewpoints, prompting and supporting others, solving problems, resolving conflicts, building consensus, articulating and explaining personal viewpoint, discussing preferences, speaking to extend current understanding, and celebrating special events and accomplishments).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Work in pairs to develop and script an interview on an issue of interest or on an incident in a literary text, for a particular audience and purpose.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>In role, rehearse and record interview or present interview to the group.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Work in pairs to prepare and present closing argument for and against a selected fictional character on a charge which could have been levelled at a character.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select three poems related to theme and present them to a group of peers using voice to clarify meaning by emphasizing rhythm, highlighting particular words or phrases, and signalling the role and effects of line endings, stanza breaks, and other elements of structure.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recognize and use elements of classical speech forms (including introduction, body with transitions, conclusion) in formulating rational arguments and apply the art of persuasion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recognize and adjust oral presentation elements (i.e., articulation, pronunciation, volume, tempo, pitch, stress, gestures, eye contact, facial expression, and poise) in keeping with purpose, audience needs, and situation.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC B10.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create a variety of written informational (including a business letter, biographical profile, problem-solution essay) and literary (including fictionalized journal entries and a short script) communications.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write informational and literary texts that:use various elements of discourse (e.g., purpose, speaker, audience, form) in narrative, expository, persuasive, informational, and/or descriptive textsexhibit logical structures appropriate to audience, purpose, and contexthave a central foci and strong messagesstructure material in appropriate styles for audiencedefine the main idea by selecting relevant, logical details that meet the reader’s perceived needsorganize ideas in a logical and appropriate sequenceinclude smooth transitionsprovide logical and convincing conclusions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, use, and evaluate purposefully a variety of before (page 28), during (page 29), and after (page 30) strategies to construct and communicate meaning when writing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand and apply language cues and conventions to construct and communicate meaning when writing including:Pragmatic cues and conventions: selecting and using language that includes people across cultures, races, genders, ages, and abilities, and avoids common usage problems including imprecision and the use of jargon, slang, euphemism, clichés, gobbledygook, and “abusages” (such as “Me and John…”, “I can’t get no…,”“Like,…”).Textual cues and conventions: creating written texts that are unified (i.e., all elements combined to form a single whole or “oneness”) and coherent (i.e., consistent, logically arranged, and connected).Syntactic cues and conventions: using sentences that are varied in form (e.g., parallelism, inversion, subordination); are free of misplaced qualifiers and dangling qualifiers; show agreement of subject and verb, consistency in verb tense, pronoun agreement, and clear pronoun reference; and use correctly that/which, who/whom, and punctuation.Semantic/lexical/morphological cues and conventions: using words correctly including prepositions (e.g., suited to, suited for), homonyms (e.g., to, too, two), plurals and possessives (e.g., the cat’s paws, students’ projects, people’s pets), and meaning (e.g., then/than; few, fewer/less, lesser).Graphophonic cues and conventions: recognizing and using Canadian spelling conventions and clear pronunciation to aid spelling (e.g., accept, except).Other cues and conventions: using appropriate written elements (e.g., font size, type face, formatting); writing legibly with appropriate speed and control; using communication elements such as neatness, underlining, indentations, spacing, and margins to enhance clarity and legibility of communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write an explanation and defence of personal point of view that:explains writer’s beliefs about an important subjectidentifies focus of essay in opening paragraphorganizes ideas in a logical and appropriate sequenceincludes smooth transitionsprovides logical and convincing conclusions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a biographical profile that:includes key ideas learned about the personbegins by sharing some important background informationdescribes the subject and explains what he or she accomplishedends by leaving the readers with something to think about and consider</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a problem-solution essay (e.g., an essay in which you analyze a problem and present one or more solutions) that :focuses on a problem that is important to selfidentities the problem in a clear statementanalyzes the problem thoroughly, explaining its parts, history, and causesweighs possible solutions, what is being done to address the problems, and suggestions or solutionsdetermines what readers need to knowexplains why situation exists and how it can be fixedincludes all the important facts and reasonsends effectively explaining what the writer would like to see done.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a business letter (e.g., letter of complaint, e-mail request) that:uses a consistent style (semi-block or full block)presents information completely and in the correct orderincludes all the parts of a business letter – heading, inside address, salutation, body, complimentary closing, and signaturestates purpose clearly and immediatelygives complete and accurate detailsstates clearly what the writer wants the reader to doavoids expressions that are wordy, clichéd, vague, or discriminatorybegins, continues, and ends with courteous tonedetermines what the recipient needs to know.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write fictionalized journal entries (e.g., of a literary character or a historical figure) that:focus on a made-up character or someone read about or observedfocus on an ongoing event or experiencecontain impressions, reflections, and observations about life, people, and experiencesgive insight into the personality and values of the character.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Write a short script (e.g., a short play or a script for an advertisement) that:includes stage directions that indicate the time and place of the action, entrances and exits, and what characters are doing on stagegives details of setting that lead into the beginning of the scriptemploys dialogue (characters’ words) that moves the action alongbuilds around a believable conflict or problem that makes sense in the lives of the main charactersincludes (if multimedia) graphics, music, Blend In, Cut To, Fade In, Fade Out, Insert, and other elements.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with and explore a variety of written text forms (such as letter of complaint, obituary, brochure) and techniques (such as figurative language, literary devices, anecdotes).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
    <goal_section>
      <goal_heading>Assess and Reflect (AR)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR B10.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Establish and apply criteria to evaluate own and others’ work.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use feedback to evaluate own effectiveness as a communicator.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate own and others’ contributions to group process and provide support where needed.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Set goals in language learning and use; identify strategies to achieve those goals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Consider alternative ways of reaching goals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Celebrate special accomplishments by using language to describe and discuss achievements.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR B10.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Set personal language learning goals and select strategies to enhance growth in language learning.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use feedback to evaluate own effectiveness as a communicator.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate own and others’ contributions to group process and provide support where needed.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Set goals in language learning and use; identify strategies to achieve those goals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Consider alternative ways of reaching goals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Celebrate special accomplishments by using language to describe and discuss achievements.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
  </outcomes>
</curriculum>