<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<curriculum>
  <pdf>https://www.edonline.sk.ca/bbcswebdav/xid-181785_1</pdf>
  <banner>english/ELA8.png</banner>
  <dark_colour>#5493ad</dark_colour>
  <light_colour>#dde9ef</light_colour>
  <goals>english/englishlanguagearts6-9aimsgoals.htm</goals>
  <teaching>english/englishlanguagearts8teaching.htm</teaching>
  <curriculum_name>English Language Arts 8</curriculum_name>
  <classification_id>english language arts 8</classification_id>
  <outcomes>
    <goal_section>
      <goal_heading>Comprehend and Respond (CR)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>View, listen to, read, comprehend, and respond to a variety of texts that address identity (e.g., Becoming Myself), social responsibility (e.g., In Search of Justice), and efficacy (e.g., Building a Better World).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>View, listen to, read, and respond to a variety of visual, multimedia (including digital), oral, and print texts that address the grade-level themes and issues related to identity, social responsibility, and efficacy including those that reflect diverse personal identities, worldviews, and backgrounds (e.g., appearance, culture, socio-economic status, ability, age, gender, sexual orientation, language, career pathway).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate comprehension of a variety of visual, oral, print, and multimedia (including digital) texts by: understanding the ideas: Clearly, completely, and accurately summarize and explain the ideas and implicit and explicit messages (including setting, main characters, conflicts, events) in texts; cite details that support the main ideas; make logical inferences; interpret obvious themes or author’s message logically. understanding, using, and analyzing the text structures and (language) features of texts to construct meaning: Use key text features (e.g., headings, diagrams, paragraphs); recognize organizational patterns (e.g., text structure) and structural cues within texts (e.g., transition words); recognize rhetorical techniques and craft of texts (e.g., hyperbole, parallelism, colour, repetition); identify how texts were constructed, shaped, and produced. responding to and interpreting texts: Make, explain, and justify reactions and personal connections to texts; give opinions and make judgements supported by reasons, explanations, and evidence; make judgements and draw conclusions about ideas on the basis of evidence; make logical interpretations of the author’s message; make and support inferences about characters’ feelings, motivations, and point of view; organize response and interpretation around several clear ideas or premises.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explain the motivation of the characters in literary texts, providing evidence from each text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and describe techniques used to create mood in visual, oral, written, and multimedia (including digital) texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explain preferences for various texts, genres, or specific authors.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and explain connections between new ideas and information and previous beliefs, values, and experiences.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify stereotyping in what is seen, heard, and read and begin to recognize its negative impact on individuals and society.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify techniques used to create particular effects or portray various people and cultures.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Discuss how similar ideas, people, experiences, and traditions are conveyed in a variety of oral, print, and other texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Consider how text has contributed to understanding of self and others (e.g., cultural groups).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Describe and give examples to explain personal criteria for assessing and responding to what is viewed, heard, or read.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate the content, quality, organization, and presentation of a text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Produce response journals and use interactive websites such as web logs (“blogs” for short) that serve as journals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Describe the purpose of specific texts and explain how their key features aid understanding.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Select and use appropriate strategies to construct meaning before (e.g., previewing and anticipating message), during (e.g., making inferences based on text and prior knowledge), and after (e.g., paraphrasing and summarizing) viewing, listening, and reading.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Before: tap, activate, and build prior knowledge (e.g., review what is known and has been learned about subject of text; identify what needs to be learned from text to fill in gaps)ask questions (e.g., survey text and ask questions about it; form implicit questions and search for answers in text)preview text (e.g., look briefly at each section and page of a text, paying attention to the headings, illustrations, boldface type, and organizational structure; read the first and last paragraphs of a print text)anticipate message and author’s/presenter’s intent (e.g., consider the author’s/presenter’s possible intention given a brief biographical sketch about his or her background and causes)predict what text will be about (e.g., review an outline of the main ideas in a text and predict what information or stance will be used to support these main ideas)Set purpose (e.g., discuss and set a purpose with peers).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>During: connect and construct meaning (e.g., make connections to self, other texts, and to the world to help with making predictions, visualizing, and drawing conclusions)note key ideas and what supports them (e.g., stop at the end of each page, section, or chapter to answer the who, what, when, where, why, and how questions; note how examples, illustrations, and visual aids support or take away from key message)construct mental images (e.g., imagine what a character might be seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, or feeling in a particular place and time)make, confirm, and adjust predictions (e.g., identify and explain the clues in the text that confirm defensible predictions)make, confirm, and adjust inferences and draw conclusions (e.g., analyze, infer, and explain unstated ideas in texts)ask questions (e.g., ask questions, focusing particularly on evaluative questions to gain meaning from text, and to locate key points)use cueing systems to construct meaning and self-monitor comprehension (e.g., use and insert notations such as + for “that’s new”, ? for “I don’t understand”, * for “that’s important”)adjust rate and/or strategy (e.g., skim, scan, and read carefully depending on the text complexity and purpose).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>After: recall, paraphrase, summarize, and synthesize (e.g., connect, compare, and contrast ideas in texts; determine implied and literal messages; make notes to assist recall)reflect and interpret (e.g., keep an open mind and consider ideas that differ from own)evaluate (respond critically) (e.g., identify strategies used to influence audience including exaggeration, one-sided view of a group, jolts)evaluate craft and techniques (e.g., draw conclusions about presenter’s, speaker’s, writer’s message, values, point of view, and craft)respond personally (giving support from text) (e.g., connect, compare, and contrast ideas in text to own knowledge and experiences)listen, read, or view again and speak, write, and represent to deepen understanding and pleasure (e.g., listen, read, or view again to evaluate the effectiveness and overall impact of the text to deliver the message intended).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.3</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Use pragmatic (e.g., intended audience and tone), textual (e.g., how author organized text to achieve unity and coherence), syntactic (e.g., variety of sentence structures), semantic/lexical/morphological (e.g., imagery), graphophonic (e.g., stress, pitch, and juncture of a word), and other cues (e.g., layout and accompanying graphics) to construct and to confirm meaning.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>NOTE: Italicized text refers to those indicators that are emphasized at this grade level.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recognize and understand the particular purpose, tone, and register (pragmatic), textual structures and patterns (textual), sentence structure (syntactical), word patterns and meanings (lexical/semantic/morphological), sound-symbol relationships (graphophonic), and other cues and conventions in visual, oral, print, and multimedia (including digital) texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language cues and conventions to construct, monitor, and confirm meaning including:</p>
            <p>Pragmatic: Textual: Syntactical: Semantic/Lexical/Morphological: Graphophonic: Other Cues</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>View critically and demonstrate comprehension of a variety of visual and multimedia texts including videos, television broadcasts, informational presentations, dramatic presentations, websites, and news programs to locate and interpret key messages and details, to develop conclusions, opinions, and understanding, and to evaluate the effectiveness of the text.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the behaviours of an effective and active viewer including formulating questions before viewing; viewing attentively; relating text to self, text to other texts, and text to world; recognizing main ideas and underlying messages and values; recognizing how images and other elements (e.g., data displays) are capturing and holding attention; identifying the impact the text is having on self; reflecting and reviewing in light of purpose.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate ability to navigate and process information when viewing websites, films, videos, and presentations.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify the different techniques (including data displays) used in different media works (including digital) to impact viewers.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify creative uses of language in visual and multimedia texts including those associated with popular culture (e.g., animation, video, computer games).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compare how various forms of media (e.g., newspaper, radio, TV, and Internet) cover the same topic.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compare various styles of data displays for clarity and effectiveness.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate the overall effectiveness and impact of a range of individual visual and multimedia texts (including digital texts).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.5</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Listen critically to understand, gather information, follow directions, form an opinion, and analyze oral presentations for diverse opinions, presenter’s point of view, values, and biases, stereotypes, or prejudices.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the behaviours of an effective and active listener including adapting listening and focus to purpose and situation, keeping an open mind and considering ideas that differ from own, determining the congruency between the speaker’s verbal and non-verbal cues, determining whether fact or opinion is being expressed, interacting appropriately with speaker, and seeking clarification when meaning is not clear.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate ability to process information when listening to a formal presentation (including a podcast).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Make connections among different texts by comparing features including themes, issues, styles, and appeal.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Paraphrase a speaker’s purpose and point of view.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Listen critically to evaluate others’ ideas or opinions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate the credibility of a speaker and the various ways in which visual images communicate information and affect impressions and opinions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate ability to analyze informational texts differentiating between fact and opinion and recognizing point of view, biases, and stereotypes.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.6</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Read and demonstrate comprehension and interpretation of grade-appropriate texts including traditional and contemporary prose fiction, poetry, and plays from First Nations, Métis, and other cultures to evaluate the purpose, message, point of view, craft, values, and biases, stereotypes, or prejudices.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the behaviours of an effective and active reader including previewing text, anticipating author’s message, reading with purpose in mind, recognizing main ideas and relevant details for purpose, making jot notes to assist recall, considering author’s reasoning for creating text, analyzing and evaluating ideas and craft as one reads, and recognizing underlying biases, stereotypes, or prejudices in text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate an understanding of the main ideas, events, or themes of a variety of novels, stories, poetry, and other oral, print, and electronic media.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Interpret and report on information obtained from more than one source to inform others.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use various forms of note making (e.g., lists, summaries, observations, descriptions) appropriate to purpose and situation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the ability to comprehend and use everyday texts (e.g., directions, schedules, brochures) and make judgements about purpose and importance.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Utilize note making and outlining as learning tools.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Show understanding that the author’s experience, background, and culture influenced the treatment of theme.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify with and develop an understanding of the characters the author has created from what they say and do and from what other characters and the narrator say about them.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, independently, texts that address learning needs and interests.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.7</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Read independently and demonstrate comprehension of a variety of information texts including understanding the main ideas and supporting evidence, explaining connections between new ideas and information and previous thoughts, and recognizing any biases or false reasoning.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the behaviours of an effective and active reader including previewing text, anticipating author’s message, reading with purpose in mind, recognizing main ideas and relevant details for purpose, making jot notes to assist recall, considering author’s reasoning for creating text, analyzing and evaluating ideas and craft as one reads, and recognizing underlying biases, stereotypes, or prejudices in text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate an understanding of the main ideas, events, or themes of a variety of novels, stories, poetry, and other oral, print, and electronic media.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Interpret and report on information obtained from more than one source to inform others.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use various forms of note making (e.g., lists, summaries, observations, descriptions) appropriate to purpose and situation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the ability to comprehend and use everyday texts (e.g., directions, schedules, brochures) and make judgements about purpose and importance.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Utilize note making and outlining as learning tools.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Show understanding that the author’s experience, background, and culture influenced the treatment of theme.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify with and develop an understanding of the characters the author has created from what they say and do and from what other characters and the narrator say about them.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, independently, texts that address learning needs and interests.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CR8.8</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Read Grade 8 appropriate texts to increase fluency (140-180 wcpm orally; 180-230 silently) and expression.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the behaviours of an effective and active reader including previewing text, anticipating author’s message, reading with purpose in mind, recognizing main ideas and relevant details for purpose, making jot notes to assist recall, considering author’s reasoning for creating text, analyzing and evaluating ideas and craft as one reads, and recognizing underlying biases, stereotypes, or prejudices in text.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate an understanding of the main ideas, events, or themes of a variety of novels, stories, poetry, and other oral, print, and electronic media.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Interpret and report on information obtained from more than one source to inform others.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use various forms of note making (e.g., lists, summaries, observations, descriptions) appropriate to purpose and situation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the ability to comprehend and use everyday texts (e.g., directions, schedules, brochures) and make judgements about purpose and importance.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Utilize note making and outlining as learning tools.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Show understanding that the author’s experience, background, and culture influenced the treatment of theme.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify with and develop an understanding of the characters the author has created from what they say and do and from what other characters and the narrator say about them.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select, independently, texts that address learning needs and interests.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
    <goal_section>
      <goal_heading>Compose and Create (CC)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create various visual, oral, written, and multimedia (including digital) texts that explore identity (e.g., Telling One’s Life Story), social responsibility (e.g., Examining the Influence of Popular Culture), and efficacy (e.g., Creating Turning Points).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a variety of texts (i.e., oral presentations, written and other compositions) that represent experiences, ideas, and information about identity, social responsibility, and efficacy with clarity, correctness, and variety.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create speeches, writing, and other representations that feature the following qualities: Message Content or Ideas (Meaning): Focuses on main ideas and information; provides relevant details, examples, and explanations; is accurate, complete, and uses own words; shows some individuality or originality in literary texts; contains ideas and images that create an impact. Organization and Coherence (Form): Introduces the topic and purpose; provides some context; sticks to the topic; is easy to follow with related ideas grouped together and sequenced logically; uses appropriate connecting words; creates a logical ending; includes appropriate and required text features (e.g., titles, headings, diagrams, illustrations), correctly constructed. Language Conventions (Style and Language Choices): Uses clear purpose and language; shows a good sense of audience; contains description and variety in diction; contains a variety of sentence lengths and varied sentence beginnings; demonstrates the use of several different conjunctions; formulates complete, simple, compound, and complex sentences correctly (avoiding run-ons and fragments); applies the conventions of oral and written language, including correct spelling, correct punctuation (including use of colon, dash, and hyphen), uses legible cursive handwriting and clear representations which are visually accurate, legible, and neatly presented.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Represent, articulate, and explain personal viewpoints clearly.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Summarize main ideas discussed and conclusions drawn, encourage others to contribute, disagree courteously/sensitively, answer others’ questions clearly and politely, and add to others’ ideas</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Participate in group inquiry related to the themes and issues being studied in English language arts:</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create and present a group inquiry project related to a topic, theme, or issue studied in English language arts.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Determine personal knowledge of a topic to generate possible areas of inquiry or research.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Formulate relevant questions on a topic to establish a purpose for gathering information.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Contribute ideas, knowledge, and strategies to help identify group information needs and sources.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Collaborate with others using technology to plan inquiry.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and use a plan to access, gather, and record in own words relevant information.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Gather information from a variety of sources (e.g., interviews, print texts, CD-ROMs, Internet) and integrate ideas in analysis.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Organize information and ideas in order of priority according to topic and task requirements.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Make notes in point form, summarizing major ideas and supporting details.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Sort, organize, classify, and extend data using information technology tools.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Adjust inquiry and research strategies to accommodate changing perspectives and availability of pertinent information.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Document cited resources within presentations and composition.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use the language of inquiry (e.g., “What processes or procedures could we use?”, “What criteria will we use to judge how effective the sources and processes are in addressing the topic?”, “How can we prepare a presentation suitable for the purpose, audience, and situation that we identified?”).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.3</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Select and use the appropriate strategies to communicate meaning before (e.g., plan, organize, and sequence ideas to fit purpose, point of view, and format), during (e.g., use and maintain appropriate point of view for audience and purpose), and after (e.g., revise final drafts and presentations to ensure that the format and patterns within that format contribute to the effectiveness of the composition) speaking, writing, and other representing activities.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate an understanding of the creating process by preparing (pre-writing), creating drafts, revising, and creating a final copy or product.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Progress through stages/phases of the creating process (i.e., before [pre-], during [drafting], and after [revising] presenting) as needed.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use several strategies before, during, and after representing, speaking, and writing including:</p>
            <p>Before: consider prompt or find a topic and activate prior knowledge (e.g., consider the variables in the prompt or assignment including purpose, role, audience, topic, and focus)consider purpose and audience (e.g., ask questions to analyze purpose and audience)consider and generate specific ideas and information that might be included (e.g., formulate pertinent questions to explore and develop the topic)consider and choose/adapt a possible form (e.g., consider the best pattern to present ideas including cause and effect, problem/solution, opinion/reason, fact/proof, sharing experience pattern)collect and focus ideas and information (e.g., collect details about the topic and plan how to use them; identify gaps in ideas and information)plan and organize ideas for drafting (mapping and authoring) (e.g., create a pre-writing plan as a guide; consider alternative ways to organize and present ideas)consider qualities of effective communication and the language to use (e.g., consider the best register and point of view to use).</p>
            <p>During: create draft(s) and experiment with possible product(s) (e.g., develop main idea with sufficient supporting detail; change any ideas that are not clear or complete)confer with others (e.g., use a peer response sheet)use language and its conventions to construct message (e.g., attend to the tone and sincerity; communicate in a way that sounds informative and confident)reflect, clarify, self-monitor, self-correct, and use a variety of “fix-up” strategies (e.g., use clear transitions to increase flow and fluency)acknowledge sources (e.g., cite sources )include sufficient detailexperiment with communication features and techniques (e.g., consider elements of style including tone, humour, imagery, and dialogue).</p>
            <p>After: revise for content and meaning (adding, deleting, substituting, and rethinking) (e.g., consider the assumptions and values presented)revise for organization (e.g., check that the text patterns and features are appropriate to the form of representation; review for consistent point of view; include a beginning that attracts the viewer, listener, or reader, a middle part that supports the focus, and a closing that connects everything)revise for sentence structure and flow (e.g., use a variety of sentences that flow smoothly and clearly from one idea to the next)revise for word choice, spelling, and usage (e.g., review and revise writing conventions for intended audience; use vivid verbs, specific subjects, and well-chosen qualifiers)proofread for mechanics and appearance (e.g., check for the rules of punctuation, capitalization, spelling, and usage)confer with peers, teacher, or others (e.g., use pre-determined and/or student-developed criteria for revision; revise with peers’ and others’ responses in mind)polish, practise, and decide how work will be shared and published (e.g., enhance for clarity, correctness, variety, and legibility; use blue or black ink and write neatly; check margins; use easy-to-read fonts)share final product, reflect, consider feedback, and celebrate learning (e.g., use a reflection sheet to think about the product, delivery, and planning for future communications).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.4</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Use pragmatic (e.g., use appropriate language register), textual (e.g., use artistic devices such as figurative language), syntactical (e.g., combine sentences to form compound and complex sentences for variety, interest, and effect), semantic/lexical/ morphological (e.g., use words to capture a particular aspect of meaning), graphophonic (e.g., correctly pronounce words with proper emphasis), and other cues (e.g, arrange and balance words and visuals as well as fonts) to construct and to communicate meaning.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>NOTE: Italicized text refers to those indicators that are emphasized at this grade level.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply consistently the conventions of oral and written language and the conventions of visual and multimedia texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use and apply language cues and conventions to communicate meaning including:</p>
            <p>Pragmatic: Textual: Syntactical: Semantic/Lexical/Morphological: Graphophonic: Other Cues:</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.5</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Create and present a variety of visual and multimedia presentations including an illustrated report, a role play that ends with a tableau, a dramatization, presentation software, a newscast with adequate detail, clarity, and organization to explain (e.g., an important concept), to persuade (e.g., an opinion on an issue, a mini-debate), and to entertain (e.g., a humourous incident).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Explore ideas and express understanding using various forms of representing (e.g., storyboarding, illustrating, role playing, e-mailing, preparing a concept map).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Choose appropriate medium/media to fully explore and extend ideas.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Choose appropriate technology (including digital) to represent understanding and enhance communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Design graphic organizers to demonstrate understanding of ideas and information.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use visuals (e.g., data displays) and other techniques to portray key ideas.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Consider ways to enhance clarity and impact of representations.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Integrate various forms of representing (e.g., music, audio tape, graphic organizer, diagram) to express understanding and to enhance oral and written communications.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with representing in a variety of familiar and unfamiliar forms (e.g., presentation software, dramatization, illustrated report).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use more than one type of media in a presentation.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.6</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Use oral language to interact purposefully, confidently, and respectfully in a variety of situations including one-to-one, small group, and large group discussions (expressing feelings and viewpoints and contributing to group harmony).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Initiate conversation about a range of topics and respond appropriately when others initiate conversation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Engage in dialogue to understand the feelings and viewpoints of others and contribute to group harmony.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language and tone to suit audience, purpose, and situation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use gestures, facial expressions, and visual aids to enhance meaning of talk.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Contribute ideas and information and pose questions in class discussion to gain understanding.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use talk to express and to share feelings, ideas, opinions, and responses in one-to-one, small group, and large group discussions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Give reasons for opinions and points of view.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Summarize main ideas discussed and conclusions drawn.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create and deliver oral responses to texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Deliver a focused, coherent oral presentation that includes an introduction, transitions, a logical body, and an effective conclusion as part of an individual project within a unit.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recite poems, sections of speeches, and dramatic soliloquies using voice modulation, tone, and gestures expressively to enhance the meaning.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Give a dramatic reading of a poem or play excerpt and participate in Reader’s Theatre.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with speaking in formal situations (e.g., mini-debates, meetings).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.7</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Use oral language to effectively express information and ideas of complexity in formal and informal situations (e.g., to debate a point, to participate in a meeting, to give a dramatic reading of a poem or play excerpt).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Initiate conversation about a range of topics and respond appropriately when others initiate conversation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Engage in dialogue to understand the feelings and viewpoints of others and contribute to group harmony.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use language and tone to suit audience, purpose, and situation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use gestures, facial expressions, and visual aids to enhance meaning of talk.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Contribute ideas and information and pose questions in class discussion to gain understanding.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use talk to express and to share feelings, ideas, opinions, and responses in one-to-one, small group, and large group discussions.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Give reasons for opinions and points of view.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Summarize main ideas discussed and conclusions drawn.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create and deliver oral responses to texts.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Deliver a focused, coherent oral presentation that includes an introduction, transitions, a logical body, and an effective conclusion as part of an individual project within a unit.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Recite poems, sections of speeches, and dramatic soliloquies using voice modulation, tone, and gestures expressively to enhance the meaning.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Give a dramatic reading of a poem or play excerpt and participate in Reader’s Theatre.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Experiment with speaking in formal situations (e.g., mini-debates, meetings).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.8</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Write to describe a landscape scene; to narrate a personal story or anecdote and a historical narrative; to explain and inform in a presentation of findings, a biography, a documented research report, and a résumé and covering letter; and to persuade in a mini-debate and a review.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the ability to write effective, coherent multi-paragraph (minimum of 5 paragraphs) narrative, descriptive, expository, and persuasive essays of at least 500 to 800 words using appropriate before, during, and after strategies.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create narrative texts (e.g., story, anecdote, historical narrative) as follows establish a context, plot, and point of viewuse a range of narrative devices (e.g., dialogue, tension, suspense)make the narrative engagingdevelop characterdevelop it systematically leading to a climax or conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create expository, informational, and procedural texts (e.g., presentation of findings, a biography, a documented research report, a résumé and covering letter) as follows: pose relevant questions to limit scope of presentationintroduce the purpose, and define a thesisdevelop topic with important facts, details, examples, and explanations from multiple authoritative sourcesinclude several paragraphs or sections organized in logical sequencesuse transitionsorganize and display information on charts, maps, and graphsoffer conclusion(s).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create descriptive texts (e.g., a landscape scene) as follows: present a clear and colourful picture of the placeinclude sensory details and vivid wordsuse a logical order (e.g., near to far).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create persuasive texts (e.g., mini-debate, a review) as follows: include a well-defined thesis (i.e., one that makes a clear and knowledgeable judgement)provide support by reasons, explanations, and evidencesupport opinion with examples from textpresent a clear organization.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compose original texts (e.g., lyrical and narrative poems, letters, scripts, humourous instructions) using a variety of different literary techniques (e.g., imagery, dialogue, figurative language).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>CC8.9</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Experiment with a variety of text forms (e.g., Reader’s Theatre, role play, humourous instructions, an electronic presentation, a dramatization, a mini-debate) and techniques (e.g., imagery, music, graphics and statistics in a multimedia presentation).</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the ability to write effective, coherent multi-paragraph (minimum of 5 paragraphs) narrative, descriptive, expository, and persuasive essays of at least 500 to 800 words using appropriate before, during, and after strategies.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create narrative texts (e.g., story, anecdote, historical narrative) as follows establish a context, plot, and point of viewuse a range of narrative devices (e.g., dialogue, tension, suspense)make the narrative engagingdevelop characterdevelop it systematically leading to a climax or conclusion.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create expository, informational, and procedural texts (e.g., presentation of findings, a biography, a documented research report, a résumé and covering letter) as follows: pose relevant questions to limit scope of presentationintroduce the purpose, and define a thesisdevelop topic with important facts, details, examples, and explanations from multiple authoritative sourcesinclude several paragraphs or sections organized in logical sequencesuse transitionsorganize and display information on charts, maps, and graphsoffer conclusion(s).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create descriptive texts (e.g., a landscape scene) as follows: present a clear and colourful picture of the placeinclude sensory details and vivid wordsuse a logical order (e.g., near to far).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create persuasive texts (e.g., mini-debate, a review) as follows: include a well-defined thesis (i.e., one that makes a clear and knowledgeable judgement)provide support by reasons, explanations, and evidencesupport opinion with examples from textpresent a clear organization.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compose original texts (e.g., lyrical and narrative poems, letters, scripts, humourous instructions) using a variety of different literary techniques (e.g., imagery, dialogue, figurative language).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
    <goal_section>
      <goal_heading>Assess and Reflect on Language Abilities (AR)</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR8.1</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Use information gathered in self-assessment and teacher’s assessment to develop and work on goals for improving viewing, listening, reading, representing, speaking, and writing.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate the quality of own contributions to group process, and set goals and plans for development.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop and use criteria for evaluating self, goals, and projects.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Appraise own and others’ work to determine the appropriateness of resource choices, language use, organization, and communication forms.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess own and others’ work for clarity, correctness, and variety.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Reflect on and assess viewing, listening, and reading experiences and the strategies selected; use relevant criteria to assess viewing, listening, and reading activities; and set goals for each.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Contribute to and use criteria to self-assess and set goals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and analyze effectiveness of a variety of language strategies and competency level of self as a representer, speaker, and writer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Collect materials for a portfolio or e-portfolio that reflect language achievement in relation to career choices.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>AR8.2</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Appraise own and others’ work for clarity, correctness, and variety.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Evaluate the quality of own contributions to group process, and set goals and plans for development.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop and use criteria for evaluating self, goals, and projects.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Appraise own and others’ work to determine the appropriateness of resource choices, language use, organization, and communication forms.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess own and others’ work for clarity, correctness, and variety.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Reflect on and assess viewing, listening, and reading experiences and the strategies selected; use relevant criteria to assess viewing, listening, and reading activities; and set goals for each.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Contribute to and use criteria to self-assess and set goals.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and analyze effectiveness of a variety of language strategies and competency level of self as a representer, speaker, and writer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Collect materials for a portfolio or e-portfolio that reflect language achievement in relation to career choices.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
  </outcomes>
</curriculum>