<curriculum>
  <pdf>https://www.edonline.sk.ca/bbcswebdav/xid-197592_1</pdf>
  <outcomes>
    <goal_section collapsable="true">
      <goal_heading>Photography 20</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 2B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Capture images that demonstrate advanced camera functions and controls.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: Individual cameras have a variety of different features or different terms for features. Students should become proficient with the capabilities of the available equipment.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select and display tools that can be manipulated (e.g., white balance, histogram, exposure compensation, automatic bracketing).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select and adjust a variety of camera functions when shooting pictures including: metering modes, focus modes and points, frame rates, flash settings (e.g., rear and front curtain sync, manual vs. ttl).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 3B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Utilize and extend skills from Module 3A to capture images of increasing quality and refinement.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a variety of images demonstrating planning, including awareness of aspects such as focus, light manipulation, framing, and the photographic triangle.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a log of camera settings, personal reflections, and knowledge regarding increasing skill level.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Load and unload the storage media from the camera.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 6B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Demonstrate an understanding of selecting various lenses and focal lengths to create a variety of effects on the image.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Illustrate how different lenses affect an image (e.g., fast versus slow, zoom versus prime).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the change in image as a result of using a variety of lenses (e.g., fisheye, wide angle, telephoto).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Understand and illustrate, through providing examples, the concept of how a resulting image is affected by focal length and/or format size.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 11B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Continue to develop proficiency with software to improve digital images.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use curves to adjust brightness, contrast, and colour saturation and tone.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Apply various types of filters when adjusting an image (e.g., sharpening, texturizing, blur, black and white).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use software tools to retouch an image.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 12B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Discuss and reflect on the need for societal standards (e.g., legal, ethical, and community norms, and values) and cultural sensitivity in photography.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Formulate a list of societal standards in relation to issues such as sexism, racism, and homophobia, and support the list with positive media examples.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compose a strategy for inclusion of appropriate content and images reflective of societal standards in personal, class, and school projects and assignments.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and discuss issues regarding posting of images on the web including safety, possible consequences, and permanence of web postings.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 13B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Continue to develop skills using basic image editing software to manipulate photographs for a defined purpose.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate techniques such as retouching, skin correction, contrast, layering, panoramas, stitching, and masking as examples of manipulation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Provide personal and ethical justification for choosing manipulation procedures to enhance an image.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 14</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Develop abilities to critique photographic work as a means of evaluation and self-reflection of personal, peer, and public work.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Research and discuss various aspects of critiquing work (aesthetic and technical merits).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a critique of acquired images produced by self and peers.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Express an opinion based on knowledge of composition, genre, design, style, message, presentation, and target audience.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 15A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Explore and demonstrate a variety of presentation formats that photographers use to display work.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Maintain a personal portfolio reflecting growth in understanding and skills involved in image creation.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compile personal images for display.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a style and venue for a school or public showing.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Practise aspects of presentations such as matting, mounting, and framing.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 16</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Demonstrate skills and processes used by photojournalists.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Investigate and report on what a photojournalist does.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Choose a theme and document an event through the use of images and captions in the style of a photojournalist.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 17</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Develop skills and processes used in commercial photography to promote a product or service.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Critique an existing advertisement on the effectiveness of the photography.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a series of images of various products.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a fictional draft advertisement using an existing campaign or a personal example.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 21A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Recognize how school-based skills development will be used to meet workplace expectations.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: Work Study is used to prepare students for employment through specific skill development within a workplace. The number of work study opportunities is equal to the number of courses available in the curriculum area at the 20 and 30 level.</outcome_note>
        <outcome_note>Note: For more information about implementing work study in schools, see the Work Study Guidelines for the Practical and Applied Arts included in the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook. The training plan for the student should be designed to relate to the outcomes of the course modules chosen in collaboration with the cooperating employer.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Obtain a list of roles and responsibilities of the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Brainstorm factors that may affect workplace performance.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Discuss effective and positive verbal and non-verbal communication in the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop a resumé and portfolio that can be forwarded to a potential employer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Practise effective interview techniques based on established guidelines (e.g., the greeting, the exchange, and the parting).</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 22A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Gain experience in the world of work in the photography industry to make more informed career choices by expanding career research and exploration beyond the classroom.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop an awareness of career opportunities in Saskatchewan and beyond.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Gain an opportunity for the development of entry-level workplace skills that may lead to sustainable employment in the photography industry.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Establish standards of work performance acceptable to the student and employer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and report on essential skills and employability skills as they relate to a work environment.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 23A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Reflect and report on the work experience including but not limited to hours of work, personal relationships, employer expectations, evaluation criteria, and overall personal performance.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Design and participate in an exit interview with the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present a report on the work study experience including aspects such as: expected hours of work, dress code, job description, employer expectations, employer evaluation process, absent and late policies, personal relationships, problem solving, communication.,</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 99B</identifier>
        <outcome_text>Note: The extended study module may be used only once in each 100 hour course. In the Student Data System, record 99A for the first extended study module offered in the course series, and, if needed, 99B for the second and 99C for the third.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Module Overview: Evolving societal and personal needs, advances in technology, and demands to solve current problems require a flexible curriculum that can accommodate new ways and means to support learning in the future. The extended study module is designed to provide schools and teachers with an opportunity to meet current and future demands not provided for in the current modules in the Photography curriculum. This flexibility allows a school or teacher to design one new module per credit to complement or extend the study of the core and optional modules to meet the specific needs of students or the community. The extended study module is designed to extend the content of the pure courses and to offer survey course modules beyond the scope of the available selection of PAA modules. The list of possibilities for topics of study or projects for the extended study module approach is as varied as the imagination of those involved in using the module. The optional extended study module guidelines should be used to strengthen the knowledge, skills, and processes advocated in the Photography curriculum. For more information on the guidelines for the extended study module, see the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
  </outcomes>
</curriculum>