<curriculum>
<pdf>https://www.edonline.sk.ca/bbcswebdav/xid-181860_1</pdf>
  <outcomes>
  
    <goal_section collapsable="true">
      <goal_heading>Welding A30</goal_heading>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 7B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Demonstrate cuts to fit a given template to increase accuracy to within 1⁄16” tolerance.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Complete round and/or curved cuts specified by the instructor.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Complete square and/or rectangular cuts specified by the instructor.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 12A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Select, complete, and assess an approved oxy-acetylene welding project to demonstrate welding proficiency.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Create a drawing and develop a cutting list of materials.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Use organized and practised skills to construct a project using appropriate technical language. Utilize the following guidelines to complete a project:Generate different project ideas, , Plan and manage the project including assessment criteria in consultation with the instructor, , Plan and use drawings with appropriate symbols, , Set a procedural sequence, , Prepare a material list and cost estimate, , Create a timeline, , Determine fabrication techniques, , Cut material and set up in the proper sequence, , Complete each part as specified, , Interpret and follow directions, , Adhere to timelines, , Work cooperatively, , Follow all safety requirements, Follow all handling and storing procedures, Fulfill cleanup and tool maintenance responsibilities, Present the completed project and complete a self-assessment based on the criteria for the project.,</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 20B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Perform intermediate arc welding skills with increasing competency.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: All tacks on vee butts are allowed to be ground and feathered prior to root installation.</outcome_note>
        <outcome_note>Note: All root passes are allowed to be ground prior to fill and cap.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Perform a square butt weld (6010; weld root side, flip and weld face side) capable of successfully passing a bend test.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Perform a 3⁄8” vee butt flat (6010 root, 7018 fill and cap) capable of successfully passing a bend test on root and face.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Perform a 3⁄8” vee butt vertical (6010 root, 7018 fill and cap) capable of successfully passing a bend test on root and face.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Perform a horizontal fillet 10 pass (7018, 7014, or 7024; 10” coupon on ¼” mild steel).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Safely perform bend tests on a variety of welds.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compare and chart personal progress to identify increasing skill.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assess personal technique and results in consultation with the instructor.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 21B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Complete an intermediate approved project with a self-assessment of the specified skills.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Assemble and present a project utilizing skills in planning and management as outlined in Module 21A.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate increasingly proficient fabrication techniques, work skills, and presentation skills.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 22</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Develop and articulate an understanding of the materials and processes used to turn raw materials into commercially useful ferrous compounds.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compare and contrast the production of pig iron, cast iron, wrought iron, and steel.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Summarize the differences between the following furnace types: Bessemer, open hearth, electric, and blast.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Accurately use steel production terminology including hot rolled, cold rolled, cast steels, ferrous metals, non-ferrous metals, and metallurgy.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Examine the differences between high and low carbon steels.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Describe the effects and implications of expansion and contraction of metal.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 25C</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Set up GMAW equipment successfully, including care and maintenance.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate knowledge of GMAW equipment such as nozzle, contact tips, liners, wire rolls, gauges and flow meters, amperage adjustment, and voltage adjustment.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Compare the various types of wire and shielding gases used for GMAW.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Disassemble, clean, and reassemble GMAW welder components.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 27C</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Develop increasing skill using GMAW welding equipment</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: Bridge plates may be used for tacking vee butts together to allow for a fully opened root.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Perform vertical fillets (uphand; ¼”, 3⁄8”, and ½”).</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Perform 3⁄8”vee butt flat (short circuit root, spray fill and cap) capable of successfully passing a bend test on root and face.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 28A</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Complete an assigned or approved project using GMAW equipment.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Select a project through consultation with the instructor.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Utilize skills developed in previous modules to complete a project.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Utilize the following guidelines to complete a project:Generate different project ideas, Plan and manage the project including assessment criteria in consultation with the instructor, Plan and use drawings with appropriate symbols, Set a procedural sequence, Prepare a material list and cost estimate, Create a timeline, Determine fabrication techniques, Cut material and set up in the proper sequence, Complete each part as specified, Interpret and follow directions, Adhere to timelines, Work cooperatively, Follow all safety requirements, Follow all handling and storing procedures, Fulfill cleanup and tool maintenance responsibilities, Present the completed project and complete a self-assessment based on the criteria for the project.,</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 29</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Analyze workplace skills, knowledge, and attitudes that lead to successful employment.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Establish a relationship with others in a workplace or shop setting by clearly defining the roles and using effective communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop a résumé or a skills list to forward to an employer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Determine and practise guidelines used to participate in interviews.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 30</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Integrate classroom learning with work-related experience to develop an awareness of employability skills and workplace expectations.</outcome_text>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Research to gain knowledge of the world of work in the welding industry.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop an awareness of the Employability Skills which would be important to be successful in the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Investigate the Essential Skills and identify which would be most important to a career in welding.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 31B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Recognize how school-based skills development will be used to meet workplace expectations.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: Work Study is used to prepare students for employment through specific skill development within a workplace. The number of work study opportunities is equal to the number of courses available in the curriculum area at the 20 and 30 level.</outcome_note>
        <outcome_note>Note: For more information about implementing work study in schools, see the Work-based Learning Guidelines for the Practical and Applied Arts included in the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook. In collaboration with the cooperating employer, the training plan for the student should be designed to relate to the outcomes of the course modules chosen.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Obtain a list of roles and responsibilities of the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Brainstorm a list of factors which may affect workplace performance.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Discuss effective and positive verbal and non-verbal communication.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop a résumé which can be forwarded to a potential employer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Practise effective interview techniques based on established guidelines including the greeting, the exchange, and the parting.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 32B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Gain experience in the world of work to make more informed choices about careers by expanding the career research and exploration beyond the classroom.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: For more information about implementing work study in schools, see the Work-based Learning Guidelines for the Practical and Applied Arts included in the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook. In collaboration with the cooperating employer, the training plan for the student should be designed to relate to the outcomes of the course modules chosen.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Develop an awareness of career and opportunities in Saskatchewan and possibly other provinces.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Gain an opportunity for the development of entry level workplace skills that may lead to sustainable employment.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Establish standards of work performance acceptable to the student and employer</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Demonstrate the required skills and perform the duties expected by the employer.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Identify and report on essential skills and employability skills as they relate to a work environment.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 33B</identifier>
        <outcome_text labeled="true">Reflect and report on the work experience including but not limited to hours of work, personal relationships, employer expectations, evaluation criteria, and overall personal performance.</outcome_text>
        <outcome_note>Note: For more information about implementing work study in schools, see the Work-based Learning Guidelines for the Practical and Applied Arts included in the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook. In collaboration with the cooperating employer, the training plan for the student should be designed to relate to the outcomes of the course modules chosen.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Design and participate in an exit interview with the workplace.</p>
          </indicator>
          <indicator>
            <p>Prepare and present a report on the work study experience including aspects such as:Expected hours of work, Dress code and personal protective equipment (PPE), Job description, Employer expectations, Absence and late policies, Problem solving, Communication.,</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <identifier>Module 99 B</identifier>
        <outcome_note>Note: The extended study module may be used only once in each 100 hour course. In the Student Data System record 99A for the first extended study module offered in the course series and, if needed, 99B for the second, 99C for the third, and 99D for the fourth.</outcome_note>
        <indicators>
          <indicator>
            <p>Module Overview: Evolving societal and personal needs, advances in technology, and demands to solve current problems require a flexible curriculum that can accommodate new ways and means to support learning in the future. The extended study module is designed to provide schools and teachers with an opportunity to meet current and future demands not provided for in current modules of the PAA curriculum. This flexibility allows a school or teacher to design one new module per credit to complement or extend the study of the core and optional modules to meet the specific needs of students or the community. The extended study module is designed to extend the content of the pure courses and to offer survey course modules beyond the scope of the available selection of PAA modules, either in depth or breadth. The list of possibilities for topics of study or projects for the extended study module approach is as varied as the imagination of those involved in using the module. The extended study module guidelines should be used to strengthen the knowledge, skills, and processes advocated in the PAA curriculum. For more information on the guidelines for the Extended Study module, see the Practical and Applied Arts Handbook.</p>
          </indicator>
        </indicators>
      </outcome>
    </goal_section>
  </outcomes>
</curriculum>